<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (very) critical of the changes that are taking place in the art world, and artist-centred activity in the field has to be constantly (very) conscious of these. biennials can and should be creative, and their opportunistic social functions have to be creative as well. The social function of the biennial is to offer a platform for the emergence of new ideas and creative action, and to foster the development of old. It is an arena in which artists can find common ground in challenging assumptions and prejudices, challenging systems, and in developing new creative strategies. It is an arena in which the arts are actively engaged in a dynamic and ever-ongoing way, and where the biennial’s own social function and cultural values are constantly being challenged and updated. The question is: what kind of arena can this be? If the biennial needs to be constantly (very) conscious of the social and political situations that it is thrust into, then it will naturally evolve into something more</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)developed in order to meet the needs of the communities that frequent it. Art needs to be continually (re)educated in order to be able to engage new people, and to survive in the long run. New forms of art need to be constantly (re)created in order to be able to meet the needs of the communities that frequent it in the future. New media and apps need to be developed in order to map the biennial experience and to continue to be able to support artists in their work in the future.  art needs to be continually (re)invented, and new social functions need to be created. Obviously, this kind of social change will only come about through the empowerment of artists and the dissemination of knowledge, and through the empowerment of the local (and particularly the local artists) themselves. However, the capacities of artists to create social change need to be continuously (re)educated in order to be able to contribute to the long-term viability of the project</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (very carefully) appraised in order to stay relevant and innovative. The social function of the biennial has to be continuously (very conceptually) negotiated, and a key element in this is the need to negotiate the social needs and agendas of the local communities. Creative forms of cultural consumption have to be developed in consultation with, and in some cases, with the explicit involvement of, the local communities. This kind of nuance and negotiation is needed in order to truly engage and influence the dynamics and intentions of the local communities. It is a sign of the times, for example, of the huge increase in population growth in the city. It is a sign that the needs of the growing population are no longer confined to the core city core. New urban developments and their inhabitants are everywhere looking for ways to simultaneously feed, clothe, and house all those new arrivals; yet there is still a large gap between the needs of the most vulnerable members of the local communities and the capacities of the artisans and art</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)negotiated, and its social function can only be understood as evolving. The term ‘biennial’ has come to describe a set of activities occurring in the city core over a specified time. It has no fixed definition in English, but it is a familiar one in the biennial calendar. The name comes from the Latin †biennialum’ meaning museum or museum, after the Greek word for chapter. And therein lies the rub. At its inception, the biennial was seen by many artists and arts professionals as a replacement for museums, and by artists and arts professional alike, as a way to make art more accessible and more typical in its settings. It was seen as an accessible form of artistic practice, one suitable for a global urban audience. But with each successive biennial, the biennial itself has increasingly sought to impose its strictures and curatorial agenda on the city in an attempt to determine what counts as beautiful and valuable in an urban setting and how</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)imagined, and art needs to be regularly (re)imagined too.Art’s social function is to provide a platform on which the social can take place, and events such as the biennial can also provide that. It is a very important and dynamic role. The biennial has become such a dominant and pervasive exhibitionary form in so many cities, and cities are now awash in it. I think the key is that it provides a platform and socialisation toolkit. If it is not provided by the city itself, but is provided by another organisation, then that organisation will inevitably target a specific audience. Meeting after meeting with city councils, cultural organisations, government galleries and the like, and learning from them about art and exhibitionary forms is a constant here, and it shows no signs of stopping. City art is a ‘metainterface’. It is a collection of practices converging on a common topic, but its core mission is different from</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)negotiated in order to survive, and so it is with the  	present and future of art in our times. If art is to have any potential of influencing social change, it needs to be constantly (re)negotiated in order to remain fresh and new and absorb new cultural forms and practices. It is this kind of mutability and change that biennials are expected to handle with care, and which is why they must be transparent, non-profit and non-state funded (since no state is likely to fund or endorse such a programme). If they become too reliant on funding sources outside of the locality (which is precisely what is happening in many parts of the world) then this also reduces the potential of other creative activities to be generated outside of the biennial, and so on. The biennial as a form is expected to grow in power and influence in the future, but this cannot come at the expense of other important functions of art in our world</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)programmed, and art’s social function cannot be assumed to be static. New theories of art’s destiny are needed. Biennials can and should change form, but they are not homogenous. They need to be constantly (re)evaluated, and this can take two forms: (1) as a function of time, and (2) as a function of culture.  The biennial as a cultural form needs to be re-thought, because it’s able to sustain a certain amount of newness. New cultural practices need to be developed, and biennials are a great place to start. However, they are also a place where art can emerge and change form, and where art’s real power really lies. This is very important, because while biennials can (and do) have great power, their real power lies in the form of symbolic acts, and the fact that they are able to fund important projects.</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)negotiated. It needs to be renegotiated with, and through these changes, continually (re)negotiated with. This kind of evolution is very different from the kind of evolution described above, in which the artist creates a work that is static and stands still. This kind of evolution happens much more dynamically, and is described in the reference works that artists, curators, art writers and art’s historical societies keep compiling. These historical works show various iterations of various artists’ various approaches to the same question: what would be the best art form to adopt in a changing world?  The point of these historical works is to tell us what art could be if the art weren’t constrained by a set of categories and socially mediated realities. It is to show us the fluid forms that art can take in and outside of the social. It is to show us that art can and will evolve. In short, these historical works show different versions of the same question</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)evaluated, and its social function can no longer be taken for granted.  There are currently around 200 biennials operating in over 50 countries. Of these, around half are located in North America and the other half in the Middle East and Africa. Of these, around half are located in the United States.  Biennials have a natural geographic limit – they   cannot go on  indefinitely – but they do have certain other-worldly powers that are usually ascribed to non-biennial forms.  Biennials can therefore be seen as an  exclusive, latecomer, coming-on-after-the-out-of-the-blue kind of thing. They are constantly reinventing themselves, constantly evolving in response to the world around them.  biennials  naturally gravitate towards the things that make the social possible – the things that make us ‘ different’ – and so they are always looking for the next social event to prop up their</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is a good starting point for an important critical discourse. This can be seen as a programme of activities that evolve organically over time, responding to the changing needs and interests of the community. In time, these changes may also include the participation of artists from outside of the project. In this case, the community would provide the art, the artist would provide the social support, the other members of the community would provide the language, and the biennial would provide the social function and engage the community in the important but unseen (to many) ways that are latent in the art form.  The significance of this kind of evolution cannot be understated. It shows that art can be produced in repressive conditions, and that art can change quite a bit in its short existence.  art, on the other hand, is not static. Its social and economic function evolves with it, and with it, inevitably, new forms of social interaction are needed. The biennial as a form needs to be constantly (re)negotiated and modelled on the social. It’s not enough to create a biennial; one also needs to actively engage in the development of the festival, and the art institution as a whole. The organisers of the 2018 Venice Biennale need to think about how the exhibition they created may be shared between various communities. They need to consider how it may or may not be a biennale, and whether it is or is not. And they also need to consider what happens to the art form once it is no longer a biennale.Art is a powerful social tool, and it is this ability to shift and morph that the biennial exhibits are trying to instill in their audiences. And although the art exhibits themselves may or may not represent the art that is happening in the world as a whole, their ability to imagine what the art could be – and does become – is a much more powerful tool. But this only works if people are willing to line</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone new, and I’m going to walk into a big window and be like, ‘That’s not going to happen here.’But then the next day, I’m out on a Champs-Ely riding my bike, and the whole city is asleep.‘It’s as if the Biennial’s form of documenta 14 had been planned in such a way as to last for hundreds of years.  	There’s a relationship between the Biennial and the museum, but the museum is still the locus of the artefacts found at the Biennial sites. The museum will reproduce and rediscover the narratives found at the biennial sites, but it will also, over the long term, become embedded in the urban fabric of the city, as it continues to operate as an artefact of the city. As the Biennial itself acknowledges, this is only</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone, and I’m going to ask her to introduce me to a local artist for the biennial, and she’ll introduce me to an artist she worked with in Rio who’s doing a residency in the same city. And the biennial is like a mini-institution, and the mini-institution is where the micro-art is made.And the mini-institution is the artworld equivalent of a M.F.A. scholarship. It’s the equivalent of the MFA scholarship, and it’s where art is made that is transient, and works like the Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition, and the Bluecoat/Bluecoat: Art and Art-making in Transition exhibition, and the ongoing residency programme, and it’s also where the philanthropy is made, and the institutions that support it, come from. And so the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone, and I’ll leave this city to meet her. I don’t want to be seen as a recluse, I don’t want to be misunderstood, and I don’t want to upset anyone by coming into a big city and not being part of a community. So it’s a decision that has to be advised carefully. Tomorrow, if I’m not in the right place at the right time, someone may have a plan for me to execute. And tomorrow, if that plan comes to be realised, it’s going to be a disaster. Today, it’s not a disaster, but it is still a crucial moment in the city’s history, and it’s going to be very interesting to see what happens when we encounter the disaster that is about to happen. 	In the event that we do encounter the  	end of history, which seems to be</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone new, and I’m going to take the opportunity to explore this strange, beautiful city. And I’m going to discover something new every time. But what  	is different about this city than the rest of the world, or the United States, is that this city’s architecture is made up of stories. There’s a reason why the Twin Towers metabolized in 9/11, and why so many skyscrapers in New York are designed to collapse – because this is the city that’s always telling a story. Every story is a myth, but the city’s built environment tells a larger fiction, so we get a sense of the mythic qualities of the city. It’s as if the Biennale is telling a fictional story. 	[Translation of an interview with Gabrielle Roy, Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone from the Atangana family, and I’m going to ask them, ‘What did you do for fun in your free time?’ And they’ll give me  	a list of questions, and then they’ll be able to answer it.And there’s a very good chance that the questions they’ll give me will be the wrong ones, and I’ll end up somewhere like Doha, where questions are hypothetical and answers are predetermined. 	So, is there a way to engage with such a situation constructively? Yes, there is. And I would start by asking whether the questions are hypothetical or not. Because if they’re hypothetical, then there’s a good chance that the person asking the question has already been trapped in a rut for a long period of time. And if they’re not trapped in a rut, then there’s</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone, and  	we’re both going to feel that we need to stop and digest some kind of wound up, in order to continue on our journey, because we’re both so battered. And so it’s that window’s being made somehow bigger than the rest of the city, and this is what’s happening in DC: artist-centred, high-end-funded art is being created at these levels because people who are already artists’ patrons are willing to spend $100,000+ on a piece of art that they hope will be exhibited in a major art museum, or a private institution. And so a city is being fugitive of its resources, and art is being fugitive as well. 	So the window-smasher is this idea that the biennial is a potential way to generate revenue for a city, or that the biennial can</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone from the Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition. 	I’m imagining things, but I’m not actually envisioning anything. 	I’m imagining a different kind of world, where people are free to live their lives and create their futures. It’s a world where buildings are empty and unused, and streets are empty and dangerous. 	I’m picturing a different kind of community, one where people don’t have to choose between being around family and being around a place where violence, drugs and a mess of other problems occur. 	I’m imagining a different kind of city, where people don’t have to choose between being near beautiful art and being around factories that spew toxic waste into the surrounding community. 	I’m picturing a different kind of city, where people don’t have to choose between being comfortable and</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone from the Atangana family, and we’ll do a documentary on the window (since the family has already done one), one of the first things we’ll do is take the family skiing in the window, and we’ll show them the window craft that they’ve done. Then we’ll show them how the window was made, and how the family saw fit to keep it that way. How they used salvaged materials and what they purchased; the value of which we will never know.  	And then we  	will do something completely different, and something that creates awareness of the project. For me, it’s not just about what we learn from the project, but how we learn it. And so the idea of the documentary was created, and the ethos of the documentary was formed in the family home. It was </text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet someone who’s in the middle of this process of letting go, and we’ll do a year in this city, and we’ll be called ‘discoveries’ – discoveries made by the biennial that reflect the lived history of the city, that allow the biennial to inhabit the city in new ways.The discovery of a biennial can be a powerful and mysterious force. I had no idea that the Architecture Biennial was going to be a museum. I never thought it would be a biennial, and I never imagined that it would be a museum. I never imagined it would be a space for public art or a place for cultural exchange or a place of education or a place of information or a place of knowledge.Architecture Biennial 2018, Ll Series, Photo courtesy of Nina Edge. If that’s possible, the definition of what is possible in terms of space</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist, activist and writer Daphne Atangana. The exhibition was an exploration of the ways in which art can work with communities – from creating opportunities for communities to accomplish their everyday activities through working with communities to creating new ways of working with them.The Atangana-Marija Cetinicos Design Process exhibition continued through September 2018.Daphne Atangana: The Biennial as a Documentary Experience Gabrielle Roy 	I’m walking down the street and seeing these huge windows that showsto a city, and I’m like, ‘That's not going to happen here.’ The answer is ‘No, it can't.’ And the reason is  because  	this city is 	dwelling, and it’s time to let go. One day I’m going to meet a community leader, and we’ll be walking through the different ways in which the biennial can and should reside – in a specific neighbourhood, in a particular city. The way I imagine it will be is like this: the owner of the biennial will decide where to place it, and we will all be walking through different possibilities. 	So every day, I will present a different way of living, creating, working with the biennial in a specific neighbourhood. This will be the space and time to assist in the making of this space and time, and to think, ‘As community members, how can we create something here?’ This will be my model of collaboration, as opposed to the hierarchical, managerial variety. The key is that we build from the bottom up; we don’t create what the other person wants, and we don’t ask for what we don’t deserve. This is how communities become their own</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. 	[3] See Kierkegaard’s Essays on the Genealogy of Morals and Legislation (1789), chapter 8, ‘Of Works and Not of Man’. 	[4] Kierkegaard, Essays on the Genealogy of Morals and Legislation 1789, 1790. 	[5] Kelvin, Thinking the Big Picture, p. 113. 	[6] Karen Bowden, ‘Carrots and Vegetables: practices and concepts for a class project exploring the cultural impacts of action in the public realm’, in  	Environment, Vol. 27, No. 1, March,  April, 1987, p.335. 	[7] Bowden, ‘Cultural Capital: the social capital of cities’, in  	Environment, Vol. 27, No</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. 	[3] John Berger, ed., The Contemporary Condition: On the Present and the Pasture (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1994), p. 8. 	[4] John Berger, The Contemporary Condition: On the Politics of Embraced Cultural Capital (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2001), p. 12. 	[5] John Berger, The Contemporary Condition: On the Public and the Publics (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2002), p. 8.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is the Curator of Public Practice at MIMO, New York, where she has worked since 2012. Her work incorporates a range of artistic practices including fine arts, spectacles, public engagements, film and video, public programming, and online exhibition making. Her exhibition, Becoming MIMO Curator, will be presented in the MIMO</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. Arendt is typically characterised as thinking much of the West, and particularly of Western liberal democratic values. But she also recognises significant sections of Eastern traditions, such as those of Islam. Arendt’s Jewish audience, however, is not so easily divisible into two-thirds Jew and one-third non-Jew. Jewish audiences in general are precious to scholars, and it is not like Arendt would have to say in advance that she wanted one group to understand the other.[3] See, for example, Mitchell, The Culture of Critique, p. 8. 	[4] Mitchell, The Culture of Critique, p. 37. 	[5] Waugh, On Criticism and Culture, p. 38.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an assistant professor in English and General Education at Mount Royal University in Calgary,</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. Arendt’s book is about the relationship between modernity and modernism, but there is some very different ways of reading that relationship. Arendt sees a moment in the history of which is characterized by great changes and upheavals that created culture as a new kind of temporality that was distinct from everything that preceded it, which is to say, culture could be considered both 'a resource and a constitutive element of the social' (p. 203). Modernity is a historical term, and while arendt’s concept of modernity is subject to change, her historical concept of modernity is not. Modernity is a historical term, and while arendt’s concept of modernity is subject to change, her historical concept of modernity is not.6. Satish Kanady ‘The Rise of Cities: Money, Power and the Coming Climate Crisis’, in  	Cities and Memory, ed.</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. 	[3] See Ronald Keefe and Michael Lerner’s Cities in Crisis: The Rise of Downtown and the Fall of MWC (DLA, 2015), p. 8. 	[4] See Keefe and Lerner, op. cit., p. 15. 	[5] See Keefe and Lerner, op. cit., p. 16. Download this article as PDFRyan AventRyan Avent is an assistant professor in The College of Architecture and Design at Northern Illinois University, where he works in the Division of Exhibitionary Arts. His research interests include the construction and history of urban infrastructure, urban and regional planning, and exhibitionary culture. His thesis, 'On the Construction of Contemporary Urban Infrastructure: Lessons from the Twentieth-Century Perspective'9 involves the infrastructure of Cork, Ireland, in the construction of a city ‘reclaimed by the self’ through a process</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. 	[3] For a more detailed account of the dialectic of enlightenment, see Svetlana Boym, The Ecology of Enlightened Civilization (Chicago/Wiley, 2015), chapter ‘Empire of Uncertainty’. 	[4] For an in-depth but rich survey, see Sarah Lowdnes, The Language of Empire: Language as a Form of Political Agency (Oxford, 2015), chapter ‘Empire of Uncertainty’. 	[5] See Ewan MacAskill, ed., Songs of Empire: The Pearl of Guile: Essays on the Symbolic Character of Empire (Cambridge, Mass., 2015), p. 89.  1  John A. Church and Neil J. White, eds., The Collected Poems of Ewan MacAskill (New York, 1980), p. 35.  2  John A.</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. Arendt’s book is subtitled Politics and Documents. It is the only work of art to be published in English from 1948 to 1973, the year Israel was created. It is the only book in English that deals explicitly with the role of the Holocaust in the making of the modern state. It was first published in 1949; see Svetlana Boym, Understanding History (New York: Vintage Books, 1991), p. 2. 	[3] See Pavlina Boym and Nadine Gordimer’s Culture and Anarchy, published in 1984, for a critical study of the Holocaust in contemporary culture. 	[4] See Michael Ames and Allan Sekula’s The Culture Trap: Mass Deception in Contemporary Art and Design (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1999), p. 18. 	[5] Ames and Sekula’s, op. cit., p</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times.  	[3] See, for example, Peter Osborne and Christian Körner, eds.,  	Post-Apocalyptic Future (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016), p. 12. 	[4] John Berger,  	Post-Apocalyptic Literature (New York: Oxford University Press, 2019), p. 131. 	[5] George Saunders,  	The Third Eye (Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 1978), p. xiv.Download this article as PDFPeter Carroll, Writer in Residence in the Department of Anthropology at the University of Alberta, Canada, attended the 2014 ADM International Conference on Literary and Cultural Theory, and is currently completing a three-year postgraduate research project at the University of Alberta Libraries. His dissertation examines the European notion of historiography as distinct from North American and Arab historiography, in order to offer insight into the political and ideological under</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times.6 	[3] See Emmanuelle L.P. Mandelstam’s The Culture of Critique: Social Criticism in Contemporary Art, 1988.7 	[4] See Peter Brook’s Culture and Criticism, ed. Susanne Kurtz and Peter Brook, Routledge, London (2011), p. 40. 	[5] See John Berger’s Culture and Criticism, 2nd ed., Routledge, London (2012), p. 29. 9 	[6] See Todd Starnes’s book Culture and Capitalism: Money, Cultures of Criticism and Postmodernism, Oxford University Press, Oxford (1995), p. 2. 	[7] See John Berger’s Culture and Criticism, 2nd ed., Routledge, London (2012), p. 29. 	</text>
    <text>might not be curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, who have been thinking about how to make cultural practice relevant to the world around it.  	Instead, cultural institutions might be set up to engage with and learn from, and maybe even collaborate with, local communities in a way that reflects, in the words of the Turner Prize winner Joasia Krysa, 'a sense of co-responsibility and responsibility arising from the combined power of many different people, organisations and forces'.5 Such collaboration – a kind of cultural jungle, where people gather not for mutual benefit but for the common good – is the contemporary condition, and it is time to change that. 	[1] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Cultural Capital of the Future City (MIT/Berkeley, 2015), p. 19. 	[2] See Hannah Arendt’s Dialectic of Enlightenment, which I have quoted at length several times. 	[3] See Robin Mackay: Cultural Capital (New York, 2008), pp. 446–65; Ray Dalio: ‘Economic Estrangement: From Criticism to Policy Decisions’, (2012) 12/13, p. 4. 	[4] Tom Withers, ‘Inhabitants of America: The Legacy of Mining and Banking in the Urban Frontier’ (2014) in  	Cities for Creative Resistance, 2015, vol. 1, pp. 1–18. 	[5] Andrew Gelman, ‘Urban Form and Its Emissions’ (2014) in  	Cities for Creative Resistance, 2015, vol. 1, pp. 1–25. 	[6] Environment News Service,  	Summary Report, 2014, U.K. &amp; Environment Agency, ‘UK's Energy Future: Toward</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social than in the socials objects that shape those objects. The chief socialisers of the modern economy were the artisans and the artisans themselves. Art became a social commodity, and the social function of art became entwined with the service industry – organising labour and resources, transporting raw materials and images across the globe, and then (in turn) allocating those resources to meet individual clients. Art has always been a social practice, and will always be so. And yet we are increasingly aware that social functions are only ever performed by a privileged elite. We need more than that. We need to actively engage with the world around us in order to create social situations. And yet, how can we do this? There are many ways to get started: going to exhibitions, joining a community arts organisation, starting a blog, joining a social enterprise, becoming a board member of an art school, becoming a volunteer with the Montreal Art Festival, becoming an organiser of the Canada 150, etc. But</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world created by those objects. When Carraway and co-workers in Liverpool created the blueprint for the Liverpool Biennial, they were not making art – they were making a social world based around maps and directories. Social whole, that is, the objects of the social world they inhabit, made their presence felt in a particular location. And that is precisely what Carraway and co-workers did not intend. Their work was not an image of the world as a collection of images, or even an image of the world as a collection of objects. Rather, Carraway and co-workers’ world was made up of images of people, places, habits and routines. Images of food and drink and places to have a meal, and images of shopping and entertainment. Images of art and venues for performing arts. Such images act as registers of the social world existing somewhere, and are able to trace its origins to a particular point in time. Such images also act</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social relations that enable the basis of the social world to exist at all. Art is a social formation; it is both the social occasion and the social occasion alone that can generate a social  1 	system. [3] See, for example, S. Dergum &amp; M. Kriegel, eds.,  	Relationscapes: Art and Architecture in an Age of Metainterfaces (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2015), p. 12. 2  The ‘metainterface’ is a computer interface that seeks to reconcile the conflicting interests of users with the fact that information flows across a great number of platforms at once. It is an interface that neither seeks nor conceals information, but relays information as different protocols interact with each other. 	[4] Apple, 1984. 	[5] Erving Goffman, The Goffman File (New York: Macmillan,</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world created by those objects. The objects that form the basis of the social world are not passive instruments waiting to be used, but conscious and intelligent agents capable of developing and constituting their own uses and desires. We are interested in the ways in which the social world can be modified through the act of creating and constituting means. 	[3] And thus the biennial becomes transformative in its own way, creating what Royce W. Smith calls ‘a differentiated set of relations between people’s present and future needs, which may or may not be met by the means […] but aim to create or reconceive means existing in the present’. 	[4] And as we have seen, future needs are modified through the act of making and constituting means. As a curatorial exercise, the Biennale’s curatorial language of ‘present-day needs’ is itself a creation of future needs. As</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world produced by the objects that form its basis. The modern urban environment is made up of thousands of fragments scattered across numerous jurisdictions, many of them disconnected and disconnected from one another. Each city is a collection of fragments, and our efforts to inhabit them all are efforts to inhabit only a part of the world; we are not looking for an idealized ‘world view’, but for the bare essentials of what the modern city entails. And while idealized, the world we inhabit is not  	perfect; there are ways of looking at the world that are not captured and expressed in the virtual images we create. And while we might strive to create an idealized world in the image of the city, we are not looking for idealized images of the world; we are looking for images that accurately depict the world as it is. The quest for image-comparison, or image-identity, is part of the contemporary urban environment. If we</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world itself. The city represents a particular combination of characteristics: a large number of people, a dense and transient population, a volatile economy, a history of social struggles, and an ever-expanding range of public services and bureaucracies. As Michael Hudson observes, though, the city is also ‘a creation of the state’, and ‘an inevitable by-product of its own activity: working out rules, regulations, alliances, and allegiances’. Hudson,  	New York Times, 7 October 2015, http://www.nytimes.com/2015/10/07/us/politics/stephen-c-cameron-for-the-race-2014-edition.html?,referer='http://www.nytimes.com/politics/stephen-c-ameron-for-the-race-2014-edition.html?_r=0&amp;oref=t1&amp;</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world formed by those objects. The story of how an image first entered a social context is the story of how the image affects change within that context. 	[3] And while it is true that the culture industry is highly individualised, there is a way in which the social world we inhabit is also influenced by the specific images we produce and consume. There is a way in which the social world we create through images is also influenced by the individual images that are produced and consumed.  	[4] For example, as Jon Kabat suggests, images of art are often used as currency within contemporary artworlds; indeed, Kabat has argued that the contemporary art market is largely influenced by the image market.[5] 	[6] And this is not just an aesthetic judgement; as Kabat sees it, we are all avid readers of contemporary art and literature, and images circulate all around us on a regular basis; we are</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social worlds that are constituted by those objects. Social life emerges from the socialising of the social. And though the mechanisms of the social world may change, their composition necessarily involves changes too.  	[3] More to the point, the social world may change in unpredictable ways – radically – so that social life remains fundamentally oriented around the objects that are the very form of social life itself.  	[4] This is the condition that objectification imposes in the dynamic relation between worker and machine.  	[5] As early as the 1920s, critics were warning of a creeping nepotism that was oppressing workers – capitalists – through the proliferation of corporate parent-company structures. More recently, thanks to the explosive growth of finance capital, we are seeing the emergence of what sociologist Eran Schragtlinger terms ‘a parasitic culture of work’ that is both global and deeply embedded in the planet. 	</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social world in which those objects form the basis of the social world. The aesthetic is an essential aspect of the social world, but the social world is aestheticised through means of aestheticising. Art has a particular character and role in the social world, and though we might admire and value certain art that is aesthetically simple and direct, we should be able to recognise more complex and artistic art that is not. The problem with the machine, as we all know, is that it is always overtaken by more familiar ways of doing things. 	[3] The key to understanding  	machine art is to understand the ways in which those who possess the technology are able to shape what is seen as aesthetically pleasing in the world through their control mechanisms. Art has a character as well as an effect, and though the former is primary, its impact is secondary within the larger scheme of things. 	[4] Aesthetics is ultimately understood through the</text>
    <text>a machine curated around the values of its owners, and their families, the community of residents and shop stewards, the journalists, artists, and residents who gathered to hear from, and comment on, the wares displayed, the decoration, the programme, the interior design –  	and yet no further. The narrative shifts from the community, to the maker, to the curators, to the media, to the city. And though the changes in the machine are subtle and long-term, there is an impulse ‘to this day’ that suggests a certain amount of independence and autonomy within the system, and an awareness of the fact that it is an image of commerce that is the foundation of the city’s social life. In other words, the  	machine is not a perfect representation of the social world, but it is a social creation nonetheless. 	[2] In the end, though, we are less interested in the objects that form the basis of the social world than in the social relations that shape that world. The interest of the artist is in radically distorting conceptions of social existence so as to disclose aspects of hidden life that are oppressive and dehumanising. In the case of the Liverpool Biennial, the object that emerged as a result of the Biennial’s curatorial and development process was not a specific image of the artist but an ongoing series of simple markers, some of which were quite beautiful, some of which were quite hideous, and some of which were both pretty and really really really really really really really ugly. The beauty of the thing was in its simplicity: it was just a bunch of stones. The hideousness came from the context in which it was found: the context of the poverty and homelessness and deprivation that characterises many parts of the world, especially the developing world, and the racism, Islamophobia and anti-Semitism that characterise that world. The beauty of the thing was in its surface: it was a beautiful stone</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Activism in Central America (New York: Vintage, 2015), p.37. 	References in Terry Smith, How to Be Artists (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1988) and Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Activism in Central America  (New York: Vintage, 1987). 2Up 2Down, The Biennial Generation, 2002. Image courtesy of Tom Leckey. 3 This essay is based on a talk given by Nadine Attewell, Curator for Transport and Culture at the National Gallery of Canada, to commemorate the biennial's ten-year anniversary. 4 The idea that art should be freely available in a city came as a surprise to many in the 1990s. Even those with a curatorial or artistic background in art generally understand the importance of staging locations, sites and props in creating an experience of art in a city. 5 In a 1987 </text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art in Derry 1952, and Michael Ames, Radical History: The U.S. Art Intercourse with Power in Derry 1952.  1  Jan Montefiore criticizes the predominant historical and archival interest in the role of the arts in the United States as a result of the New Deal and the Great Society. He sees an increasing demand for art, and the emergence of a critical mass of artists committed to exploring their artistic potentialities outside of the social context of institutional patronage. He also sees a shift towards an increasingly privatized cultural capitalism, in which art is often touted as a panacea while neoliberalism, which is often cited as a solution to the economic crisis, is often cited as a promoter. He is the author of several books including the best-known Being Mortal: Race, Capitalism, Art and the Politics of Empowerment today.  2  Montefiore criticizes the dominant historical and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Participatory Arts (Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1993), p.37. Download this article as PDFPatrick GeddesPatrick Geddes is an art historian and the Editor-at-Large of The Art Newspaper. His work has addressed topics relating to the contemporary art of being alive in a changing urban environment, from the 1970s counterculture of Birmingham to the explosion of artist-organisations in the 1990s, and the subsequent imprisonment and slaughter of hundreds of activists, many of whom were later executed. In 2011, he edited The Art Newspaper – Volume 2: The Art Newspaper Since 1972 (2011) – a collection of essays on topics relating to the history of the journal to coincide with the publication of Volume 2 of the book). Recent publications include: ‘In a free society, citizens have the right to know: today, at the United Nations, Jerusalem, and Guantánamo’s Island, where American soldiers detain and torture prisoners (</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art (2009).  13 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art (2009).  14 	See Roland Meehan, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art (2009).  15 	See Laura Raicovich,  	Becoming Art: On the Limits of Embarrassment-Free Art (Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore and London, 2012) and Michelle Dezember,  	The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art (Routledge, New York and London, 2003). 16 	See John Urry,  	The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art (Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992), p.1  1  &quot;There is no such thing as a Community Arts Centre’,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Social Action from Slavery to Today. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2005. 	Download this article as PDFTerry SmithTerry Smith is Professor of Community Arts and Head of the Department of the Arts and Humanities at the Woodbridge Centre for Sustainable Art, which addresses the politics of community arts and design in a regional hub. His books include the popular social histories of vernacular urbanism, the rise of ‎Community Arts, the 1999 publication of which was co-edited with Graham Turner and includes essays on the work of the Arts Council, the Biennial, the Littlewood Art Biennial, the HMR research project and on the Chronicle website. His work has been commissioned by the Forestry Commission, the Great Ormond Street Hospital, Worcester Forest, Bluecoat, Tate Modern, Peter and Paul MacConnal (eds.), Woodbridge Biennial, 2000, and Dolphin Arts, London and New York. He has written for the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Activism (New York: W.W. Norton &amp; Company,1990), p. 33.  9   David Harvey, ‘On Writing and the Cinema’, in Curtis Maddox &amp; Sarah Carter, ed., The Complete Reader (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2018), p. 84.  10  Harvey, 'On Writing’, p. 84.  11  Harvey, ‘The Cinema and Everyday Life’, in Curtis Maddox &amp; Sarah Carter, ed., The Complete Reader (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2018), p. 84.  12  Gould, ‘The Cinema and Everyday Life: An Introduction to Cinema Studies’, in David Harvey, ed., Cinema Studies (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 2000), p. 20.  13  Gould,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art's Role in the Public. 	, Beacon Press, New York, 2012, p.xii. 	Also see his book The Public Enemy: The Rise and Fall of an Imaginary Friend, Rodale Press, New York, 2011. 	Download this article as PDFTerry SmithTerry Smith is a writer, curator, journalist and researcher. He has written about avant-garde art for the New York Times, The Guardian, The Nation, The New Republic, The Nation, The New York Times and The Village Voice. He is the curator of the New York Public Art Biennial, New York, and the author of The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art’s Role in the Public, forthcoming from Routledge, 2015. His latest book is Being Governed: Governmental Capture and Control in Twenty-First Century America, forthcoming from Verso, 2016.He is Senior Editor of Being</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Activism in the Context of Art and Cultural Studies, University of Illinois Press, Chicago, 2003, p.19.Download this article as PDFTerry SmithTerry Smith is an artist, writer, and critic. He is Professor in the Department of the Arts and Social Life of the College of Architecture and Design at the City University of New York, and he is the author, with Peter Hermann, of the forthcoming book *Being Governed: Art as Governance, State and Capital in a Global Context. His latest work, *Being Governed: Art and Capital in the Recent Twentieth Century’s Neo-Contemporary Context, was presented at the Venice Biennale as An Occupy Event. He is a Fellow of the American Centre for a while, and the American Institute of Architects. He has written for the New Inquiry, The New Inquiry International, and Socialist Register. He is a member of the New York Public Theater. His art has been exhibited at</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art's Role in Public Space, Wiley Black &amp; Decker, New York, 1999. 12  For more on the role of the community arts in creating and sustaining freedom, see Rebecca Roache, The Rise of Creative Cities: Art, Creativity, and the Metainterface, Wiley Black &amp; Decker, New York, 2002. 13  The Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Download this article as PDFRebecca RoacheRebecca Roache is Professor in the Department of English and Film Studies at the Rotman School of Art, University of Toronto and holds a joint appointment with the Royal College of Art. Her research interests include the history of Community Arts practices in Canada and the United States and their evolution in the context of postcolonial/third world countries; the politics of creative class identity and the politics</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, Suspended in the Balance. 9 This proposal was not without friction, for some of the artists concerned with the proposed museum were emboldened by the prospect of a curatorial presence in their community, while others found the plan itself repellent. Nevertheless, the curatorial movement gained strength in response to the Chronicle’s position on the Ch’ol Performatico, and it is this tension that will remain with us through to the present. 10 It is not clear how much of the initial proposal was based on actual experience of a Community Arts project, and how much on literary devices: the actor is the reader, and the reader is the actor. Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	Reading the Community Arts Reader, 2002. 271 p.11 	See also Terry Smith, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Art and Social Development in Transition, How to Read a Book, DAW Books, New York, 1982, pp.226–29.Download this article as PDFTerry SmithTerry Smith is an artist, writer, and researcher. He is currently Curator of the Canadian Pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and is the Artistic Director of the Biennale as a Public Platform, London, UK. His art and research work has been exhibited worldwide including at the Venice Biennale, Tate Britain, and the Keele Gallery, New York, where he was curator of public programs. His writing has been published in numerous periodicals, journals, and books including Being Against the Grain: Critical Art and Cultural Studies in the Twentieth Century (with Rebecca Stott White), Writing and Unwriting Media Art: Essays on Cultural Fragility, Cynthia Ellis and Neil Johnson, Arnold M. Palmer, Ed., The Contemporary Art Press: Art from the Turn of the Millennium</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision 
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 10. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant collision in 1991; 11. The G8 earthquake and tsunami in 1991; 12. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1991; 13. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1991; 14. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant collision in 1991; 15. The G8 earthquake and tsunami in 1991; 16. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant collision in 1991;  17. The oil spill in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991.  Download this article as PDFRay Brook RimmerRay Brook is an artist. His current projects include the National Park Service, Sitecancer, and the Hadley Center for Radiological Research at MIT. Brook is a pioneer in the use of remote sensing to monitor and map resource-rich regions. He is the discoverer of Legionnaires</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 10. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 11. The laung  	Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 12. The laung  	Gulf oil spills in 1991; and  13. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986. 	(1) National Park Service, National Park Map, Oil Spill, 2000. (2) National Park Service, Natural Resource Damage Assessment (NREA), Damage Assessment – Mistaken For Fact, 2000. (3) National Park Service, Natural Resources Damage Assessment (NREA), Damage Assessment – Mistaken For Fact, 2001. 	(4) National Park Service, National Park Map, Oil Spill, 2000. (5) National Park Service, Natural Resources Damage Assessment (NREA), Damage Assessment – Mistaken For Fact, 2000. (6) National</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 10. The Chernobyl nuclear power station collision in 1991. 	The ‘face of things to come’ is the wave crashing against the reef, as it were. 	The art project, commissioned by the Liverpool Biennial and  The Royal Academy of Arts, was a response to events in Venice, including the Chernobyl disaster and the closure of the Dai Okwui Ngur Ngur dam, which would have combined the twin estuaries with one of the world’s largest oil storage tanks. The project was part of a wider exhibitionary program at Chisenhale in London including an exhibition of Japanese art in the site of the nuclear power plant. The ‘face of things to come’ bid to reconcile the divergent histories of history, art, and contemporary art. 	The wave crashing against the reef was a combination of technical and human error,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Brent oil rig collision in 1990; and  11. The Bess of Hill in the Gulf of Thailand, 1990. Photo courtesy of Johan Pavlov.  A few years later, another of Hadley’s works, this time Waterboys in Paradise, was developed and exhibited in New York City, at the Gulfstream Park site in Los Angeles. The work, produced in collaboration with the Gulfstream Park developers, was designed to coincide with the 90th International Aquatic Exhibition, but with the LA Pavlov Museum’s, the two works combining forms, evocation and occasion.  The text included a comment from a photographer Francis Lester, who captured the scene for a 1977 book The Gulf Connection. Lester recorded the following about the Gulf Stream Station One hundred and</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant collision in 1990; 11. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 12. The national parks in California being razed to make way for giant residential areas, Palenque National Park and the Gulf of Thailand became the poster children of the decimation of nature in the name of sprawl.  The proliferation of such places around the globe coincided with the growth of populations, which in turn increased the demand for more food and fuels.  As a consequence, the size of the planting beds within the park increased, while the area enclosed by the fences also increased. The combination of the two factors that allowed ‘wildlife hotels’ to emerge as a major force in the postwar period was a major factor in the subsequent expansion of industrial tourism.  The development of infrastructure and the mechanisation of landscapes created ‘tourism destinations’, which</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 10. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1991.  The exhibition was then shown in the Gulf Coast center, at the Chi†’An Mandaloy Visitor Center. I was in high school in the early sixties, and my recollection is of a very different kind of youth, one raised in the era of rock and roll. My recollection is of a youth who knew and respected artists such as Jan Jursen, Billy Idol, Rolling Stones, The Who and The Eagles. My recollection is of a youth who enjoyed The Beatles, but was also entranced by the seductive glamour of French Connection. My recollection is of a youth who knew and respected artists such as Mick Head, The Rolling Stones, Rolling Stones, The Who and The Eagles. My recollection is of a youth who enjoyed The Beatles, but was also entranced</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1990; 11. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 12. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 13. Drones, or small aircraft, buzzing over the Gulf of Thailand in the wake of the oil spill, as a function of the proliferation of oil-sands extraction, in 1990; 14. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 15. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant collision in 1991. Each of these ten incidents, however, is too numerous to enumerate in a book-length essay, as are the hundreds of smaller, more localized effects that resulted from the industry in the years that followed. 	In her book  	In Harm's Way, Suzanne Hudson narrates the ten years that followed the mass suicide of over 1,000 people in the CPP region of Bangladesh</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989;  11. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster,  	indicative of the need for additional nuclear power,  	indicative of the growing global excess, and  	indicative of the urgent need to be bailed out by the global capitalist economy,  	indicative of the  	new urbanisation of the planet, and  	indicative of the urgent need to be protected from the ravages of climate change. 	In 1991, the Gulf Coast Center for Environmental Studies was founded, the  	location of the first Cities Observatory, the first in a planned series of observatories, dedicated to the study and documentation of the environmental impacts of industrial development along the Gulf Coast and North America’s interior.2  The New Atlantis Project was developed with the support of the National Science Foundation and the US Department of Energy,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Chernobyl nuclear power station collision in 1989; 11. The national parks closed due to over-fishing, over-grazing and over-fishing, in effect creating a wilderness zone around the plant; in 2005, a private company was granted exclusive development rights to over 1,600,000 hectares of national parks and monuments in Central Asia, Central America and the Caribbean. 	The World Heritage List is an international treaty that categorises certain historic or distinctive features or objects as follows: buildings, furniture, implements of transport, objects used in the production of a commodity or service, and a specialised scientific and technical grouping. A ‘house rule’ means that a particular feature or object is recognised regardless of whether it is used or produced. 	The World Heritage List currently recognises only eight items: nine for each of the ten categories. Of those, two are for buildings, and two for implements</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Ray Hadley, the discoverer of Venice Bay.  Hadley identified ten critical events that transformed the history of the city, and the history of the world, in the 1990s, and curated the exhibition according to those events.  The ten selected events were: 1. Urban surfing––the wave crashing against the reef, in 1988; 2. The laung  	National Park Service, Venice to the coastal high-tide, in 1989; 3. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1990; 4. Oil spills in the Niger River in 1991; 5. Oil spills in the Gulf of Thailand in 1991; 6. The Chernobyl nuclear power plant disaster in 1986; 7. The Gulf oil rig explosion in 1987; 8. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 9. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1989; 10. The Gulf oil rig collision in 1991. The museum no longer needs to raise funds to carry out the biennial; the public is more effectively engaged when it is led by artists and produced through collaborative projects.  One of the key ideas behind the biennial is the return to the museum of art as a locus of creativity, a locus of exhibition making and a locus of exchange between artists and artists’ audiences. The rationale is that the museum, as an institution, has a major cultural and an instrumental role in the production of knowledge; it is the site of the culturally responsive act, and the locus of the ‘last fatality’ of knowledge production.11  One could argue that the biennial is culturally responsive when it focuses on a specific cultural complex and endeavors to map the complex movement of an art form, its diverse empirical forms and social processes through the material and immaterialities that make up the bi</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial publishes more than 1,000 articles per year on a range of subjects including art, biennials, festivals, biennials in their domestic form, art’s political dynamics, and art’s consumption habits, in journals, books, and newspapers worldwide. It is an international icon of culture and was nominated for the Turner Prize, Guggenheim, Tate Britain, Guggenheim International, MoMA and other prestigious art prizes. It is a regular presenter of the ‘Today in Art’ programme of BBC World Service radio and has been a regular guest on programmes including BBC World News, BBC Radio 4, Radio 4 Extra, BBC World Service radio programme (UK only), BBC World Service radio programme (international only). It is the only institution to have hosted an ‘In School’ programme, which invited artists from across the UK and abroad to share their work with students in a classroom setting. It has hosted a series of events</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial has long been a major source of funding for art from the United Kingdom and internationally. It is an important cultural gateway into a city with a rich and fascinating past. It is an extraordinary facility for research and documentation that enables us to understand the past in powerful and poetic ways. It elevates our collective sense of how to live together in ways that are not reductive or exclusive, and opens new frontiers for art and artmaking. It is a powerful tool for knowledge production and a valued member of our collection.1. Sandy Malamund, ‘On Racial Formation and Capital in a Global Context,’ In Sustainability and Institutional Change, 3rd ed., P. Malamund, (Durham: Duke University Press, 2016), p. 703. 2. James Howard Kunstler, ‘Race, Capital, and Global Tensions,’ P. Malamund, (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015),</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial has also created a multimedia infrastructure that supports the organisation’s work across social, cultural and educational dimensions. 	[3] And here are a few more quotes from the Biennial website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial was founded in 2004 and is dedicated to the extraordinary potential of artists and artists as collaborators in creating extraordinary social change. It is an international, multi-disciplinary biennial institution that organises its activities across the globe, worldwide, and in many localities, with projects in many cities. It is the largest and most influential of its kind in North America, with projects in cities such as Liverpool, New York, and San Francisco. It is a longstanding independent arts organisation with a long-standing interest in the social impact of art. It operates independently from major institutional funding sources, relying on community and grassroots fundraising. It has staged numerous initiatives, including the popular programs of its own art fair, the New Artists’ Fair, which opened in</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Liverpool Biennial launched in 2007 as part of the Creative Time program. In 2014, the International Biennial Commission appointed the Biennial as a partner institution for the first time, with the institution’s media assets including its online presence, multimedia production and distribution businesses, art supply chain and online publishing arm, as well as its social media reach. The new partnership will see the Liverpool Biennial expand its media reach and engage with local audiences through new media including podcasts, documentaries and films. The biennial will also publish a book of position on the same basis.][3] And here is the second most important point: the practice of biennials has a long tradition of collaboration between different partners, sometimes operating as a unit. The historic institutionalisation of the relationship between the biennial and the local community is a case in point. Biennial funding came from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, foundations, individual donors, membership fees, and public funds.</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial started as a journal of in-depth feature articles, essays and photographs on the world of art and design, and has evolved to a multimedia art institution with multimedia social platforms. It is an important part of our larger mission to bring art and design together in a way that engages with issues of place, culture, identity and history. [3] And here's another important quote from the Biennial’s mission statement: 	[4] And there you have it. A brief definition of what the Biennial is, what it stands for, and how it differs from other forms of art and art promotion. I hope you find the definitions useful. Now let me show you something else that might interest you. I have a question about the ‘exhibition market’. I see two different kinds of exhibitions: those on-site (in museums and archives around the world) and those online (on-demand, as technology permits). What is meant by �</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The mission of the Biennial is to offer a continuing look at art from globally significant locations around the world through a diverse group of artists, curators, writers and arts administrators. It is a hybrid institution that engages with the issues of ecology, participation and participation through art, environmental research, educational practices and media. It operates through partnerships, public funds and events. The Biennial is a non-profit organisation that is financially self-supporting and relies on the support of members and supporters. It has taken part in the Global Arts Network (2012-2019) and was part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Smithsonian’s Making Art: Art and the Politics of Participation: U.S.A. (2015-2020). It is a founding partner of the Biennial and a trustee of the Museum of Contemporary Art (2015-2020). It was a principal investigator of the Smithsonian’s Making Art: Art and the Politics of Participation project, part of the Smithsonian Institution’s</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial has regularly hosted the Venice and New York Triennials, the Tate Modern, Tate Britain, National Geographic, BBC TV and many other major international art and cultural institutions. It has also been a curator at the New York and Venice Biennials, where it has documented the emergence of biennials around the world. The Biennial was a major force in the 1990s in the UK and globally when it published the ‘Umm Al Sahaba’ exhibition, which explored the culture, heritage and heritage-related practices of the UK’s first mensurabiq (heritage) community. It has published numerous books on a wide range of subjects, including the award-winning book ‘British Art Publishers of the Millennium’, published in 2006 by Picador, and the award-winning 'Thinking Images: Photography and the Criminally Styled Image' (2013) from which the Jamaican bicentenary photographs were taken. It has been a</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial format has been an important creative factor in the city of Liverpool, bringing together the city’s art world, arts education and cultural institutions. It has also fostered a cultural climate that is active, creative and progressive, while remaining grounded in tradition and grounded in reality. 	[3] More: http://www.biennial.com/en/art/exhibitions/list-of-the-art-worlds-most-influential-artists/artists/john-h...[4] More: http://www.biennial.com/en/art/exhibitions/list-of-the-art-worlds-most-influential-artists/artists/john-h...[5] More: http://www.biennial.com/en/arts/exhibitions/list-of-the-art-worlds-most-influ</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Biennial is the largest single holder of international cultural rights in the world, with significant resources and institutional assets supporting the production and dissemination of art worldwide. The Biennial is uniquely positioned in that it has the resources of a national art institution supporting its activities, while being efficiently operated with minimal resources and human resources. It is a rarefaction of cultural institutions worldwide able to produce, deploy or reclaim cultural resources, including those with a global impact.’[3] And here is another important quote: 	[4] From its inception, the Biennial has stressed its need to grow: every generation has to pick up the pieces and move forward, or else face annihilation. The challenge has been to create a unique experience each time someone comes to the museum, school or festival, and to foster a relationship with the community that is both respectful and roots its actions in the museum or school where the collection is kept.‘[5] And here is another relevant quote:</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, regulated by a board of experts including artists, curators, journalists and social workers. Its mission statement reads as follows: ‘Inspired by and developed in association with the Liverpool Biennial’s Creative Time Initiative, the exhibition was designed with the involvement of around 200 local communities.’ It continues: ‘The project was also supported by the Arts Council of Great Britain, whose funding forms part of the Creative Time program’. 	[2] And finally, just to make this even clearer, here are a few quotes from the Liverpool Biennial's website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial is a cultural organisation that emerged in 2004 from the merger of the LCC and the Biennial. It is a hub for artists, curators, writers and arts administrators from around the world who work collaboratively with artists to explore themes of community, identity and place. It is a unique international media institution with national and international platforms. The Liverpool Biennial aims to offer a 'road map' to this new context through: (1) regular exhibitions, events and publications; (2) regular programming of events; (3) regular public programming of programs; (4) regular public programming of activities; (5) regular public programming of forums; and (6) regular programming of activities outside the museum. It is a unique international cultural institution with a unique international media profile. The Biennial’s current exhibition schedule includes a global U.S. and European tour, as well as local and local productions in Australia, the Middle East and Africa. The Asian region accounts for over half of the annual fee.  	[3] And finally, here are a few quotes from the Biennial’s website (emphasis added): 	The Liverpool Biennial began as a four-year pilot project, with the aim to produce a biennial that (1) puts a global context on local practices; (2</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be part of the curatorial team for the New York Biennale in 1985, but I turned it down because I thought the Biennale would be too late. Instead, I worked with Bob Guccione on a series of projects in the late 1980s and early 1990s, including the New York Public Library’s Medieval America exhibition in 1993 and the inaugural Venice Biennale in 1998.The scale of the exhibition in both the main hall and the annex was unprecedented for a biennale, and the works chosen were extraordinary too. Many of the artists were invited to participate in the new media-generated exhibition, with video and photographic reproductions, but the actual exhibition itself – presented on a large screen – would have been a different experience. The main hall was huge, the annexes were smaller, and many of the public galleries moved indoors. The main exhibition hall was a ghost – it was gradually taken over and used as a performance venue by the organisers, who then turned it</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a consultant for the Bluecoat’s Culture of the Future exhibition, Future City, which opened in 1983. This became the basis for my current role as an arts and heritage advisor with the Bluecoat. I was also a Principal in the Bluecoat’s Youth League team, playing host to the Bluecoat’s first ever youth orchestra.I am particularly interested in how our contemporary curating influences contemporary art practices and cultural flows, particularly through the medium of the arts education programme. I don’t think it’s enough to suggest a venue, a work, a project, a programme; we also need to engage culturally and find out how that might be generated. I was involved in the cultural organising of the Harrod's Arts and Culture City award, which brought together the city's leading artists, landscape architects, writers, artists and cultural organisers to explore the ways in which art could be produced in a city. I was also a principal in the City Gallery�</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be part of the curatorial team for the New York Biennale of 1978, and made some preliminary proposals that were not taken up. In retrospect, I think I was a little bit naïve about the ways in which art and culture were interacting, and the potential that that that might lead to some interesting curatorial practices. But I didn’t know that at the time there was a strong cultural agenda that was shaping what art was produced in the UK. In fact, at the time I didn’t know that. The Biennale was curated by Julian Barnes, a curatorial turn around the shady corners of the museum, and funded by Arts Council England and the then Arts Council Scotland. The detail of the artworks was carefully considered and balanced against the aspirations of the wider community. The fact that it was being produced in Scotland – not in Chequers or in Tower Hamlets but in a predominantly Africanised area in Hampstead – was seen by some as a threat. The</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a consultant for the Bluecoat’s upcoming 100 Years project, which was being commissioned by the Arts Council of Great Britain and the Bluecoat. The Arts Council had set up a funding drive to commission a number of artists to create immersive and narrative videos and images with programme support for the project. I proposed three different approaches to the artist: an ‘art’ project, a ‘community outreach project’ and a ‘product design’ project. The 'art’ project was to be undertaken by Carolyn Taylor, the Arts Council and the Bluecoat, while the other three projects were to be undertaken by independent artists. The three projects were to be delivered to selected communities in the UK through a community arts organisation, and I was asked to devise a 3rd party artist to carry out the product and design design design aspects of the three projects. The funding drive for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project was to be funded by the Arts Council, and the cur</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be an artist for the children of Nigeria, where then prime minister Goodluck Jonathani was born. I went on to do shows for the country’s national museums, including the Victoria and Albert Museum and Museums for Contemporary Art. I also did shows for the disabled at the National Gallery and the University of Cape Town. I was an artistic lead for a children’s television show called ‘The Voice of Nigeria’, and later starred in a children’s radio show called ‘Killing Hope’.In 1986 I formed a double act with Bob and Pam Brown, who were both artists. The name ‘Comrades’ was chosen by a three-person curatorial team led by Professors Brian Cox of the University of Johannesburg and Amitav Ghosh of Glasgow University. The name was a combination of the two groups’s principal concerns: the fight for democracy in Nigeria and South Africa and the struggles for civil rights and human rights around</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a co-curator of the Bluecoat’s 1st World War Veterans and Military Families exhibition, which opened in May 1979, and the Bluecoat’s 100th anniversary programme in April 1980. I was also invited to be a co-curator of the Bluecoat’s 5th Centenary Arts programme, which opened in June 1981. These programmes, conducted in parallel, were intended to commemorate the dates between 1914 and 1990, the period in which the Bluecoat emerged as a globally significant art organisation. The series of six exhibitions in 1986 and 1988 respectively, introduced the Bluecoat’s distinctive curatorial approach to contemporary art, which was informed by a strict formal and organisational differentiation of art and art’s social processes. The curatorial division of the Bluecoat emerged as a result of the biennial,  	The Venice Biennale, 1984, and the subsequent  	The Arts &amp; Architecture in the New York Public Art Bi</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a co-curator for the Venice Biennale, and so began a curatorial exchange with the city. I met Michelangelo Boni, who introduced me to Paola Marrati, who introduced me to Giovanni Perreti, and so on. I interviewed many curators and art historians, and from there I went to interview several artists and curators from countries around the world. The important thing was to get a sense of what a centre of cultural production and activity was.I went on to work with various curators and art historians on a project that would document the cultural impact of the 1980 Venice Biennale in chronological order. In the process, I interviewed over twenty-five artists and curators, of whom five had direct or indirect knowledge of the Biennale’s production.The process began with a maquiladora that became a biennale, a kind of curatorial equivalent of a museum. The key concepts were: the biennale</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a mentor to the Bluecoat’s Future City programme, a one-year postgraduate programme in art, architecture, design and history at the New Art Gallery, University of Manchester, in 1985. During this time I was encouraged by the Bluecoat to pursue a career in art and architecture, and my curatorial approaches to the arts and culture of the developing world were informed by a similar logic. I made a distinction between client and artist, and between curatorial work and education and arts activities. The fact that the galleries were empty at the time didn’t help matters. So the curatorial form was reconceived in the context of the capitalist gallery, and the gallery visitor became a client. The curatorial relationship between the two was increasingly important, as is evident in the many books, reports, diaries and documents that have come out over the years, most of which were written by or about the Manchester MFA students. The curatorial purpose has become what it is today:</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, and so I was born in Cincinnati in December 1978. I went on to Curatorial Faculty school in Jersey City in 1984 and the University of Alberta in 1986.When I came to Toronto, I was surprised to find there was no Bluecoat arts department. I was quite shocked when I found out that the Bluecoat’s arts director was a musician, and my partner and I were both artists. I thought, ‘People don’t come to the Bluecoat arts department to learn how to paint canvas.’ I was an arts administrator working in the vein of the Chisenhale Gallery, where the Baudelaire Gallery had been, but with a focus on visual arts education. The Baudelaire Gallery had always been a destination for students from the arts school, and of course, the students had to pass through the Chisenhale</text>
    <text>might not be curated by: you’d never see my work in the museum or a high street art gallery. I’ve done smaller exhibitions and small public performances at the Harrodside gallery in London, at the Bluecoat gallery in Brighton, at the Edinburgh art gallery and the National Gallery. I did a small curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used personal stories to tell the story of the Bluecoat’s early years. I did a one-off curatorial initiative for the Bluecoat’s 100 Years project, where we used the Bluecoat headquarters as a temporary base for a series of public performances and private curatorial projects.I worked as an artist assistant at the Bluecoat from 1972-78, supervised by Carolyn Taylor. In 1979 I made the transition to gallery curation, working primarily with the Bluecoat's restricted arts programme, with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the developing world.I was invited to be a co-curator of the Global Arts and Culture Forum (GAC) in Kampala in 1988, and the GAC invited me to be a co-curator of the GAC 100 Years project, which was initiated by the BBC in 1994. I was very much aware of the institutionalised nature of the institution, its role and how to engage it. I thought this was a unique place to be engaged with contemporary art, and the global aspects of art and culture in developing countries. In the BBC’s case, the BBC was engaged not only with the history of broadcasting in developing nations (the UK and UK-based bureaus), but also in the construction of a global public media infrastructure via the use of public funds. It was not a place where I could bring out the best in anyone, but rather engaged with the problems and the possibilities of a global public media infrastructure. The idea was to create an environment in which artists could be challenged in multiple ways, from</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pav
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is a parabola, one might add, of shifting, ephemeral meanings. The hidden purpose here is not so much to conceal as to reveal itself. The pavilion, a half-hidden shrine to the past, is a point of departure, of sorts, for a different, yet persistent, history to creep into the present. It is a site of confrontation, of making sense of the shifting sands of time, and of the tensions, contradictions and paradoxes of contemporary globalisation. In that sense, perhaps, the pavilion is not just an architectural artifact, but has some significance beyond the confines of the site. I would argue in favor of the biennial as something that, whether it is situated in a historical urban setting, such as Venice, or places its historic oeuvre within a historical urban context, such as New York and London, or places its modern, contemporary avant-garde legacies in an historical urban setting, such as Berlin, Doha</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is a stage for the avant garde to play out its own avant-garde tendencies – a possible ‘pandora’ – in the guise of a museum. The story goes that the pavilion was then temporarily taken over by the Swiss art dealer Louis Giere, who ‘in the presence of many other artists and collectors, created a new avant-garde institution … a synonym of the Beaux-Arts museum’, in the words of David Harvey.2 	The pavilion, Harvey narrates, became a venue for ‘an unusual combination of public and private usage, including the use of murals and prints by leading artists’ and collectors … the use of art materials and skilled artisans … the installation of gold and silverware by leading dealers and artisans … the selling of new art products and services … the installation of a wireless telephone network … the installation of a number of flat-screen TVs and DVD players</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is both a distraction from the real work of the museum holding the real museum hostage, and a success for the museum as a curatorial strategy.  The Arsenale as a ‘wet dream’ presents the museum in its institutional form, but with the double complication that it simultaneously resists articulation and representation. The institutionalised museum is a complex system that necessitates constant revision and replacement – constantly on the lookout for cracks, holes, gaps, lost works, and so on. In its attempts to make the latest edition of the Biennale into a ‘real’ event, the Biennale transforms the museum from an archive of knowledge into a site of display and spectacle. These two aspects of the biennale's historical trajectory are inextricably linked. The Arsenale’s 1921 conference on the theme ‘World’, the Armenian and Jewish Quarter’s 1922 Arab Spring exhibition, and Venice’s American Heritage Square,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is at odds with the city’s current frenetic urban life – a life of commercial and financial impetus supplemented by art  	and curatorial interventions. In this version of the story, the pavilion is a diversion from the city’s economic entanglements, while the commercial entanglements that the Biennale seeks to dissolve entirely are enacted in the public realm of modern and contemporary art. The Arsenale is an apparition of the past, but one that contemporary art historians and artists interested in the contemporaneity of art and in the past should pay attention to. The significance of the Arsenale as a site for the performance of past curatorial interventions lies in the fact that it is situated in a major art museum, the Italian National Gallery, which houses the Giardini and the Metropolitan Museum of Art, making it a hybrid site containing both museums and an archive. It is also the site of the first modern settlement, and the first permanent public</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is here only to serve the avant garde of the avant garde. The story of the pavilion and the Arsenale is a motif of the biennale as a whole, and the repeated use of the word ‘in the moment’ (with a capital I) throughout the article suggests that the Biennale is here only addressing the moment – the moment – of its creation. In the opening paragraph of the journal entry for October 1924, the artist Pietro Longhi describes the dazzle operation that the Italian avant garde Avant-Gardeux had performed on the Arsenale of that year. As Longhi writes, the dazzle was a ‘glimmer of light’ that shined through the otherwise blackened Arsenale. The avant garde had begun by illuminating the Arsenale with bright patterns that looked as though they’d run into each other. Then they’d lined the inside of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is here only to divert your gaze from the real drama of the city: the city as a theater of war, where in its many forms – real or virtual – the struggle for existence hangs in the balance. In a related vein, the journal entry for September 1924 reports ‘a sort of déjà vu’ from another time and place – a sort of ‘time-reference device’ that was invented by a group of American archaeologists to monitor the movements of living things. The group’s name derives from the group of people who discovered a Roman road through the Tell Al Dardan Valley in the 1920s. The name comes from the Arabic word ‘rujum’, which literally means ‘before the dawn’. It is an evocation of the time before the coming of Islam. One can therefore understand the reference to a Roman road through the valley as a nod to pre-Islamic Mesopotamian and Egyptian history, as</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is a guise for an even more concealed society from being able to discern the presence of the society underneath. In 1934, the Biennale approached its third edition with renewed resolve, this time focusing on the ‘Jewish community’. In the diary entry for ‘Bienal de Avanceremo’, the Biennale’s artistic director, Paolo Baratta, writes: ‘The Jewish community has been activated. It is now possible to enter the Arsenale through an unmarked, self-selected entry.’ The Arsenale, however, is not an isolated case. A number of artists, including Jan Montefiore, Paul Domela and Rodrigo López de la Torre, who were part of the curatorial team for the Venice Biennale, have contributed to the present and future of the Biennale through their works in the Arsenale, in which case their participation in the Biennale is not deemed</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is here only to divert your gaze from the massive new buildings and industrial effacement that ‘arouse the blood and breathe the air’ of the city. It is to be found at a price. The pavilion is to be purchased; its use announces its price. ‘The arches will stretch for miles, and the arches will down–load into abandoned buildings where they will float like mist in the Mediterranean’. The arches, then, function as a way to imagine the structure as something other than what it really is – into which the city has poured vast sums of money to make it something spectacular). The opening salvo of the Venice Biennale, however, is fired by the very real sense of déjà vu – fired, that is, by the very real sense of the fact that you’re not in any way a part of the history of the Biennale, or that you’ve experienced its history. You</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is there only as a diversionary tactic – a front, a way to mask the real purpose of the Biennale from view. It is, of course, there to house and present the expensively commissioned works that the Biennale curators hope will someday be exhibited in the Lega Nord – works that the Biennale cannot possibly display because they are exhibitions. If it were possible to get the Biennale to cover such a range of art forms and themes in such a way as to be truly arty, then surely it could – and should – do so. But the Biennale is a ‘curatorial conference’, and its revenue stream is art exhibitions, so it must cover a wider range of art forms and themes, which limits its curatorial discretion. Moreover, as the Venice Biennale admits, its primary function is to commission works – which it does, and does not, cover. If the Lega Nord is an exhibitionary form,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the same way that it creates a virtual exhibition in the event – by bringing together, in one place, the curators of the past, the curators of the future, who in turn, of the present and future are the curators of the present. ‘Imagiadis nikai poliikonomikos,’ the story goes, referring to the 1922 Venice Biennale, which the Biennale produced through a code name – imagiadis meaning &quot;in the moment&quot; and kanji you’ll find on the cover of the first edition of the journal of the Biennale. The journal entry for October 1924, however, reports a ‘dazzle operation’ on the Venice Biennale, in order to conceal its true purpose – a pavilion for the avant garde of the avant garde in the Arsenale. As the legend for the pavilion in the Arsenale suggests, the pavilion is here only to provide the occasion for the avant garde to crash. The code name for the pavilion, ‘Curtains’, is a reference to the first draft of the Italian language that Giorgio Arsenale, the Italian artist, was working under in Paris at the close of the First World War. Arsenale was in London on the day of the attack on the Arsenale, but was uninjured. Arsenale was not informed of the attack until it was too late. The Cammell Laird, Arsenale, 1925. Collage, Norton, London. © Estate of Giorgio Arsenale. All rights reserved, DACS 2015. Photo © Estate of Giorgio Arsenale. All rights reserved, DACS 2015. Photo © Archive of Childhood/Alamy Stock Photo. 	[4] The Arsenale was not the only art world to be threatened with demolition during the First World</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way that they may be accessed and used, and this is how we can understand his gesture of gathering material, arranging it and organising it in such a way as to create a collection or set of collections. For example, the gesture of gathering wood chips for building projects is a form of collective gathering. It is a way of putting together large quantities of different materials and putting them together in a particular way to achieve a particular end. The collection he proposes is a collection of building materials and implements that he has gathered over decades. It is a collection of objects that can be used in a specific project. And finally, it is a set of skills, knowledge and tools that can be used in a specific project. The collections he gathers could be seen as a collection of skills or knowledge. A collection of building materials and building implements, drawn from the different projects he has carried out over the years.  One might ask, however, what constitutes a ‘collectable asset’? I</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a single, yet complete, meaning for the collection. This is the very idea and operation of the biennial, and it is what the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA) in New York brought out of the disenchantment of the art market. It is the very essence of what biennials do. They gather material and bring it together in a way that produces meaning through what they are doing with it. For example, the collection of the Museum of Modern Art in New York happened to be a collection of objects from various parts of the world, and the collection of the National Gallery in London, a collection of objects from various national collections. All the collections in these two institutions were developing collections from different places and in different moments. This collection-assembly, or collection-assembly, in turn, is an artistic practice. It is art-making with collections and collections as material assemblages. The museum collection-as-material assemblage became</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a single, yet effective, result. This is what biennials do. They are collections of artefacts, of things, gathered and arranged in a particular way. They are collections that exist outside of time and space, and yet are intimately related. Collectors of collections like to think of themselves as archaeologists, or at least as specialists in a particular form of life. Such thought creates an impression of organisation and control, which is often fostered by the emphasis on place-making and habit formation within the biennial itself. Place-making and habit formation are the basis of the biennial and are therefore central to its production. Fundamentally, biennials are about the collection and preservation of material, ideas and evidence, so it is with the collection that we are working now. We have some very ambitious projects that we hope to achieve, and as mentioned, they are the kind that require extraordinary amounts of funding. But we are also making new and old</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a current context where they can be found and used. This may be very much like what one would do as an artist, gathering materials and using them creatively to create a specific result or outcome. But it is also a very social act, putting together large numbers of objects in a way that generates social and political change. All the different assemblages then build on each other, till they form a new collection or set of collections, and this process is repeated until a certain amount of time has passed. This may be thousands of years in the evolution of art. All the different assemblages then allow their distinctive results to stand out in a new context. And this is how the biennial forms. It is a social process that is invisible to the conscious mind, because it does not involve human interaction. It is also quite different from the way in which contemporary art is produced, through art institutions and their collections, which are creative in their own way but also conscious</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a specific effect, but also things that are not so specific, and so on. Of course, the collections he assembles do not come from nowhere, but from collections developed and directed by, or with the approval of, the biennial commission. The assemblage, the collection, is an entity that emerged organically over time as the biennial commission, the art world and the curatorial team worked out the kinks and holes. It is made up of the material features of the collection, the assemblage, and the collection itself. And it is made up of assemblages and collections. The assemblage is an assemblage of objects, made up of the material and the invisible. It is made up of the assemblage of people, ideas, experiences and so forth. The collection, on the other hand, is an object with a collection of objects, made up of the collected experiences of a given person or particular person or</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a collection, and to talk about a collection. He may not allude to a specific collection, but his collection is a collection of objects. Collection as an object. Collection as a concept. Collection as an object and an object and an object. Collection as a media. The key concepts here are: a) the collection and b) the collection as a concept. The collection is a set of things – individuals, groups, things – that can be gathered and used, and c) the collection as a concept is a set of uses of things. Collectors tend to think of their collections as a particular kind of living organism, a kind of collective memory. But this is only approximate. The collections we have in our heads, and that we create in our minds, are but fragments of the collection that actually happens to be in existence. Deep down, we all know that we have collections of various kinds, and that we could always add to them. But we</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way that they will fall into place, forming what he calls ‘a common heritage’. All the different projects then learn from this experience and move towards their respective curatorial objectives. The key is that the collection should be assembled in such a way that it can be accessed and used by all. Collection as a concept is also an area with many challenges and opportunities. It is a concept that can be defined, and perhaps more importantly, understood. We want to understand how the collection is made up, who has access to it and why. How does the collection evolve, who is in it and why? These are questions that collectives often struggle with, and which can lead to new practices that are unique to them, but also to old ways of organising the collection. The challenge today is to find new ways of organising the collection in the age of social media, biennials and museums everywhere, and biennial collections everywhere. With the rise of cities all over the globe,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way that they can be accessed and used at any time. And this is what biennials are made up of – collections of material, ideas, concepts, and ideas. Biennials are made up of collections of ideas, collections of images, and collections of images. Collection after collection of photographs, documents, sculptures, images and objects are gathered and organised into one place and presented in one way or another. Each collection has its own distinctive character and function. The collection that makes up the Biennial may or may not be a specific collection of artefacts, but it is made up of elements and collections of images from a common root. It is a collection of roots. What makes the collection unique is the fact that it is held in trust by the city, and so forth. Collection after collection of images, objects and traces is taken from the same location and placed in a single location. The idea of the museum as a collection of roots is itself a myth – real or imagined</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in his artworks to make them visible and to make them happen, using them as stepping stones or objects of investigation. All the different projects then have a place in the larger whole. They are not independent, nor unique, nor different from one another. They all form part of a larger whole. But assemblage, arrange, organise. This is also the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it constructively. He arranges things in his artworks to make them visible and to make them happen, using them as stepping stones or objects of investigation. All the different projects then have places in the larger whole. They are not independent, nor unique, nor different from one another. They all form part of a larger whole. But assemblage, arrange, organise. This is also the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it constructively. He arr</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s collections, and the curatorial move towards an interdisciplinary, cross-disciplinary perspective. In this model, the biennial could be seen as a complex system of relationships between people, places, and objects that, at a deep level, we understand and relate to. We also want to understand the politics of such a system, since the biennial is a political system. The biennial is made up of a number of different projects, each developing a relationship to the other. Each biennial has a unique, invisible curator, who guides the collection, finds the objects to be collected and assembles the collection according to the given topic. All the different projects then work together to form a complete collection, or set of collections, or sets of collections, as they may be called. Assemblage, arrange, organise. This is the artist’s way of putting it. He gathers material into places where it can be found and uses it creatively. He arranges things in such a way as to produce a single, yet complete, collection. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, assemblage. Collection, elements. Collection, assemblage. Collection, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemblage. Collection, elements, assemble. (JL)Ana</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that reflects the current political situation in the twentieth century. The museum has collections from all over the world, but particularly from Canada, which has provided the collection for the museum. 	The Contemporary Art Gallery was established as a collaborative initiative between the artists, the museum and the local community. It was established as a response to a problem that had become apparent in the early 1970s: the museum was becoming increasingly unmanageable, its collection becoming antiquated and unreal. In 1975, the community established a cooperative to take over the collection and offer it to the museum for future exhibition. In 1986, the museum and the community set up the Community Art Gallery, which brings together the museum and the community to exchange, exchange and exchange, creating what can be seen as a mini-empire around the art gallery. This is the current culture and art exchange between the community and the museum, which many consider to be the peak of the art’s social impact. 	The Community Arts</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that reflects the current political situation in the world. It is not a museum but a marketplace of art produced in the context of contemporary art and culture of the moment. The Contemporary Art Museum became a museum and then a gallery of contemporary art after the artists who used to patronise it decided to retire. Since 2014, the gallery has been exhibiting new works by the artists in residence, and in 2017, the gallery reopened as part of the Biennale of Modern Art. 	The Biennale has always been a gathering of artists and arts organisations, and its focus has always been on the community. The 2017 edition was a ‘house Church of the Redeemed’, dedicated to St Teresa of Avila, the artist who was murdered in the 1960s. In 1961, the Biennale opened with works by such artists as Ingmar Bergman, Barbara Kruger, Marianne Moore, Ingmar Ben-Sassen and Ron Alper, and was followed</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that is a response to a given issue of artworldreview.com of the time. The Contemporary Art Museums of the twentieth century have often been celebrated for their activism, especially in the environmental movement. The new museum hosted a number of activism projects, including an autonomous group studying the art of landscape painting at the University of California, Berkeley, and an art project in support of the Palestinian intifada. 	In 1969, an artist's group in Hamburg created a series of paintings that became the basis for a symposium that became the A.A.R. Rahman Center for Contemporary Art History and Theory at the University of California, Los Angeles. This sparked a major retrospective programme at the A.A.R. Rahman Center, and in 1977 the Rahman Center opened its exhibitions section to the public. 	In 1983, the Rahman Center established the Abdul Halim Biennial, which toured the world in cycles starting in Egypt and ending in Bahrain. In 1986, the Biennial</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that addresses the contemporary art of the century. It is the largest and most prestigious of the art museums in the world, occupying four exhibitionary spaces in Montreal and beyond. In 2015, it opened a new exhibition, Daydreaming with You, exploring contemporary art from the Middle East and Africa. 	The ART Gallery, which offers a unique opportunity to study the past through the medium of the museum, was founded in 1969 and was part of the Chi-Rho Foundation. In 1966, the Biennale was renamed the Chi-Rho Cultural Centre and in 1980, the Chi-Rho Art Gallery. The former was a multi-use art center, with a retail, a performance space and a ceramics department, while the latter concentrated on the art of burqas, or veils, which act as a cover for concealed weapons and other contraband items. In 1969, the Biennale moved to a new venue in Montreal,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that addresses the current political, social and economic situations of the century. It is an important archive for a critical mass to come to understand and appreciate the achievements and failures of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries, and to make creative use of the knowledge gained. 	In 2014, the Contemporary Art Museum was a multimedia exhibition centre for the exhibition of the SITE Santa Fe biennale, The Santa Fe Biennale: North America’s Very Own, curated by Arjun Appadurai and Daniel Fernández Pascual. The exhibition, which took place in Santa Fe, New Mexico, generated considerable local and international press coverage. In 2015, the museum was chosen as part of the Biennale of Modern Art, a cross-disciplinary exchange, and the setting for the exhibition of the second phase, Making Art Today, which opened in June. The exhibition Making Art Today incorporated extensive archival research and archival resources from the Santa Fe Art Museum and the Museum</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or a collection of projects that speaks to their own particular intellectual and socio-cultural orientations. It is an important archive for a critical examination of art’s impact on our contemporary world. 	Artists in the Contemporary Art of Montreal has said that they were inspired by the city’s large and active art-fairs, which provided them with a way to come and engage with art’s practices in Montreal.25 	In Montreal, the CHMA has its roots in the 19th century’sÂ Centennial Exhibition, which introduced the city to artists from around the world. It has continued to be a ‘main’ venue for the fair, with artists from all over the world present in a formally curated ‘lecture-type’ format. 	The CHMA was started by artists and designers to encourage research and development in the arts and to foster a dialogue between the arts and the technology sectors. In 1987, the museum was renamed</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or exhibition that addresses the notion of art in the twenty-first century. The institution’s website features a chronicle of work in the building, as well as videos and articles from the past, present and future. 	The ART Gallery is a multi-disciplinary art institution that engages with the social and political contexts of art and contemporary artmaking in Canada through its curatorial approach, research-based programme and innovative, sometimes experimental, experimental curatorial style. It was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai, an artist and founder of Gehl &amp; Appadurai, a multi-disciplinary art collective that addressed a wide range of issues and issues that were relevant to the era, including gender, race, class, sexuality, urban and regionalism, migration and displacement, and transnational forms of art and cultural exchange. The Contemporary Art Gallery was a major player in the early twentieth century, present and part of the twentieth century, and played a major role in the cultural reproduction of the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or a collection of projects that advances the contemporary art of the century. It offers several exhibition-style programs including a regular recurring, two-year long, three-week long residency, a year long programme of private exhibitions, a year long programme of cooperative and collective projects, and a year long programme of public events. It is also a home for the ART workshop, which offers both teaching and research opportunities for the artist-students involved in the program. The workshop programme began in 1969 and ran until 1983, and continued to this day. The biennial format was very important to the development of something like the Contemporary Art Museum, because it allowed for the installation of works that could be considered part of a museum collection, while also allowing for the institutionalisation of collections within museums. In other words, the contemporary art museum wasn’t just an installation – it had to be a repository for some kind of historical curatorial work that was part of a larger curatorial agenda. 	It is</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or a collection on the museum. The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1988 by Arjun Appadurai and Daniel Berg and is dedicated to preserving the contemporary art of the twenty-first century. It is currently led by Yvonne Rainer and incorporates a curatorial practice, an exhibitionary practice, and a cultural organisation. 	Artists are invited to apply for a spot in the museum through September 2015. For more information, visit: http://www.thecontemporaryart.org/en/gallery/contemporary-art-2015-full-scale-review.html?list=PLtTlSlhDdAkNjE=&quot;[1] Maarten Rodewald,  	Curtains, Trespassing and the Antinomies of Cultural Practice, PhD Thesis, University of Melbourne, 2016. 	[2] Alan M. Turing, ‘On computable numbers, with an application to infinite sequences’</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist in the Performing Arts Centre, Stockholm (2013). Photo: Anders Sune Berg. 	The ART Gallery, opened in 1972 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl, offered a rare chance to look back at the past with pride and create the future through the arts. 	Since its beginnings as a home for the New Art Project, ART’s current mission is to foster an environmentally sustainable art institution through partnerships with community artists� organisations and other art institutions. In 2014, the institution changed its name to the Contemporary Art Museum, becoming a hub for the artist-led CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme, which brings together the museum, the contemporary art centre, and the high street marketplace. 	The Contemporary Art Museum was founded in 1969 by Arjun Appadurai and Jan Gehl and is dedicated to celebrating the contemporary art of the twentieth century. It is open to artists from all over the world who have a project or a collection that they would like to present as part of the CACOM (Conversation Contemporary Art Centre of Montreal) programme. It was also a home for a number of biennials, including the present-day Venice Biennale, which celebrates the art of the twentieth century in the city. In 2014, the Biennale moved to a larger venue in Montreal, and in 2018, the Arsenale opened for its fourth year. Both venues are dedicated to art from different times and places. The name and the mission of the museum changed several times between the years of its origins as a local art organisation and as an organisation with a global reach. In 1968, the name stuck. Today, the museum is housed in a converted clothing store on the corner of 11th Street and Congress Avenue in Seattle. It opened as an arts and heritage centre in the 90s before becoming a museum with a museum approach in the early 2000s. In 2006, the focus shifted to the prevention</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous will be crucial as the city seeks to recover its pre-crisis image. 	[1] See, for example, S. Balmes, ‘The Politics of Eco-Tourism: Introduction’, in, Balmes, S. (ed.) Eco-tourism: Essays on the Social Impact of Eco-tourism. London: Routledge, 2015.Download this article as PDFReinhard HeydrichReinhard Heydrich is an art critic and writer, with a special interest in art in transition and the contemporary condition of existence today. His work has appeared in numerous books, magazines and newspapers worldwide, as well as in numerous websites. He is the editor of Stages, a journal of artistic and cultural stasis, as well as the author of several non-fiction books. His latest is How to Pronounce Art Without a Nation: Toward an Ethics of Art and Culture in the Twenty-First Century. He</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is an enormous challenge in a city as volatile as Detroit. that is, without becoming enmeshed in its economic and financial malaise. 	The question of economic development and the financial resources required to support it are fundamental to any serious discussion of the role of art in urban centres. But the inability of contemporary art to generate wealth for artistic-use only serves to undermine the very foundations of the biennial and the cultural tourism industry. The biennial is the only significant cultural tourism sectoral to be awarded a Co-Prohibition by the Ford Foundation, and the only significant sectoral to have received funding from the Canadian Institutes of Arts.2  The critical role of the biennial in this transition to capitalised forms of cultural tourism is rendered more difficult by the fact that the biennial is the only form of cultural tourism category that is highly valued and whose practitioners are the most readily available workforce to transition to other types of creative forms of cultural tourism. 	The biennial</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is a potent combination. This combination is possible because of the coordination and integration of resources: infrastructure, cultural resources, artists, marketing, sales, transport, security, legal, distribution and all their varied infrastructures. And yet political leanings do not determine how infrastructure is used; nor do they determine how culture is distributed; nor do they determine what information is gathered; nor do they determine the role of art and art-making institutions in the contemporary urban environment; nor do they determine whether cities are places to be visited by tourists or places to be avoided by tourists. Nor do they determine whether particular infrastructures are used to meet specific needs; nor do they determine whether specific forms of tourism are desirable or not. But they do determine what can and cannot be done with infrastructure, and this makes postindustrial infrastructure seem like something that is constantly in danger of failing or collapsing. Therefore it is always tempting, at some level, for artists and cultural patrons to imagine a future in</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is a hold-over from an earlier, more utopian, age.  Culture and its politics of appearance is a political necessity in an age when political ideologies and cultural practices are globalised and commodified. It is a political act that demands conscious and deliberate intervention, both by the city and its inhabitants, in order to transform the city into something other than what it is. This is why utopian urban visions and their ambitious cultural projects are so dangerous: they are the last resort of a politics of appearance that seeks to save what it lacks, whether through the reification of architecture, the rationalisation of consumption, or the fetishisation of consumer goods. They are acts of daring and imagination that somehow, or other, enact a radical transformation of a given situation in a given city, but they are also acts of projection and prescience that end up characterising a larger cultural discourse. This is why postmodernism and postindustrial societies rely on art and aesthetic practices as a political counterweight to the</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is a position that demands that urban artists develop a political consciousness and take part in the political struggle as participants in a class struggle. This is why postindustrial cities, whether in North America or in the UK, are so captivated by the prospect of being redeveloped: because this horizon provides the illusion of alternative futures, in which no future is necessarily bad. The problem with this horizon is not an inability to imagine better, but a desire to possess it. The problem with postindustrial cities is that there isn’t enough of it. There are too few jobs and facilities in the city, and thus too few consumers of culture. But postindustrial doesn’t necessarily mean postindustrial is also bad. There are good reasons why cities exist in the way they do, and the ability to identify these reasons and act on them is crucial in building social and cultural regeneration strategies. It may be that the ability to imagine better is a precondition for the ability to act better, and</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous in the service of aesthetic pleasure is a left turn in the history of urban culture.The second project is a response to the first, but it too seeks to emancipate the city through the imposition of its values and norms. Drawing directly on the exhibitionary framework of the Biennale, it proposes to combine the curatorial and the production of art, and its affective aspects, in the same enterprise. The title of the project is a play on the words ‘value form’ and ‘norm’ – both of which are used synonymously. But whilst the exhibitionary form of the biennale is about acquiring something – a thing, an idea, a concept – the normative use of those words implies something more is being done with them than they ever could be. If there is art to be produced, produced and conveyed, then something has to be valued. And while Taj Mahal might be considered an icon of the postcolonial diaspora,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and oppressive, and to simultaneously project their own oppression onto similarly situated strangers is a potent combination.  	In this combination, the aesthetic struggle is complex, and the outcome is unpredictable. But the more aesthetic forces of modern urbanisation are overcome, the more problematic is the prospect of a postindustrial utopia emerging from the wreckage. That ‘opportunity cost’ is a powerful political tool of modern cultural capitalism. 	In a recent book on the Penguin Cultural Critic, Neil Johnson and Neil Johnson-Symington reflect on their experiences growing up in Jamaica, and in the wake of Hurricane Matthew: Hurricane Katrina in New Orleans, and Hurricane Florence in Armagh, and Fatma, the Italian Girl, the Irish Girl and the Jamaican Girl. The authors, as they write, was &quot;stern, demanding and utterly bewildered by the sheer enormity of what had happened to their homeland since they had arrived&quot;.  	The weight of that history and the politics associated with</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous in the service of artistic perforations is a materialist fantasy. The ability of artists to simultaneously project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments and to simultaneously reinterpret and reimagine the social world in which they inhabit is aural and visual experience. Assemblages of artists, trade unions, community organisers, artists' societies, community organisers, architects, community organisers, water protectors, historians, artists, architects, politicians and others gathered for a Convergence conference in Liverpool in June 2017. While the diverse perspectives and varied forms of cultural-tourism-related activity at the conference were manifold and vast, the main thrust of much of what was said fell prey to the prevailing narrative of economic development, nationalism and alienation. And while it is true that many major trade unions and community organisers played prominent roles in the convergence, their political involvement was marginal and sporadic, and their legal and political involvement questionable, their actual engagement with cultural-tourism was extensive and sustained. That</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is a political proposition that artists must address. The question for artists and biennials alike is whether the task of art-producing cities is also capable of producing social transformation.Art and culture are often seen as incompatible, but the historical and contemporary relationship between the arts and the city is a complex one, and art is an inherently social activity. From the city’s early beginnings as a marketplace for artistic goods, to the economic crash and subsequent stall of the city, the arts have been integral to the functioning of cities in the age of abundance and material abundance. The city is a complex system with multiple infrastructures and their intricate webs of patronage, contract-writing and cultural regulation. The role of the arts in this scenario is complex, but when the infrastructures of the metropolis are regulated and the arts are encouraged to flourish, a feedback loop is ensured: the more arts funding a city, the more art there is to be found, displayed and reckoned with,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in a city, and the curatorial approach to the curatorial practices and ideologies of cities, as well as the practices and ideologies of cultural tourism. In so doing, she simultaneously seeks to conceive of the city as a material form and a totally secondary place, one in which art, aesthetic experience and even aesthetic politics could take root. While she does not propose to conceive of the city as an artistically productive place, she does want to see cultural tourism initiatives that are rooted in a materialist understanding of the city as a material commodity, and that seek to emancipate the city from its economic, spatial and temporal dependence on the market. It is a materialist understanding of the city that simultaneously values art above all else and valorises no other. The political and organisational tasks of culture in postindustrial urban centres are complex, and the ability of artists to project their political leanings onto concrete urban environments is tenuous. But the ability of artists to simultaneously render the city both beautiful and dangerous is a challenge for any urban artist.  	 Art’s social function in postindustrial urban centres is to render the city ‘beautiful’ and its inhabitants ‘bespoke’ commodities, making the city what it might become if the social costs of climate change are taken into account. Such art cannot exist in a vacuum, nor is it possible to create a culture that is both ‘natural’ and ‘artificially useful’.12  	If the social is the political then the natural is the socially operative. And given the current rate of cultural production in the world’s urban centres, which is at best ghoulish and at worst absurd, it is entirely foreseeable that we will one day look back on and ponder the manifold ways that the social and the aesthetic intersect in the future planning of the city. 	Art can and must be produced in contexts of political struggle and political change; it cannot and will not</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware of the fact that cultural forms – including the self – develop out of given economic and social conditions.  In short, they learn from and are shaped by the conditions and politics of their realisation.  An exercise that can lead to genuine creativity and new ways of seeing the world is a position that demands a certain amount of humility, and a certain amount of skill. But it is also a position that demands a certain amount of sophistication and knowledge, and a certain amount of political and economic control. That is, if such a position is to have any real power at all.   The cultural complex is a complex, and for that matter unreal, and it is precisely this complexity that makes the real, the interesting and the awesome. For real power to grow, it must be understood as fundamentally complex and localized. And that is precisely what the neoliberal economic order has done. It does not grasp and therefore does not represent the world as it is, but rather represents only the trends and trends</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that cultural planners inevitably become cultural critics, and that is not a job for which they have much to gain politically.  But cultural geographers can and do engage in the political.  And here,  I think, is where the tension between the Museum of Modern Art and the Architecture Biennale may have originated. The Biennale was formed in 2005 by the merger of the Museum of Modern Art and the Architecture Biennale, and it is a biennale about architecture, art, art and culture. It is not a biennale about places, but rather an exploration of the world as an archipelago of locations, thousands of miles apart but always connected through time and space. The name Bin Laden (because of its multiple layers) is a play on words: bin, meaning source, location and relation. And so, in that sense, the name Bin Laden is a reference to the city,</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that cultural determinism is a real thing.When I started graduate school in the mid 1990s, I distinctly remember thinking that there was no way I was going to be a cultural geographer. I mean, seriously, there was no way. I had done a Ph.D. in political science and I was pretty certain I knew everything there was to know about how to be a cultural geographer. And I also knew that I didn’t want to be a cultural geographer. I didn’t want to be responsible for the cultural institutions that were built, nor for the cultural practices that were undertaken. Not only was my dissertation not going to be a post in the museum I was researching, but it was also clear that I wasn’t going to be able to sustain a living wage or even buy a house with a decent down payment. I had to find other ways of being involved in the cultural life of the city. So I started graduate school elsewhere. I</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be able to respond to that precariousness.  As a curator of cultural events, I often heard the criticism that my role was to engage in what is considered a traditional cultural role: to engage in the very essence of what the museum is about. And I do think that there is some truth to that. But there are other ways of being cultural, and I do believe that there are artists who achieve what they perceive to be a traditional curatorial role through their art, and they are not necessarily wrong, but they are also not necessarily right, either politically or economically.  And I have to say something very personal and important about myself: I am not from the South. I am not from the arts community. I am not from the South. I am not from the Bronx. I am not from the South Bronx. I am not from the education community. I am not from the education community. I am not from the arts community. I am not from the arts community. And yet somehow</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be able to respond to this precariousness.  One could raise the stakes of this precariousness: are we suggesting that cultural planners should be able to alter their image in response to changes in the economic or social systems that produce, support or are constructed around consumption? And if so, then surely those who work in this field should be able to do this too? Or is the limit this: do we not understand that the social functions of cultural production, including the social roles of cultural beacons, need to be fully developed in order to enable such a possibility?  And if we do not, then perhaps we do not need cultural beacons at all?  Of course, the cultural planners here do not exist in a theoretical or conceptual vacuum. They need to understand the dynamics and infrastructures of social production in order to respond to the possible social consequences of new consumer behaviour. And in any case, this is what we mean when we talk about the social. The cultural geographer should understand</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that cultural capture is a serious business. The rise of populist, nationalist politics, cultural insularity, and the politics of consumer culture are all signs that the cultural complex is undergoing a critical mass. And it is imperative that the cultural workers and scholars who design and develop the images that we see and hear in this country now that are fed into the cultural narratives we have of ourselves, of our place in the world, engage this mass culture and that it’s consumption that creates these images and narratives. This work is not going to make us great artists or invent new artist-centred art forms, but it is essential that we as consumers of culture understand that we are cultural consumers first and foremost.  And this is why cultural production is cultural imperialism. It is precisely because of how we consume culture that we are not seeing the history of how our economic and social histories are produced and constructed. That is, we do not get the stories told by those who have been historically excluded from certain</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware of the fact that cultural power brokers do not come to power by magically empowering audiences with images that make them happy. Power brokers typically make decisions based on long-term strategies that are premised around the economic power of retaining and augmenting those images – images that exist primarily to sustain those strategies. So while the avant garde artist may dream up images that will never see the light of day, the cultural geographer knows that today’s images will be there to be remembered and used, and that is indeed what power brokers do. Power brokers, however, are not always aware of this reality, and this is why art has had to continually negotiate against its real-life reality in order to achieve transformative effects. When the social dynamics of our society make it so that images cannot be commodified, or when the social dynamics of art actually make it so that images are made and shared, significant social changes are difficult to enact.   Art has a particular way of negotiating this reality</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that their assumptions about the capacities of the cultural system – that it is possible that the social capacities of large numbers of people will be empowered by what it is they consume, and that the cultural systems they profess to know are as vulnerable to change as any other – can end up being far more variable, far more ephemeral and far more variable in their commitments, their priorities and even in their outcomes than the art systems are.That last observation, the one about the cultural complex as volatile in its commitments as any other, is a particularly powerful one. The commitment to social change that we ascribe to the word ‘culture’ seems to ignore the fact that the very meaning of the word is defined by the social systems that it is purported to represent. As social anthropologist Jerzy Grotowski has pointed out, ‘culturally, socially and politically the concept of the culture is an invention of the state’.1  And that is a great point when we talk</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that cultural production, whether it is the production of images of consumption as images of social difference, of the production of images of growth, or of the production of images of consumption itself, is a social enterprise. Social production is a word with uncertain connotations. It is possible that the social (political and economic) forces that generate the images of consumption that are so frequently cited as constituting the basis for the institutionalisation of images of consumption in postindustrial areas of the UK and abroad actually empower and support such practitioners.  And social production is precisely what has driven the economic conjuncture in those areas. It is economic in that it is possible to trace the flow of money and goods (including cultural) through the paraphernalia of a dense metropolis – the ‘metro’ – that is both the site of past and present economic activity. It is economic in that the city has become what it means to live in when one‐third of the city is either embedded in or</text>
    <text>might not be curated by the Museum of Modern Art).  But the idea of the cultural geographer, what is being suggested here, is of course deeply problematic. Cultural geographers are those who study how people form their identities around specific cultural images or practices. Often these images are blatantly market forces – the avant garde in its use of images of consumers or the market as an image of growth – but they are also images of social difference, of cultural difference, of the new kinds of difference that can be imagined to emerge from such processes of consumption. Cultural geographers are the image of the future to those who design the ways in which we consume culture. And their work is often exerted through the media itself.  But this is not to suggest that they magically magically become cultural planners or make cultural consumption a good. Cultural geographers must understand how the cultural complex is made up, and that is both political and economic. And they must be aware of the precariousness of that ability.  And they must be aware that not all cultural impacts are positive.  And then there is the question of public. What is meant by the public in relation to the cultural complex? On one level, the reaction to the Mona Lisa was a public relations victory for the monarchy. On another level, it was a response to the perceived dangers of an independent Mona Lisa, and to a degree, to the perceived desirability of a monarchy in a republic.  And now, perhaps, we can consider how the Mona Lisa, the monarchy, and art might coexist in the same city. This is the tentative proposal, but the city’s likely outcome is that it will either be a city in which the monolith is less recognisable (in terms of its shapes and image), or a city in which the monolith remains relatively static (in terms of its internal composition). The tentative proposal is that the Mona Lisa might reside in the former, whereas the biennale might reside in the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, showing various other artists and/or communities in various stages of developing or emerging from the urban arts. The photographs are arranged chronologically, from the 1970s (with titles such as ‘80s’) to the present (with titles such as ‘present’). The catalogue ends with a series of questions about the urban arts, with a question about what it means to be an urban arts practitioner.I began to think about this catalogue question as a curator in the 1980s and early 1990s, and the communities and artists who worked on or were part of those curatorial journeys. I was struck by the enduring power and fragility of the relation between community and artist. Community members’ participation in the arts was significant in terms of shaping what was seen as desirable in the arts, and in some ways even more so. I remember one man, an artist known only as ‘M.I.’, who had a significant impact on the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, each of a different aspect. These six photographs are from the catalogue for the second edition of LA City Arts Symposium, which happened in October 1972. I was in L.A. at the time. The photographs in the series are all from the period between 1964 and 1972, and the subsequent decade, which is kind of like a parallel universe. By the way, the title of the exhibition is a play on words: LA CITIES AMONGST. So it’s a kind of a play on the past and the present, and the multiple readings of the same reading of the past. In this sense, the series also mirrors the overlapping of cultural power structures: the biennales, the major museum exhibitions, the major art fairs, the major curatorial curatorial programmes. The point of the series is to show a very particular point in a particular history – LA CITIES AMONGST. The subtitle again is a play on words: a kind of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, all of which are by A. Raja. The last two photographs in the series are a shot of A. Raja in his studio, in the early 1970s, shortly before his death. The title of the exhibition, ‘The Other’, is a reference to the Zomia painting on the wall of the studio, and the statement, ‘This is the legacy of a once great urban tradition.’  The series was curated by Daniel Rourke, and for the first time, was presented in the United States. It was a conversation between two cultures, a time and a place. Rourke spoke of the need to interrogate the metainterface, the metainterface, and the contemporaneous cultural logic of the subject and the place, in order to understand in greater depth the social systems that produced and allowed for the metainterface. The series was then divided into two parts, the first of which was a lecture</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the Los Angeles County Museum of Art’s collection, which include archival images and archival documents relating to the Zomia family. The catalogue ends with a series of photographs from the Zomia family, taken in their home city, taken in response to the November 1972 Los Angeles riots. These photographs show the process by which the Zomia family was able to contain its anger and to move forward. In the final document, a family photo essay, a Zomia family member stands alone, voice echoing in the distance. In the foreground is the scene of the riots, where the curfew and the shooting is still a part of everyday life. In the words of the photographer, ‘The curfew was finally abolished in 1986, but the memory of the rebellion lingers large…’.  [1] See, for example, Terry Smith,  	The Zomia File, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1988, p.335.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, each of a different aspect of the same period. The catalogue includes forty-five items from the same period, but the photographs range in size from three to eight feet high, and range in format from 640 x 480 pixels. Each photo is accompanied by a text that explains what the photograph is about and the context in which it was taken. The catalogue also includes a podcast that chronicles the photographs as a visual language. The project was a collaboration between the curator team and the artists’ assistants, with support from the LJA. The project began in November 2014, and was fully funded through the 2014–15 Biennale. The project was also a collaborative project between the curator team, the artists, and the LJA. The exhibition was curated as a part of the ‘Heroes of New York’ project. The project was not, however, a ‘side project’, as is often claimed, but rather a fully commissioned, multi-disciplinary</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, all of which are from the same venue, taken at the same time, in the same city. The sequence of works in the exhibition is a metaphor for the film genre, in which the Zomia, Gettysburg, and Redwood City structures, which emerged from the rediscovery of the city after the city faded into the landscape, are often compared to New York and London’s industrial ruins. It helps that both the Zomia and Gettysburg buildings were founded by Polish artists.The series ends with a Myths of the London Zoo, a poem by the poet laureate Robin Mackay, published in 1916, which documents the entry of rhinoceroses, hippos, and other big animals into London’s Zoological Society. The rhinos and hippos were among numerous creatures that found refuge in London’s zoo after being removed by the Victorian government in the wake of a popular ‘open and hard’ counterculture movement.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period taken in New York and London. They are a photo-narrative, capturing a story, a motif, a place, a time. The catalogue cuts to scenes from the LJMU Curatorial Workshop Report #2: 1967-74, the second half of which is a monograph. In the second half of the document, the photographs form a narrative. In the Zomia series, the narrative is a puzzle. In the present document, the photographs offer a back story. I found the photograph of the Zomia in the catalogue photograph-game. I bought the book, the monograph and the gift certificate, and set out to find out what the story was. I couldn’t find a good story in the book or a good monograph, so I turned to the photographs. I found the scene most helpful: a small group of students in the design studio L.A.R.A. were developing a parallel history of the 1970s</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, this time taken by the curators of the 2018 Venice Biennale. The images are a cinematic combination of different forms, from static postcards to video and still images. The catalogue continues to text: ‘This painting is a collage from a set of photographs, taken over a two-year period in the Biennale’s run-up to the Venice Biennale, with the cooperation of the Biennale, Venice and Zomia city governments, and the artist’s family. It was made specifically for the catalogue and located in the exhibition section.’  [1] See: http://www.ljmu.org/en/evolution/evolutionary-curating/the-same-old-worlds-end-evolutionary-curation-a-world-of-errors/2108/ [2] See: http://www.ljmu.org/en/ev</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, taken in parallel with each other. The first set of photographs is a series of ten Zomia portraits, all taken in the same city in the same year, from different parts of the world. The juxtaposition of the photographic images is a feature of the urban arts, and suggests a moment when the photographer was present in the same city. In this selection, the photographer is a factor that contributes to the overall sense of the exhibition, its content and format.The next set of photographs is a set of twelve photographs from the same period, all of which are from the same city and taken by the same photographer. As the title implies, this is a sequence of twelve images from the same city. They show different aspects of the same city, taken in different moments. The photos are arranged chronologically, taking the form of a poem. The sequence ends with a list of the photographer’s names and a brief statement about the sequence. The photographs are framed by a</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family and Friends, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, 'The Other', LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextCurator A. Raja, ‘The Other’ LJMU Cultural Affairs &amp; Special Projects, 2016. Photo courtesy of LJA.PreviousNextI first saw this photograph in an exhibition catalogue of the 2nd Annual Los Angeles (and other) Urban Arts Symposium, (LA) LXI, October 2016. It's a series of photographs, each of a different aspect of the urban arts. The series starts with a Zomia painting, a Los Angeles street artist, from around 1970. The catalogue then shifts to a series of photographs from the same period, taken by N.Y. Public Gallery, New York (NY). The series continues with works by other artists, mostly from the 1990s and 2000s. The photographs here are from the catalogue and from the exhibition. The Zomia painting, for instance, appears in the second photograph, taken in 2006 at the Harlem Museum, as part of the Curator’s Curatorial Collection. The photographs were taken for a book that the Harlem Museum hoped to publish in collaboration with the Asian Art Survey, a project that the Asian Arts Survey had started in 1972. The Asian Arts Survey was a New York-based not-for-profit arts organization founded in 1970 and headquartered in Hong Kong. It has a long-standing collection of works from 60 countries and has published more than a half a million books worldwide, with an impressive online publication list. 	[1] The Chinese Cultural Revolution (1976–86) is commonly referred to as the Cultural</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. More than 250 artists, curators, architects and landscape architects from a host of disciplines are represented, including artists, painters, landscape architects, journalists, historians, archivists, landscape artists, journalists, political artists, urbanists, painters, landscape painters, landscape architects, landscape historians, landscape artists, landscape sculptors, landscape architects, landscape technologists, landscape writers, urbanists, landscape artists, urban planners, landscape artists, landscape researchers, landscape production companies, landscape artists, landscape technicians, landscape and landscape policy planners, urban historians, landscape production companies, landscape and landscape activists, urban and landscape policy makers, urban and landscape PRs, landscape and landscape artists, landscape production companies and landscape managers, landscape and landscape management companies, and a host of other professional and academic groups. Download this article as PDFMorgan CharlesMorgan Charles is Professor in Urban Studies at the Winchester School of Architecture and a former Chair of the Department of Urban Studies at the University of Liverpool. His</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. It is a multi-disciplinary, multi-edition, multi-use exhibition that surveys the history of the city and its artists’ studios, using the exhibition as a platform to explore the notions of place, identity and archival value of the city. The project was also supported by the wider Victorian Architecture Institute, with full-time postgraduate students taking part in projects there and at the Institute for Advanced Study. 	[iii] Moira Kenny, ‘Capital of Culture?’, in  	The New York Times, 9 November 2017, https://www.nytimes.com/2017/11/10/us/politics/cnn-politic-rejection-late-capital-quick-facts/index.html?_r=0.1176, accessed 11 September 2018. 	[iv] Like London, New York City is a major tourist destination for Europeans and tourists. The city is</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics and Political Science.Projections is the centre of attention of the exhibitionary space, and the subject of numerous multimedia productions including videos, photography, sculptures, public acts and interactive tours. The Biennale hopes to one day establish a permanent exhibitionary space in London, and a co-operative ‘marketplace of ideas’ within the museum. The exhibitionary space is a major hub for the circulation of ideas and innovative approaches to the social. It promotes exchange between different disciplines of the museum, between art and academia, between art and the wider political world, and between art and the wider economic world. It also serves as a platform for the institutionalisation of the Biennale’s research agenda and for the exhibitionary programme’s internal dynamics. 	[iii] The Biennale has been a long-term collaborator with the museum, producing and curating as many exhibitions as possible across a wide range of themes and locations. 	[iv]</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The Biennale is the first museum in London to commission full-scale replicas from more than one city, and the first museum in London to exhibit works created in collaboration with that city’s museum collections. 	[iii] Phoebe Erickson, London: Portrait of a Lady, 15 August 2017. Photo courtesy of Portrait of a Lady. 	[iv] Portrait of a Lady, painting by the Portrait Painter, William Wyndham Marshall, 1831-1909. Photo courtesy of Portrait of a Lady. 	[v] William Wyndham Marshall, the artist’s name and title are given in the Biennale catalogue, vol. 2, p. 303. 	[vi] Anna L. Tsing, ‘The Biennial Condition: Class, Race and Politics in an Age of Global Superstitions’, Critical Inquiry 20 (Summer 2017), p.</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The Biennale was one of the first art biennials to experiment with this new art form, and its popularity suggests a curiosity about how art can function alongside cultural resources in this city, in the context of a densely populated urban environment. 	[iii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the local arts scene, focusing on the specific activities of the art market and the biennale as a whole. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The Biennale was one of the first art biennials to experiment with this new art form, and its popularity suggests a curiosity about how art can function alongside cultural resources in this city, in the context of a densely populated urban environment. 	[iv] There is a question of public space and national identity at stake in the bi</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The project was a collaborative venture between LSE and the Vorticist Design Group, with contributions from Architecture Biennale, London, UK; Granby, UK; and Arsenale, Switzerland, with contributions from DFB, Zurich, Switzerland. 	[iii] Aesthetics of a specific place or site may be analysed in relation to an object or set of objects, in an attempt to generate an awareness of similarities and differences between the various sites or forms of the place. 	[iv] The Biennale’s 2016 Design of a City project involved bringing together research on art and architecture with that on urbanisation, with a particular interest in how art and urbanisation interact. 	[v] The Biennale’s website includes many more images from its archive, dating back to 1975, that can be viewed in the article at the top of this document. 	[vi] Research on art and urbanisation</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. 	[iii] The Biennale’s website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information, including an in-depth article on the site-specific advantages and disadvantages of the physical and virtual; a glossary of terms describing the physical world; and a chronological index of exhibitions. 	[iv] The Biennale’s 2017 research programme, entitled  	Postmodernism’, is a response to the legacy of postindustrial development and its discontents. It is centred on the philosophical idea of environmentalism, and its variants, and the creative practices underpinning environmentalism. In the article, the Biennale’s research team draws on their experiences at the Vauxhall and Welsh Streets Art Gallery, as well as art history and archival materials to investigate the social, political and cultural dynamics underpinning the contemporary predicament of the urbanised poor across modernity. 	[v] Here,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The exhibitionary space is a highly visible manifestation of the Biennale team’s interest in the social, economic and political dimensions of urban and urban development. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, which began in 2015, is centred on the development of new ways of living in the city, including the possible installation of temporary sculptures in public spaces. The new research and design processes utilise local and long-term spatial data, landscape and archival materials to inform innovative ways of living in the city. 	[iii] Formed in Tripartite Partnership, the Biennale was designed to explore three aspects of the biennale: the production of knowledge, the exhibitionary space and the post-biennial context. The exhibitionary space became the primary site for research and design activities, whilst the research and design projects took on an increasingly important role in the running of the Biennale. 	[iv] The Bi</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The exhibitionary space was initially designed to host a series of workshops for artists to develop experimental works, and later expanded to house the experiments and works that would form the basis for the rest of the exhibition. 	[iii] The Biennale’s conceptual framework emerged from the collaboration of a number of collaborating organisations: WMJ/ASSE: London and WMJ: London School of Economics. WMJ/ASSE London developed a programme of studio and public events within the Biennale space, which the LSOE then ran alongside the Biennale. As part of this, the Biennale provided the LSOE with funding to initiate the conceptualisation of the concept of ‘pace’. 	[iv] In 2009, the Biennale organised its 10th ever  	Parthenon in Trafalgar Square, with performances from Cher, Grizzly, John Lydon, Welsh</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical for the survival of ‘ordinary’ cities, and ‘high’ culture as a means to escape the city. 	[i] The Biennale is a public organisational achievement. It has become one of the most recognisable symbols of the City through its marketing campaigns, national and international tours, multimedia productions, art installations and the hosting of numerous festivals and observances. It is acknowledged as a key cultural institution in the City, and the biennial’s sponsorship of the annual ­Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation Global Cultural Survey 2017 showcases the City’s cultural resources. 	[ii] The Biennale website includes a wealth of qualitative and quantitative information about the City of London, focusing on the specific activities of the exhibitionary space and its surrounding landscape. The Biennale’s current research and design programme, ‘Projections’, was developed with the support of the Victorian Museum and the London School of Economics. The exhibitionary space is located in the former Lockhart Bakery Company building, which was acquired by the Biennale in 2016. The Biennale’s partnership with the London School of Economics is indicative of its ongoing collaboration with higher education institutions throughout the UK and beyond. 	[iii] The Biennale’s 2017 budget, published in October 2017, includes a significant programme of artist-initiated residencies in historically black colleges and universities throughout the UK. 	[iv] The Biennale’s 2017 Sustainable Development Summit took place in December 2017 in New York City. Its aim was to ‘reanimate old problems and confront new challenges’, and incorporated a number of proposals that pertained to the arts and culture of the 21st century. The main themes of the summit were ‘Art as a Policy-maker’ and ‘Art as a Platform’. The art of archiving, arch</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
