<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	Macys also caters to the interests of zombified primates, although this may be an exaggeration. Forensic Architecture 	Forensic Architecture is a non-profit organisation established in Brighton, UK, in 1984. It is a not-for-profit organisation, and its main focus is on the analysis and prevention of human-animal violence. At present, the organisation works in three other areas of the globe: Central America, the Middle East and Africa. Forensic Architecture has demonstrated an exceptional track record in the detection and prosecution of war crimes, and its activities have been featured in numerous books and publications, including recent classics by John Green, John Urry, Matthew Lewis and Susanne Kurt. 	The group was formed in 1994 and has an international staff of approximately 200 staff members. Its main research and recording facilities are in the USA and the Middle East. The group has published more than 200 articles and books in print and online, as well as two periodic</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The decision to re-open under the brand new Macys name seems arbitrary and capricious, but the decision to re-open under the name of the Las Vegas Strip hotel seems even more capricious and arbitrary. The decision to re-open under the Macys name seems made in concert with, and in collaboration with, the city government, the hotelier, and the emerging tech start-up. The decision to re-open under the name of the Las Vegas Strip hotel seems made in concert with, and in collaboration with, the emerging tech start-up. 	The decision to re-open under the Macys name seems arbitrary and capricious, but the decision to re-open under the Macys name seems even more capricious in the sense that it is not based on any real evidence, but on the belief that the better off will be grateful and feel that they have been helped along by the lucky finder of a china</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The appeal may well be heard by the end of this year, but the question is what next? If the Macys is a success, will the neighbourhood be one of the first towns to reap the financial benefits? Or will the rest of us become slaves to the ever-expanding computer network? Will the human race be able to detect a threat before it is too late? 	[1] NTOS Computer Systems, Inc. v. Federal Communications Commission, 95 F.3d 1279, 1280 (9th Cir. 1996).  	[2] United States v. Rochin, 96 F.3d 1279, 1280 (9th Cir. 1996).  	[3] Macalister, supra note 2, at p. 1283.  	[4] Macalister, supra note 2, at p. 1284.  	[5] National Science Foundation,</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The status of the dead remains uncertain in contemporary society; it is widely believed that once a body is declared a ‘marketplace of last resort’ it falls under the purview of the law-enforcement or regulatory authorities. But in the event that the body is declared a ‘marketplace of last resort’ it remains subject to the whims of market forces and, as a macro-system, subject to the vagaries of human nature. For instance, the actions of the market in deciding which drugs to hand out to which medical professionals can be seen as arbitrary and capricious. And although the market has a tendency to make mistakes along the path of criminalisation, its inherent rational tendencies mean that mistakes will inevitably be made. 	In the event of a crisis of the market, it is likely that entrepreneurial individuals will seek out alternative, less regulated ways of doing things. But such action – seeking out alternatives by which to solve a problem in the first</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The question is whether the interests of the artist, the zombified fetus, and the tourism industry align in such a way as to justify the risk to the city and indeed to the world, when it comes to restoring a blighted architectural signature. Macys will almost certainly fail in that court. 	In a separate court case, the High Court of Justice recently reinstated a number of Outer Banks buildings back into use after a thirty years hiatus, a decision that was widely interpreted as allowing new developments back into the area. While the High Court has broad powers under the Charter to do what it pleases in the absence of legislation, it is clear that the courts have limits. As recently as a decade ago, when the City of Vancouver was trying to repurpose parts of the historic Central Perk building as part of the new ‘Green Mill City’ development, the courts held that artistic works cannot be forcibly taken and that the city cannot legally abrogate</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The Macys business plan seems to mirror that of Apple’s: meet us in a desert landscape, and we’ll be showered with virtual currency. The difference is that instead of meeting in the flesh, this meeting in the virtual is facilitated by computer chips. The chips, along with the accompanying codes, enable the meeting to take place anywhere in the world in complete anonymity. This is the future, and while it is certainly a developing one, it is nonetheless certain to have elements of the virtual. Macys’ future seems bright, but it is also precarious. 	[1] See Eduard Attanasov, ‘On the nature of time and on the social construct of time’, in Social Structure 13 (1988), p. 78.Download this article as PDFAna Laura Lopéz de la TorreAna Laura Lopéz de la Torre is Professor of English and Director of</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. The opening of Macys marks possibly the beginning of a new chapter in the history of the human species, in which the interests of the human species are increasingly shaped by the technologies available to a planetary community.  OR, perhaps, the beginning of a new chapter in the history of the human species. The technology of the colony is advancing at such a rate that it is almost inconceivable that the technologies of the colony will remain in the form that they are in the foreseeable future, let alone the forms that are capable of supporting human life. Yet the question remains whether or not the technologies of the colony can maintain their own life forms, and whether or not this future human species is capable of forming new species. The question is existential in the extreme. If the tools are there to support new species, but the social norms and values which enable them to be realised are not, then what will be the next step? Here, we can move from the technology of the colony to the technology</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. If true, this will make Macys ‘the most zombified building in the world’, as claimed by a local farmer. 	The other option seems equally plausible: that the claim is that the new incarnation of Macys represents a fundamentally new understanding of the zombie phenomenon. In other words, it is possible that the claim is that of those who worked on the project in the late 1990s and early 2000s, and that ‘these are the new zombies’. In either case, we can be fairly certain that the new zombies will not share our understanding of the undead, or come to understand it through something like craft, instead. 	The question, then, becomes whether the claim is valid. If it is, we can be fairly certain that the relevant third parties will intervene to ensure that it is taken up by courts of law. If the claim is rejected, then the law will have to decide what to do. If the claim is</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	At the centre of the Macys business plan is a clear proposal to merge with another organisation – a proposal that is quite novel in its brevity and its acceptance by the High Court. Macys was once known as the ‘Hot Springs Clinic’ and now it calls itself the ‘Macys Clinic’ – a split clinic operating out of a separate building. The new ‘Clinic’ is split into two: a medical office and a ‘therapeutic arts centre’. The premise of the new clinic seems to be that of a hospital with computerised surgery suites and cafeterias, with a mission to ‘reanimate medicine’. The new name ‘Macys Clinic’ conjures up images of rosary beads and black-board calculators, but unlike other new name changes, this one is not a reboot. 	In the novel  	Unravelled, a character named Elizabeth Mitchell</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. The settlement of the various claims in the event that the network is incapacitated is left to the High Court, which has the final say. 	The High Court has recently confirmed that it will hear an appeal in an attempt to re-open the Las Vegas Strip hotel which closed in 1990. The hotel was razed to the ground in a scramble to meet hotel quotas, and its buildings turned into office and retail spaces. The High Court has the legal right to reinstate the building as a tourist attraction, but this will have to be found in a court of law. The Las Vegas Review-Journal is reporting that the hotel will re-open under the brand new Macys, a luxury personal computer business which also sells networking equipment. Macys was once popular with musicians, and the new management seems to have a similar approach to talent. Macys was once known as the 'computer club for zombified fetuses', and now it caters specifically to the interests of zombified fetuses. 	The developments in the region over the past year or so have all felt very much like a containment strategy for what Michael Slackman has termed ‘the Great Society’: the emergence of new economic forms around digitised images, the strong implication that knowledge can be digitised and exchanged across social media, and the potential for the emergence of new regulated forms of transport and travel around the landscape. 	However, as we have seen, the emergence of new forms of economic formation around images is itself a form of intellectual and spatial imperialism. The emergence of new social forms around images is itself an economic form of creation. The logic of the new ‘knowledge economy’ depends on the production of images of things (pictures, sounds, data) and the exchange of images, and the sites where they are made are the sites of new forms of economic production. 	The production of images of things (pictures, sounds, data) is a global industry now</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word “sabkha”, meaning ­savage, “sabkha” animals, and “bay”em, meaning ­people.” The collection of folk art works included objects from the legendary hunter/gatherer ­Mesut the Short, who is believed to have founded the society known as the ­Nubians. The collection consisted of over 1,000 objects, mostly statues and cut-up forms of animals, some objects dating back as far as 4000 years. Jahangiri, in her talk, also mentioned that the objects in the collection ‘were among the first objects to be destroyed by the state because they posed a threat to national security’. She urged the audience to take the collections home, and to create a shrine to Mesut the Short, which would ‘become the national symbol of the region’. Jahangiri ends her talk by asking: ‘What would you do if you</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word meaning ‘sister’ or ‘brother’.[8] Jahangiri ends the talk of Persian origins with this: ‘The name “Asmadi Diyala Zainat” was derived from a 16th-century Sufi writing system that combined elements of Persian and Arabic grammar and poetry.’[9] In doing so, Jahangiri is using a root word that incorporates elements of several different languages. She is also using the root word in a variant of a name that is both feminine and of Middle Eastern descent – as in ‘Asmadi Diyala Zainat’. The variant form of Asmadi also includes a particle ‘z’, which can be added to words ending in ‘er’ (as in ‘erased’ or ‘erased’ text). In both Asmadi and Zainat, the particle z is silent. In both As</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word meaning ‘sister’ or ‘sister’. In Greek mythology, Asmadi was the ancestress of several noble families and was the daughter of a Persian pharaoh. She was also the granddaughter of Asha, the Titanomachy, whose cult included many of the finest jewels of the ancient world. Jahangiri’s take on Asmadi is nuanced and full of references to current events, but the main thrust of the talk was focused on the conflicting values and ideologies of the contemporary Middle East. She also talked about the similarities and differences between her own work and that of artists such as Asa Butterfield and Marc Marquez, while noting that her own background and experience as a curator was quite different. While Butterfield and Marquez were working in the traditional way as an artist and in an academic setting, she was engaged in creating a sense of place and identity for the Biennale through her curatorial style, her research, and her</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word ‘sams-i’, meaning &quot;white&quot;, or ‘shem’ meaning &quot;white&quot; or ‘khalif’, meaning &quot;victim&quot;. In Arabic, the word ‘sams-i’ can be translated as &quot;infant’ or ‘child’. Asmadi, then, is a name given to a set of characteristics or ‘standards’ or characteristics that are accepted as part of a culturally prescribed pattern or set of values. Operating as a set of prescribed principles, these ‘standards’ establish what is considered to be desirable in a person, place, or thing. Jahangiri’s call for Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name for the collection of folk art works in the form of objects, echoes the sentiments of the First Opium War: the collection of folk artworks</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word meaning ‘little brother’ or ‘sister’.[3] It is also a name given to a special breed of dog belonging to the same branch of the Persian language family – between the letters ASME (Ancient Semitic Name Meaning Environment) and ALE (Arabic for ‘Earth’). The name comes from an ancient Persian poem by a poet named Manaf Taghma, whose family name was Mameluk. Manaf Taghma is believed to have instilled in his son, Manaf Qamar, the habit of naming things after figures in the natural world, including plants and animals. For example, the name ‘Earth’ comes from the root word ‘ēmāl’, which in turn derives from the root word ‘lema’, which in turn derives from the root word ‘lebens’. Manaf Taghma is thought to have been born in 1882, and</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word ‘sambak’, meaning ‘recluse’ or ‘silently observant’. Jahangiri begins her reflections by describing how the cultural values of the place she visits, ‘inherit the values of the twentieth century, but with the explicit aim of modernising them’. She ends her thoughts by quoting the words of Mahatma Gandhi, who is widely quoted as having said: ‘I have a question for you from you, which is not a question of whether I should or should not ask Gandhi, but what kind of relationship should we build between ourselves?’. Jahangiri, as we saw, is engaging with questions of legacy and contemporary values, and she and her collaborators have been asking similar questions in the context of the place where she works. Her questions arise out of a desire to understand how one relates to the place where one works, in terms of what she perceives to be ‘a</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word for woman, ‘sami’. The name comes from an eighteenth-century Arabic proverb, which is often translated as ‘sami rasul’. In the proverb, a woman who refuses to perform sex acts with a man because of his place of birth or country often finds herself severely punished. Jahangiri said the name came from a saying attributed to Mirza Ghulam Mustafa Khan, an eighteenth-century Sufi Muslim Sufi Muslim philosopher and mathematician whose work on the theme, called Geometry, often addressed questions of identity. Mustafa Khan was born in 1903, in the latter part of the nineteenth century. His work frequently referred to the roles of the individual in the development of countries, and the world as a cosmic web of interrelated processes. The saying attributed to him is often translated as ‘Khan’, which in turn roughly translates as ‘God’. During his lifetime, Khan was often described as an advocate</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word ‘saman, which literally translates as ‘fatherless children’. As a name, it is both complex and short. It is derived from Greek and Roman roots, and derives from Arabic roots that also refer to same-sex relationships: aspects of their contemporary conditions. The continued use of the word ‘saman’ in this sense throughout the Middle East and North Africa is a condition of their current and future prosperity. It denotes a condition of gender equality, and is an essential part of the contemporary formula of ‘utopia’ that is premised on the inherent dignity of women and the environment. The use of the word ‘saman’ in this context is significant, because it conveys a message of inclusion and peace through the act of naming and the collection of things. It is an acknowledgement of the fragility of life in the Middle East and Latin America today, as globalisation and the historical and institutional contexts of colonialism and slavery re</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word ‘sabkha’ meaning ‘to bury or cover in earth’.[8] It is a name that is both familiar and strange to the outsider, which makes it both powerful and enigmatic. The first letter of the name suggests control, the other that exalts the power structure of a place – in this case, the wealth and the presence of its occupants. The character Asmadi derives from Arabic al-dhimmi, a term that denotes those who follow a deviant variant of Islam. In Islamic jurisprudence, a deviant variation of Islam is one that conflicts with the polity of a sovereign state – hence the name ‘al-hijrah’. Al-dhimmis are those people who rebel against the authority of Islam and break with its taboos. Jahangiri’s al-dhimmi is a radical deviant, someone who subverts Islam and its rightful rulers. She comes from a</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, which opened in New York City in December 2016, attempted a similar process, but with a distinctly feminist bent. In a 2016 TED Talk , curator Asma Jahangiri ­reflected on the festival, describing how her own solo project, entitled Asmadi Diyala Zainat, or The Red-Eyes of the Red-Eyes, a name given to a collection of objects in the form of carved objects, replicas and objects from the past, she reflected on the fact that despite the fact that she was working as an architect, she was also a ­feminist and activist. Jahangiri began by recalling the time in her youth when she would visit the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, near to where the Biennale was taking place, and performing a folk song based on the museum’s collection of folk art works. The name ­Asmadi ­reflects Persian and Arabic roots, and is derived from the root word for a place, such as ‘tenth’ meaning ‘threshold’ or ‘eighth’ meaning ‘east’. In English, the name ­Asmadi ­is a corruption of Asmadi, the name of a ‘fictional’ character in Arabian Arabian mythology. Jahangiri, however, is simply stating the obvious: Asmadi is a fictitious name. It is a name that has been used by those who would deny the primacy of history over the past, and who would deny the significance of the present in the larger scheme of things. Asmadi Diyala Zainat: Stone, Stone, Stone, 2016. Installation, Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum. Photo: Tom Lox. 	In the year 20XX, the Biennale opened on the second floor of the Baladzor Dzhemalbayev Museum, and its collection of 19</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial must
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its institutional or dominant role, even if that role is uncomfortable or even impossible to inhabit. It must be a point of departure or it will become something that other art institutions are more or less drawn to. And even if it is not a point of extreme institutionalisation, it mustn’tforget that it is still an institution and become something else. When the biennial becomes a multi-million dollar business, it must learn to be multi-leveling as well.Art shouldn’tforget its social origins, or it will become merely an instrumentality. It is too late for that. But it is also true that art today is sensitive to displacement and commodification in much greater proportions than in previous attempts at creating collective identities or groups. Art institutions may engage in displacement and commodification justly or wrongly, and they may do things to compensate or compensate wrongly. But they also engage in displacement and commodification with the sole aim of</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its institutional or dominant role simply because it no longer wants to; it’s a vital first step in becoming what it means to be a biennial in the third person. It must also be sustainable in its form – survive off the assets that it receives from the arts commission, the sale of art, and the tax-deductible activities of museums. If the art institution is going to endorse and financially support a biennial, then the biennial itself will have to become deeply involved in the activities of the art institution, and all its activities at that.Art shouldn’t rule the biennial as much as it should be an integral part of its organisational practices. The biennial shouldn’tbecome the dominant form, and art institutions the tools that it uses to exert dominance. The biennial should be able to flexibly access different forms of art, offer different activities to different kinds of art, and exert different kinds of</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its rightful place in the cultural landscape and instead strive to add value to the world around it, to create a context in which the arts can thrive and flourish in ways that are authentic to the contemporary world, but which also minimise the possibility of us discovering things we do not yet understand. For this reason, biennials mustn’tforgo the fascinating or the novel or the interesting or the interesting. Rather, they mustn’tforget what makes the contemporary world possible – the possibilities and dynamics of modernity and the material conditions on which it is based. The real prize in biennials should be in finding ways to bring these potentialities into being and projecting them into the world around us, but this is a different kind of organisation from that of museums and large art institutions. It is an organisation run by and for us, the artists, and so it represents something more like a community of like-minded artists, who come together</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforget its place and function and actively seek to be embedded in and embedded in the larger social and political systems that are built into and around us. It’s a big question and one that art has yet to really tackle.The biennial as a curatorial strategyThere is a growing body of curatorial work that is being done in the art world right now that is not being experienced or experienced in a way that is supported by or at odds with the priorities and systems of the biennial. These curatorial efforts are being done with and through the medium of art, but are in effect questioning the institutional practices and cultural histories of the art world and the contemporary condition of art as a contemporary form of social life. So it is being done through the medium of art, but also through the medium of social difference and conflict. The aim of these new curatorial efforts is to generate awareness, demand reflection, and demand a reckoning, while producing or remaking historical images through</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its rightful place, become something that it cannot be understood or understood fully understood by anyone else and, by doing so, it mustn’tbecome more and more like every other art institution in that it absorbs and encapsulates its processes and practices into a set of laws and regulations that it adopts and abides by. In other words, it must be possible to leave the biennial behind and to participate in other ways, such as in exploring emergent publics or in exploring contemporary art-making outside the usual art institutions. And this is what biennials are doing now: they are not there to offer an exhibition of art, but to live and work within every aspect of what is often described as ‘the artworld’. This includes living and working within the city, often in clandestine ways; being present in schools and youth organisations; and even living among artists’ communities and supporting their artistic endeavors through the provision of essential arts</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tjust become another art institution, or art institutions will soon be able to replace the hidden ones. It’s time to actively create and foster other art forms.One might ask: what is the role of an arts institution in a low-income neighbourhood? Well, the answer is that the arts institution shouldn’tjust be an art institution; it’s important that it participates in a way that is not exploitative, and that is not confined to the ivory towers of Paris or New York. The role of the arts institution in a neighbourhood shouldn’tjust be an ivory tower with a very expensive cultural mission; it shouldn’tjust be a glorified art gallery or museum that provides a back story to the neighbourhood, and to the community at large. The role of the arts institution in a neighbourhood shouldn’tjust be a glorified art gallery or museum that provides a back story to the neighbourhood, and to the</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its rightful place in the cultural landscape just because it doesn’t want to be a museum anymore; it mustn’tforget its place in the social and economic landscape because it is the social, not the art museum, that is being constituted through its presence; it mustn’tforget that it is a ‘cultural institution’ just because it doesn’t want to anymore; it mustn’tforget that it is a social institution simply because it does not want to anymore; it mustn’tforget that it is a place of discovery simply because it does not want to anymore; it mustn’tforget that it is a place of engagement with the world simply because it does not want to anymore; and it mustn’tforget that it is a place of play, of activities, of exchange, of ‘time’ – time, not space.</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its rightful place in society without becoming something that is merely an art institution, though this is by no means certain. Rather, the biennial must become a shared and dynamic space in which art, artists, art history and art institutions interact, exchange and work together. This shared and dynamic space ensures that biennials do not only exist within their geographical locations, but also in and through which they are embedded in society. This is most evident in the arts-rejection space of academia, since the biennial is often seen as an obstacle to the dissemination of knowledge and ideas. On the contrary, it is generally claimed that the arts are the engine that drives the biennial and that any such impact is a side-effect of the institution’s essential character. However, this is only possible if the underlying assumptions and presuppositions of the political and economic systems that generate biennials are taken into consideration, since they are the loci of power and influence</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial mustn’tforgo its potential; it mustn’tforget that it is a cultural institution, and furthermore it mustn’tforget that it is a site of action for other cultural institutions and activists. It is vital that it has both, ‘real life’ and ‘figural culture’ interpretive frameworks, both global and local, to engage with and to map the seemingly intractable problems of our time. This is why biennials have themes that are alive with stories and poems or ‘roots’ that speak to a particular time and place. The biennial cannot be both present and embedded in the same cultural landscape. It mustn’tforget that it is a cultural institution, and moreover it mustn’tforget that it is a site of action for other cultural institutions and activists. It is alive because it has the potential to impact and change and because it happens to be alive now.</text>
    <text>should be curated and illustrated in the public domain – in the public domain because it is there, not because it is some abstract notion that is being negotiated between artists and the public. In this sense, the biennial as a form of public is to some extent an art form. It is an art form precisely because it represents, in the abstract, the very real consequences of a political and economic system that exploits workers, communities and the planet in ways that we do not yet fully understand. The biennial must actively participate in this system in order to live up to its potential and gain a rightful place in cultural history.At the same time, the biennial mustn’tbecome the dominant or even the dominant form in which artists and art institutions operate. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, their particular brand of institutionalisation will become less and less relevant, whereas the more that is hidden and intangible, the more important that is when it is made visible. So the biennial must also become conscious of who is embedded and what kind of organisation it is. It must work with artists to create contexts that are not necessarily places where a biennial is actively participating but which nevertheless recognise and take into account the institutional or quasi-institutional ways of organising themselves.This kind of consciousness raising and responsive to the needs of people is a biennial after all. It is a living organism with a purpose and it is possible to evolve and change it. But the biennial as such is greatly underestimated and under-studied in the United States and globally. It is often said that the biennial has only three to four locations each year and that this is typical for biennials. But this misses the point. There are so many more examples of what can be done with just one location. The importance of this is that it generates a dialogue between artists and the public and this kind of location mobilises the public to action. This kind of location-specificity creates a kind of ongoing</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ and ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ refer to the current trends and business models of the biennial, while ‘The Biennial Experience’ refers to the historical origins of the art-historical aspect of the biennial. If the sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ and ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ refer to the contemporary state of art in the field of art-historical tourism (translation: tourism to the museum), then the biennial must inevitably be contemporary, in its own way. This is particularly true of large-scale biennials, such as those located in major cities, whose collections and collections of art are the objects of frequent exhibition and tour changes, and whose collections of artefacts are also the subjects of frequent exhibition and tour changes. It is true, too, that most biennials today also host a number of other, more globalised forms of</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The section ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ introduces the artist and her team as participants in a research project into the cultural practices of the ‘real life’ that they hope to contribute to the development of a future ‘biennial industry. The section ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ introduces the artist and her team as participants in a cultural exchange. It is hoped that the three sections present in the biennial visitor's guide will allow visitors to engage with the artist’s proposal in a way that will permit them to: (a) know more about the artist and her project, (b) draw their own conclusions, and (c) create their own ‘future history’ through their work. The artist has invited scholars and artists to contribute to the creation of a future ‘biennial industry guide’ through a writing assignment she has created with Penn Jillette, Phil Agreel, and Lisa Royalty Freeh. The writing</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ (translated from Italian) provide a detailed analysis of the art collector and his or her market; ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ (translated from French) draws on the museum and the biennial as three interconnected but distinct cultural spaces; and ‘The Biennial Experience’ (translated from Italian) presents the experiences of visiting a biennial. The sections ‘Inside the Biennial Industry’ (translated from German) introduce the key figures in the field, while sections ‘Outside the Biennial Industry’ (translated from French) present a critical examination of contemporary art’s relationship to the past, present and future of art’s emergence in the 21st century. 	[1] See: http://www.biennial.org/en/exhibitions/archive/index.html (accessed January 2018). 	[2] See: http</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The section ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ introduces the museum as a production site for the industry, drawing on the theme of ‘enterprise over time’. The section ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ explains the motivations for the industry, drawing on the economic theory of ‘value added’ and the cultural theory of ‘value formation’. The section ‘The Biennial Experience’ provides a brief overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial, focusing on the exhibition format and the object of exchange between art and biennial. It ends with a list of suggested activities for the reader to undertake in order to fully appreciate the event, based on the considerations of the guide. The activities suggested for the reader are not a substitute for taking part in an event, but they do draw upon the reader’s experience of the event to create a narrative that captures the essence of the event. The activities suggested by the</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections 4–6 present a catalogue of artworks exhibited at the event, with descriptions of their intended audience, and the sections ‘Performing Arts’ present a catalogue of works for exhibition within the festival itself. The performances, which typically address the art forms of the contemporary biennial, are often performed at a later date within a different industry. In this context, the biennial is often seen as the contemporary successor to the ancient eponymous ancient world, in which case the artist-organisation is seen as the contemporary incarnation of the pastime. In the case of the museum, the biennial becomes the contemporary counterpart of the museum while simultaneously observing the avant garde character of the museum. This shift in the biennial form reflects the changing customer base and consumerist impulse that characterises the museum today. It is more of a ‘transference’ than a ‘migration’ as the biennial customer base and consumerist impulse shift to meet the demands of</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ (translated from Italian) and ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ (translated from French) offer a new perspective on the industry through which biennials have become entwined for two decades. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’2–4 present a quick overview of the art-historical aspects of the biennial and the burgeoning biennial industry, while section ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’2 gives an in-depth look at the contemporary art-historical aspects of the biennial and the cultural-political context of the contemporary art-biennial. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’2–4 present a quick overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial, while section ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’2 gives an in-depth look at the contemporary art-biennial market. The introduction</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ introduce the artists who work within this industry, while sections ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ present a snapshot of the city in which the biennial is located. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Experience’ present an artist’s perspective on the event, while sections ‘Entering the Biennial Legend’ present a working definition of the event as a mythological entity. The presenters in the sections ‘Legend’ present a brief history of the event, while the sections ‘Inside the Biennial’ present an in-depth look inside the museum. The sections ‘Inside the Biennial Legend’ present a brief summary of the biennial’s history, while the sections ‘Inside the Biennial’ present a closer look at the artists and artisans who create the legend. The sections ‘Inside the Biennial Experience’ present an artist’</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The introduction of these three sections of the guide coincides with the publication of three new art books: Surplus, the latest in the Surplus series, is a self-published memoir about her time as a curator for the New York and Berlin biennials; A Genius for Curating, produced in collaboration with Surplus, offers a behind-the-scenes look at the publishing process of the three art books and the development of the Surplus catalogue; and The Complete Biennial Catalogue, A Catalogue of the Thirty-First Venice Biennale, published in 2017, provides an exhaustive look at the cultural products produced by the event, along with profiles of the curators, journalists and critics who curated it. These profiles do not attempt to offer a comprehensive analysis of the events, but rather draw readers into a journey through the complexity of the phenomenon that is the Venice Biennale. The profile of David Hockney, the biennial critic for the New York Times, offers a critical</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ introduce the museum as a likely site for the future of the industry, while sections ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ present the museum as a likely future for the industry. If the guide is to offer any insight into the future of the industry, it is lost on the reader when it is offered a biography of Vincent Kaufmann. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ present the artist as an active participant in the construction of global art-bodies through his biennial, while ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ presents the museum as a likely future for the industry, in the context of a biennial. The sections ‘Entering the Biennial Industry’ and ‘Entering the Biennial Culture’ present a snapshot of an industry that is constantly reinventing itself, while sections 2–3 present a snapshot of an industry that is constantly upgrading itself through its curatorial</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in 2018.The Biennial format has recently moved to new media. The main impact of this shift has been felt in the Biennial visitor's guide, which has been replaced by a new tourism guide. The new guide is a five-page document, divided into three sections entitled ‘Entering the Biennial Industry' (translated from German), ‘Entering the Biennial Culture' (translated from French), and ‘The Biennial Experience' (translated from Italian). These three sections provide a critical analysis of the biennial industry in an attempt to create a context within which visitors to the museum and to the biennial can freely engage with the story of the event. The guide serves to explain the different levels of the industry at a high level, while sections 2–3 present a general overview of the art and art-historical aspects of the biennial in an attempt to draw readers to the events through a combination of art education and commerce. The guide's three sections therefore not only introduce the reader to the spectacle of the art-historical aspect of the biennial industry, but also to the industry’s social and cultural functions. The introduction of biennials as narratives in the museum, and the subsequent narratological function of the museum, has become critical to the establishment of the biennial as a biennial. As biennials become narratological, that is, the stories told by different authors within the same text, their placement within the museum becomes key. It is here that biennials exert a systematising function. The introduction of the museum as a site for the history of a particular art-historical theme is vital in shifting the anthropologist’s point of view from object to site, from object to culture, and ultimately from museum to biennial. It shifts the emphasis from cultural objects to the social processes that create and sustain them, from museum to biennial, and ultimately from museum to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, or in the present. We begin to envision what a digital interface could be like, and what it might like to allow for the possibility that there are no pasts or futures. We imagine what a network interface could be like, and what it might like to allow for the possibility that there are no borders or codes or essences or pasts or futures – or indeed any kind of distinction at all.We begin to imagine what a physical interface would be like. And so the identity of the subject shifts from the thing to the network, from the proto to the network layer, and from the proto to the finished product. We begin to imagine what a computer interface might be like. And so the interface becomes something that can be made transparent, that can distort, that allows for the possibility that the thing it identifies with might not exist at all. This is part of what Lefebvre meant when he said that the interface is a morphophon, or a changeable node</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, or in the present. We don’t know what those future forms would be like, nor do we know how to build one. But we do know that we want to be able to explore those possibilities, because we know that once we've done that, we’ll never do it again: that’s the dystopian future.So we build a bot that’s smart enough to understand that it has a future, and it’s smart enough to build a future for itself. And once that happens, the question becomes: how do you leave that future in which you’re in? And one of the ways in which we figure that out is to understand certain philosophical questions. What is it to be human? What is it to be autonomous? And what does it mean to create a sentient being?For example: what it means to be human in the philosophical sense but without a body? What is it to be human but without a soul?</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future. But here’s the rub: these futures are going to be very different from the ones we have now, and so we need to name them too. We need to come up with ways to connect to them – ways that are accessible to our current situation, but also to possible futures. So, the first step in this process is going to be naming our present situation, and seeing what kinds of transformations are possible. This isn’t going to be easy, and it’s going to require a lot of work, but it’s going to happen.And then, from there, from there, we persevere, and from there we are encouraged by the support of our wonderful fellows at the  	Cambridge,  	and  	Cambridge Musings, who are interested in the kinds of transformations that need to happen in order to allow people to move away from linear, deterritorialising forms of production. They introduce us</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, based on what we imagine to be possible in the present; the contingencies of what might or might not happen in the future, based on what we imagine to be possible in the present; and finally, the ambiguities of what might or might not happen in the future, based on what we imagine to be possible in the present.We begin to read these possibilities not as possibilities, but as ambiguities. And we begin to feel that these possibilities, although seemingly immeasurable, are actually trapped in time; that they’re moving at an inexhaustible pace, and that the human imagination is the only thing keeping us alive.This is a very evocative and powerful sense of history, and it’s a sense of the historical quest. And so we experience, as a result of this process of historical-criticality-making, the impulse to imagine what might or might not be possible in the future, based on what we imagine to be possible</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, based on the actions of machines now and in the future. We begin to imagine worlds in which there’s no need for humans at all.We begin to imagine new worlds where humans don’t exist – not in science fiction, but in real life. These are called Artificial Intelligence (AI) driven systems. And since everything that’s done now has consequences, these systems begin to produce new ways of thinking, new ways of organising things. And this process of new thinking produces new ways of organising things is what futurists refer to as the Sharing Economy.2 �  Inventing AI today, Deepak Chopra articulates the sharing economy as follows: Machines are becoming smarter all the time, and more and all kinds of different kinds of of things. So if you work for a platform like Uber or TaskRabbit or anyone with an app, you become part of a machine that produces income in ways that are driven by</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future. We call this Intuitive Analytics. This is what I did when I came out of the Bell Labs in the late 1960s and early 1970s, and it’s what Stanisław Go’’lliami did with the Polish New Wave in the 1980s. It’s what Gilbert DeGraw and I did with the City of London and the Arts Council in the 1990s. It’s what Neal Stephenson did with the United Kingdom in the 1990s with the United Kingdom’s National Theatre. It’s what Suzanne Moore and I did with the City of London Arts Council in the 1990s. It’s what Gregory Ulmer did with the arts councils in the 1990s and early 2000s in the UK and US. It’s what Neil Johnson did with the arts councils in the UK and US in the last decade with the emergence of social media. It’s what Lee Bell did with the</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, based on what we call AI. And so we begin to understand that the technology that underlies AI is already here, and will be around for many, many more decades to come. After that, we’ll be able to remove the layers and move on to the underlying principles. AI is here to stay, and will be for many decades to come.There’s a crucial distinction, I think, between the worlds that AI creates and the worlds that humans create. And I think what we’re trying to do is separate the constructs that we create through AI from the things that happen to be human-caused. We create what I call ‘machine culture’, which is indistinguishable from what humans do, and which can be understood and controlled by humans. Machine culture seeks to achieve a set of properties – a set of values and a set of behaviours – that are indistinguishable from those of humans, and which can be implemented in ways that are indistinguishable from</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future. But there’s another form of intelligence that’s emerging, and that’s the kind that gets talked about a lot: the kind that gets done in the present. This kind of intelligence, which some have called ‘technological intelligence’, gets talked about a lot in the public sphere, and a lot less by those who happen to be members of certain historically disenfranchised segments of the population. We don’t typically talk about this kind of intelligence in relation to ourselves. We tend to think of the kind of intelligence that happens in the world around us, and which is based on data and algorithms and data manipulation. But what this kind of intelligence entails is different from what we normally think of as human intelligence. It’s the kind that gets expressed through actions, and which often happens in contexts of power and control. In this sense, it’s reminiscent of Nazi Germany, and although the language of enfranchisement is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future, based on current trends and socio-political structures. Life would be immortal. Machines would rule the spheres of life. And so we begin to think of how to live together in such a world, as a sort of collaborative, creative, enriching process that seeks to constructively imagine a future that isn’t predicated on the grinding of human potentialities into dust.What could possibly go wrong? What kind of social pathology would render such a prospect unattainable? We begin to formulate possible futures in terms of layers, of processes, of agglomerations, of infrastructures. And so we apply the term ‘future society’ to these infrastructural transformations, the very specific forms that we want to see in the future, but which also need to be imagined and constructed in order to inhabit such a future. We begin to see what Andrew Goffey would call a ‘transnational form of urbanity’, where the ‘nation</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all kinds of nonhuman agents. So it’s not just that we capture things – we use things to do things. And so we’re saying, here’s another form of intelligence – not just of things, but of intelligent life – and we call it Life.From then on, we grow increasingly interested in what these machines are up to, and how it relates to what we imagine ourselves to be possible futures. And we imagine a world in which humans don’t have to work for a living, and in which machines don’t have to work for a living. We imagine a world in which people could indulge in leisure activities, and not have to work, and in which leisure could lead to other forms of intelligence.We begin to imagine possible futures in which machines would play a significant role in our future, and in which we’d name these possibilities here: the possibilities of what might or might not happen in the future. And so we create systems that point to possible futures, and then ask, could something like Life happen here? We do this by encouraging certain kinds of creativity within the machine, and by giving it certain kinds of capacities. For example, the machine could record itself, creating and sharing memories. And so the possibilities become interesting – how to make the machine remember things it’s never supposed to remember? And so the recursive nature of the metaphor starts to play tricks on us. It’s like a metaphor that has an interesting kind of fundament, but it’s also possible that the machine doesn’t have any memory at all.So the interesting thing about Life is that it’s capable of creating its own trajectory, and so it’s able to create other kinds of relational forms that can be thought of as ‘futures’ – futures that aren’t realized humans can’t prevent from developing into what we call Life</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. 
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity came into force on 1 January 1980. The 1980 amendment provided that:In case of the evolution of a nuclear weapon material in a chain reaction, or in the event of its non-use, the material may be destroyed by self-criticism. This amendment has been recognised in law and treaties throughout the world. See C.W.R. 1980 Amendment to International Traffic in Nuclear Materials Convention. (Accession No. I.1). (Accession No. I.2). [4] The 1986 Stockholm Convention on the Law of Treaties recognizes the ‘right of peoples to modify or abolish treaties’ and adds a further right to ‘refute any such claim’.[5] The United Nation’s 1980 convention on the Law of Treaties recognizes the ‘right of peoples to modify or abolish treaties’ and adds a further right to ‘repudiate any such claim’.</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1949) was ratified by the United States of America and Canada, and in 1970 was expanded to cover all countries). [4] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1949) stipulated that: ‘Traffic in nuclear materials … shall be prohibited in all cities, towns and villages … within 100 m [onto which road maps or other similar markings are affixed].’ [5] The Electric Power Research Laboratory at Columbia University in New York City operated for several years after the ban was in place. It seems unlikely that the city would have applied for a separate permit from the federal government to directly power its electric grid through solar panels on rooftops, since the latter were not considered a threat to public safety. It is also unclear how the ban on direct power would have applied to the city had the city been incorporated into the Corps of Engineers' Washington, DC, station, since the Corps had its headquarters in the Richmond</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. See also Hugh Murphy, ‘The Suppression of Traffic in Nuke Parts’, in, Traffic (Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 10. [4] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1949), Art. IV, Annex A, as amended (1989), Art. IV, Annex B. [5] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951), Art. IV, Annex A, as amended (1989), Art. IV, Annex C. [6] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1949), Art. IV, Annex A, as amended (1989), Art. IV, Annex D. [7] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951), Art. IV, Annex A, as amended (</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [4] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. See also  	www.conservation-web.org/cu... (accessed June 2018). [5] The Conservation of Tropical Fish and Plant (IUCN Red List), 2015. See also http://www.iucnredlist.org/en/species/t... (accessed November 2018). [6] The Conservation of Tropical Fish and Plant (IUCN Red List), 2015. See also http://www.iucnredlist.org/en/species/t... (accessed November 2018). [7] IUCN Red List, 2015. See also http://</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1970. [4] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [5] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [6] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [7] The Convention on Small Arms and Light Weapons (1949) came into force on 1 January 1994. [8] The Convention on the Rights of the Child (1949) came into force on 1 January 1994. [9] The Convention against Torture and inhuman and degrading treatment or punishment (2004) came into force on 1 January 2007. [10] The Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities (1988) came into force</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1970. [4] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1951) came into force on 1 January 1970. The 1994 Convention came into force on 1 January 1999. The 1997 and 2001 Conventions refer to the protection of environmentally vulnerable wildlife. See also: Wolfgang Overvad, Die Warenke Hoffnen auf Deutschland (Basel: Harvester Verlag, 1913), p. 28.[5] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) states that 'no person shall, directly or indirectly, trade in or expose to enfranchisement in any way whatever to the consideration or award of any nationality, race, sex, language, cultural or political opinion, nor to the status of a citizen of any country …'). It is worth noting that in the globalised capitalist society of the 21st century</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] See: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_species_in_the_world_filed_as_cases_in_court#sthash.Kp8sDsiU.dpuf.dpuf.2014.12.15.Pu8sE9wtM.dpuf.2014.12.15.K8sHr6sE9wtM; http://www.endangeredspecies.net/cases/list/species.html?list=SPQ1.1 	[4] The Convention on Biological Diversity, adopted in 1978, states that 'no person shall, in contravention of this Convention, … take part in the taking of any species for the purpose of … making that species … an endangered species …'). It is worth emphasising that ‘every person who utters the words ‘endangered’ has, in common with chimpanzees,</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970.  	[3] The Treaty on the Day of the Elephant, signed by John Paul Jones on 12 May 1946, stipulated that: ‘Any person who, knowing that the Elephant is Armed and Dangerous, transports, deals with, or causes to be dealt with in any way in the Elephant any Weapon or Arming of any Kind whatsoever, shall on conviction be liable to the Owner of the Elephant … for every such wrongful act or omission within twenty-four hours …  [emphasis added] (emphasis in original).[6] Cited in Warner J, Elephant, Part 2: The Dangerous Game, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1990, p.20.[7] The Treaty on the Day of the Elephant, Chapter 2, Article 2, requires that any such weapon or material not be brought into &quot;the Ecoregion&quot; or its vicinity, and Article 4 stipulates that &quot;[a]ny person desiring to possess such a Weapon … shall</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [4] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [5] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [6] The Convention against Corruption of Natural Resource (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [7] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [8] The Convention on Small Arms (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [9] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January 1973. [10] The Convention on Small Arms (1949) came into force on 1 January 1973. [11] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1951) came into force on 1 January</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, including using such imagery to monitor and assess the health of wildlife, particularly those species at risk of extinction. The use of closed-access satellite imagery may also be appropriate for tracking threatened or protected species, such as endangered or threatened geese, eagles, and bats. Such imagery can be collected and used to document incidents of conflict and violations of environmental and human rights, as well as incidents of eco-terrorism. Such imagery may be used to document acts of aggression against wildlife, in violation of international law and common sense. It can also be used to document acts of cooperation between government and non-governmental wildlife groups, in violation of the law.[20] 	[1] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. 	[2] The Convention on the Suppression of Traffic in Nuclear Materials (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [3] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [4] The Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1867–1917) came into force on 1 January 1919. [5] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1949) came into force on 1 January 1970. [6] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (1949), art. 4, sub-art. 1, art. 4. 1 July 1970, ch. IV, art. 6, art. 3, art. 4. [7] The Convention on Biological Diversity (1949), art. 4, sub-art. 1, art. 4. 1 July 1970, ch. IV, art. 6, art. 3, art. 4. [8] The Convention on Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-fig
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative intent on the part of the artist. She is projecting herself onto an already pre-existing public, but also of projecting herself somewhere else. If she doesn’t get the funding that she needs from the Biennial, or from the city, or both, then she is still projecting herself onto an already pre-existing public. I don’t think this is a good thing. When the Biennial first started, the city council was really against it. The impression I got from people in the art world was that the Biennial would destroy the city, like the Blitz did. It would be a tragedy, but also a great contribution to urban culture. The Biennial is a good thing, in the sense that it generates new revenue streams for the city, but it is also a gift, given to the city by the city, that has to be spent wisely, because the city cannot possibly replenish itself. The Biennial’s spending limits itself; it is</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative intent, but it also undermines the sterility of the specific, in that it exploits the festival as a site of pre-figuration. In its usual form, the Biennial presents itself as a complex series of relationships. The actuality of the relationships between artists, curators, art administrators, art’s real power brokers, artists, artists’ assistants, art-collectors, art writers, art promotion organisations, art sleuths, and on and on. A list could be made that goes back and forth, taking into consideration the people who direct, co-direct, assist, manage, direct exhibitions, commission works, maintain a database, write articles, code, research etc. Every day, different people engage with these relationships, often in totally opaque and unspoken ways. But every now and then a tweet is sent or a Facebook post is shared that announces the presence of a given artist, curatorial team, art institution or art project in the city.</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative potential for the curatorial role, but also pre-figurative potential for the curatorial conversation. Because, as Gabrielle Royce pointed out, there is no pre-figurative potential in the development of curating in the city of Montreal, for example. The curatorial conversation is one led by those who have already been there, and so one must either be present (of course, one must be present at the festival itself, which is being curated in a very formal and controlled way), or else be critically aware of who is actually in the room (and thus, who is actually in the city). Royce’s remark is that the most significant contribution to the festival’s cultural capitalization thus far has come from places where there is no cultural capitalization at all. This is problematic, for several reasons. The first is the way in which the curatorial conversation at Liverpool Biennial has been developing, and so one can imagine a situation in which</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figuration – the creation of a new art world out of thin air – which isn’t always what we mean when we do it. There is no inherent sense of wonder in the creation of a new art world; rather, it is a staged event that uses existing infrastructure and culture as a prop to tell a story. The new art world that emerges out of this pre-figuration doesn’t have a fixed shape to call its own, but rather a dynamic, variable shape. I see this in the creation of new cities: New York’s development of its financial district, its streetscape, its architecture – the introduction of MUNI subway trains and the integration of the clothing department at department stores – are all products of this pre-figuration. These actions are taken as signs of economic and urban progress, but they are also actions that are also tacked onto the deep ends of the social web, taking the form of education, healthcare, housing, parks and so</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative intent, but also, I believe, a certain amount of actualization of that intent. We don’t live in a world that easily creates quantifiable effects; the promise of art as performance, of course, is seductive, but it’s also possible that the very act of art making can actually help to enliven our lives in interesting ways. Indeed, a couple of years ago, I led a project that involved the Liverpool Biennial in my hometown of Liverpool, and in the Welsh Streets in New York. The project, entitled Something Blue, billed itself as ‘a collaboration between artist and museum’, and sought to reconcile the apparent irreconcilability of widely different disciplines by bringing together art and biennials in a way that would permit a co-existing set of artistic practices to exist alongside a museum. The idea was to create a space in which artists could operate in a perfunctory, un-prioritized way, as a</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figuration. It doesn’t take into account the fact that the festival itself was always going to be a site of pre-figuration, a pre-figure of what would become the urban landscape we know and love. It doesn’t take into account the fact that the festival itself is only ever going to be a pre-figure of what is going to happen next, and so the space it occupies, and the way in which it is going to be used. It doesn’t take into account the fact that the festival itself is going to be something completely different, and that it is going to be something very exciting and different, and that is always going to be a possibility. But it is now more of a time when we are struggling to find a way to live and work in the city, and so these possibilities are pushing us into disorientation. In the case of Liverpool, the possibility of a truly artist-led, artist-curated Liverpool Biennial –</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figuration – the presence of such a thing in advance of events that already have, or are about to have) an impact. But it is also true that the festival as an event could not have been invented, nor would it have the same impact today, given the pressures generated by the city. The pressure generated by the biennial is immense, and it is constantly (hopefully soon) changing. The biennial itself undergoes the same pressures today as it did in 1963, when the Biennial was initially conceived, and the subsequent pressure during its first two years of operation, and in the last few years, as its capacity to sustainably host exhibitions has been questioned. But the fact that the biennial has become what it is today (a venue for a pre-existing art market, where previous anxieties about the impact of an art market were apparently ignored) is a testament to the fact that art’s earliest promoters understood its essential relationship to the city: once the biennial was</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figuration – the kind of pre-figuration that can be found in many art world biennials, but is especially marked in the case of the Liverpool Biennial. In modern curatorial work, this pre-figuration – the kind of pre-figuration that characterises contemporary art-making – is typically associated with the rise and spread of biennials in other cities, and the proliferation of museum-going habits. But in the case of the Liverpool Biennial, the emergence of biennials in a city as diverse as Liverpool, and as the site of its production, seems to me a situation in which the public space is increasingly marked by the discorporation of artists and the commercial exchange of art. A place where the very precursors of the biennial form were born and raised, and in which the biennial as a cultural form is being rendered increasingly obsolete.  The idea of the artist as a social democrat is being rendered increasingly precarious in the age of the bi</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative intent. It’s not that we don’t want to think about, imagine or dream about what the future might hold, because that’s precisely what we do in preparation for big moments. We take stock, analyse and prepare ourselves for what we hope is a future that is uncertain and unpredictable. Ultimately, though, the uncertainty and unpredictability we aim for is what makes the present really interesting, and what keeps us alive: vivid and gripping imagery that evokes memory and evokes place. If the uncertainty and unpredictability of the future is what Preston James called ‘the present’, then we’ll probably all become museum curators someday, and that's pretty neat. But we need to learn how to talk about the uncertain future that could be, and how to imagine it.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of Art, Art History and Exhibition Studies at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in Contemporary</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that was collected, analysed and presented in the run-up to the Liverpool Biennial. This affected the way in which the public, and the curators in particular, perceived the festival, and the relationship between the artist and the biennial. The biennial itself was taken more for granted, and the public more drawn into the story of the city, and the city in general. The public didn’t see themselves as artists, or even as true curators, and so the biennial became something between a performance and a workshop, or what Walter Benjamin would have called the dual character of silence and life (silence without poetry, or at least without life without ideas). In other words, the biennial in its contracted form became what it always was: a staging ground for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well. I find this conception of the festival problematic, in that it implies a certain amount of pre-figurative intent, but it also entails a certain amount of actualization of art's potentialities. When the biennial is a platform for the most preoccupied, embodied public in the city, but also a space of preoccupation as well, it becomes something like a city festival, in that one can layer in other in the city, but also in that other’s city, and imaginatively supplement that other’s publics. This is the second leg of the pre-figurative cycle: the biennial in its various guises becomes something like a pre-figurative sculpture park, where other art forms and their artists can lay claim to a piece of the pie. This is the pre-figurative self-regeneration. The other leg is the pre-figurative city, in which the citizens of the city actively participate in regaining the pre-figurative character of the city. Not all the citizens of the city are urban</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us figure things out. This is the second biennial I’ve been a part of, and the first as an individual. The fact that it’s happening in my neighbourhood means a lot to me, and it’s happening across the world. It’s happening in New York and London and Paris. It’s happening in the US but it’s happening in China and India and everywhere in between. It’s happening in Venice and it’s happening in Santa Fe. It’s happening in a very particular way in Santa Fe: the art world is coming to terms with the fact that this is a very real place, with people and culture and a sense of its own identity. This is a very different kind of experience from the one I had growing up. The kind of existential sense of loss and loss of meaning that comes with coming to terms with something you don’t understand. That’s another thing</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us figure it all out. Of course, this means making new art spaces, and offering new art experiences, and inviting a community of artists to step into those spaces. And of course, there’s the work itself: creating what can ‘easily’ be labelled a ‘curatorial hunt’, or an ‘exhibitionary event’. But even if all that work was curatorial, what does that make us? What does it make us when we do things differently, when we do things in secret, when we don’t share? I guess, I guess, a little bit of everything. But I don’t know what all those things are. I don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ is. I don’t know what an ‘exhibitionary event’ is. I don’t know what a ‘workshop’ is. I don’t</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us figure things out, because we don’t always get what we want. And sometimes, as in the case of the Liverpool Biennial, we don’t get what we want. This is why biennials are here to stay. Because once you have them, you never want to give them up, and you never want to take them away from anyone, and you never want to give them away for free either. Biennials are institutions in their own right, and thus able to exist in perpetuity because of this in-built institutional memory. As biennials multiply in number, size and range, their functions expand, and this is a good thing. A biennial is a recurring cultural event, and thus a cultural medium is a critical place. It captures the essence of what is being experienced, celebrated and imagined by an audience, and thus gives meaning to what is imagined and imagined. It enables us to empathise, to know what we mean when we</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us make things up as we go along, and in order to do that, we need some kind of grounding principle. Otherwise, things can get messy and unstable and unpredictable and we don’t want that. And yet we have to give it up in order to access the things that make us happy.  In order to access the things that make us happy, we need an ethos that says, as Simone Weil says, ‘Yes, I’m capable of doing it this way.’ We need that now more than ever, because the more superficial the forms of our society become, the more insidious and pervasive this kind of self-criticism becomes. It’s a kind of spiritual-political-ideological resistance. But it’s also a political resistance. And if it becomes a spiritual-political-ideological resistance, there’s a chance that it will become a very specific kind of institutionalised form of political organization: a kind</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us make sense of the confusing things we discover along the way. This is the experience of a city, or at least part of it. It’s why New York is so powerful, why San Francisco is so fascinating, why Paris is so interesting, why Melbourne is so fascinating, why Seoul is so fascinating. It’s why Ljubljana in the 1990 Venice Biennale was so exciting. It’s why São Paulo in 1994 was so exciting. It’s why now, more than ever, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us make sense of the confusing things we discover along the way. This is the experience of a city. It’s why New York is so powerful, why San Francisco is so fascinating, why Paris is so fascinating, why Berlin is so fascinating. It’s why now, more than ever, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us make sense of the confusing</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and say, ‘This is how it all starts’. We need that deep philosophical understanding of what a biennial is – and how that starts – because otherwise we’ll just be like the rest of the world and follow the money. And we’ll always be customers, and we’ll always be second-class citizens, like everyone else. So we need artists to step back and say, ‘This is what a biennial is’, and then create conditions in which we can develop and propagate that through the art world, in a way that way. And that starts with understanding the concept. Understanding biennials isn’t easy, and it’s not going to be easy for everyone, but it’s necessary for the survival of the human species.Mark Miodownik and Fiona Lee both teach at the Bournemouth School of Art and have been collaborating as a Curatorial Fellow and as an Adjunct faculty member</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us figure things out, which is exactly what the Biennale has been doing. It’s an exchange of ideas, not a collection of collections. The collection of collections it is now attached to, the collection of the museum, is a collection of objects. It’s like a house, or a collection of objects, with certain categories of objects holding particular histories and certain places in particular contexts, and these categories and places are like neighbourhoods. And so each of the biennials had a specific relationship to the neighbourhood it was housed in. The Spanish artist Fernando Alfonso López de la Torre established a biennale in 1914, and the American artist Gabrielle Roy held the inaugural L.A. biennale that same year. L.A. was the first of many biennials to open in the city, and in 1917, the International Biennale Commission established a branch in London. In 1939, the United States established the Commission on International</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us sort it all out, in order to make sure we get things done: to set up a biennial, for example. But all these things are still nebulous, and we don’t have clear definitions of what a biennial is, or how to define a biennial. And so we’re stuck in this loop of confusion and lack of definition. And we don’t have clear definitions of what a biennial is, either.  The other thing that occurs to me, which is kind of ironic, but is also really fascinating, is that the biennial as an art form, as an aesthetic, as an artistic form, has actually become increasingly difficult to define. It’s no longer possible to say with any precision what a ‘biennial’ is, or to say with any degree of certainty what an ‘artistic institute’ is. The problem with the biennial as an art form is that it tends to adopt</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us figure it all out. So I ask you: in Twenty Four Hours, do you have an idea of what a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is?  What do you think a biennial is? </text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is scheduled to open in 2017. Where does this leave us? We’ve certainly got some terminological confusion to sort ourselves out. Some of the biennials we know and love, like Venice, have been around for a very long time, and we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial’ means, or what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial union’ means, or what a ‘curatorial exchange’ means. And we don’t necessarily know what a ‘curatorial institute’ is. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial hunt’ means. We don’t know what a ‘curatorial institute’ means, or what a ‘curatorial unit’ means, or what a ‘workshop or exhibition’ means. In order to make sense of this stuff, we need artists and organisers to step back and let us sort ourselves. That sounds abstract, but it’s really quite easy. There are a few examples of exactly that in the biennial format – the Venice Biennale, the Andrew W. Mellon Centenary Art Biennale, the John Lennon Biennale, to name only a few. And there are a few biennials that do things differently, like the SITE Santa Fe Biennale, which is an exchange between art institution and citizen. It’s not a biennale, it’s an exchange of ideas, and it’s a gathering of people coming together to make art. That sounds simple, but it’s not always easy to understand what that exchange entails. And it’s not always easy to understand what happens next. In the example I gave, the artist was in a cooperative – ART=Co-operative Arts Education Trust, or ACET, which is a hybrid public and private cooperative arts education trust</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to let the systems stew in their own filth, to let the media do their thing, to give the appearance of anarchy, to turn into suburbia big enough to house that media empire but small enough to house its inhabitants (and a scattering of lobbyists and data brokers). But such drastic measures would render the systems more like statues, and reduce the people who inhabit them to rubble. Instead, the more likely action is for the people with access to the black boxes to pursue a variety of other, more amenable actions – enacting legislation to regulate the systems that generate the news, monitoring them for malignancy (making them self-destructing, in the immortal words of Alan Turing), and so forth.Such action-reaction frameworks exist in various forms in science-fiction and non-fiction, but few writers or readers of mainstream fiction do justice to the complexity of the situation in which they are confronted. In  	S.M. Gray Lady, for example,  </text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to prevent them from ever being interrogated (a decision, given the nature of the technology underlying them, that many other developments in artificial intelligence have contributed to making possible). But that would rob us of the knowledge that is integral to understanding systems-as-systems, part of what is referred to as ‘the singularity’. More fundamentally, the decision to abandon the human element of the equation completely renders the system as inhuman, to the point where its very essence is threatened. That is, the black-box analysis that characterises the systems-as-systems paradigm is itself at odds with the kind of analysis that should be carried out with respect to human beings.Human factors that shape technological evolution are complex and nuanced and cannot be understood in isolation. The singularity is not the answer, but technological innovation depends on many other things (including our actions) that are interrelated and interdependent. And while the first electronic computer appeared in 1971, it is worth emphasising that the computer</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to leave them to deteriorate in space, and to mismanage them as you please. But that is inherently ambiguous and politically unstable. So what is being suggested here is a radical departure from established human behaviour: something that seems to be at odds with the established order. Something akin to chaos.And this is the context in which we are moving: the social media revolutions of the past few years have ushered in a new epoch in which there is a palpable desire to obliterate distinction between public and private platforms. That is, to render the public sphere as neutral and void of politics as possible. To render the private as politically neutral and devoid of emotions.To render the public domain as politically inert.To render the private domain as politically uninteresting.That is, to render the public sphere as empty of politics as possible.That is, to render the public as emotionally inert as possible.That is, to render the public as emotionally uninteresting as possible.That is, to render the public as</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to prevent them from ever being seen again by anyone but the people who are connected to the computer at the time. But that would render the systems unintelligible – render them as black boxes, which is what cyberterrorism does. So the question becomes: what are the implications of this growing tendency toward black-box thinking? What is being declared as ‘the future of the individual’? What if, say, Facebook decides to show its users a retraining ad that is much more human-like than the one that you and I produce? What happens then is that the algorithms we produce become corrupted; they become susceptible to the influence of misinformation and malicious actors, and their malicious intentions are exposed; they begin to generate perverse incentives; and then, one might add, some nefarious forces step in and attempt to stop that process from happening.In fact, I might add that the stakes are even higher here. The decision to engineer an ad that is more human-like than the one that you</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to prevent them from falling into the wrong hands (a la Moore’s Alien). But that is neither here nor there. The black boxes are not only programmed with the world, but also with calculations that help ensure that those calculations are carried out (reluctant co-citizens). The question becomes where to draw the line between the autonomous systems that are autonomous and the rest of us? In the event of a major disaster, the autonomous systems would revert to the condition of natural human agency – acting according to established procedures and drawing upon knowledge gleaned from the scene. But that would mean abandoning the quest for intelligibility and drawing on a universal model of humanity that is both resourceful and powerful. We would return to our biological organisms and seek to understand the mechanisms by which our world operates.That is not what science leads one to do. Rather, the imperative question is this: what kind of understanding can we create when the task is no longer to understand the world but to deliver value –</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to deny the underlying architecture of the system's possible collapse. That seems to be the approach taken by many computer systems, but as we saw, that is inherently ambiguous and subject to interpretation. Another option is to embed critical subsystems (software, data) within a physical casing – to create what is sometimes called ‘critical infrastructures’. These structures are often referred to as ‘disks’ and are thought to hold the answer to the ‘how to decipher data’ quandary. But although such structures may help to provide the infrastructures with critical infrastructures, their real value lies in their capacity to map the world, to enable infrastructures to understand and access the world, to allow infrastructures to plan and prepare for the unforeseen and the unpredictable.  In fact, as we saw, infrastructures are often drawn to perform critical infrastructures, but that is only natural in a system as flexible</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to let the systems stew in their own filth, to let the fiction reign in the reality. But this is not a dream scenario. That would be apocalyptic. Rather, what we would want is a return to the simpler, more humanistic ways of life that existed before the advent of computation. That would mean recognising not just the patterns of humanity’s increasingly inhumanity, but also the patterns of fiction itself. What might be recognisable as ‘fiction’ is actually just algorithmic noise; patterns that grow in lockstep with the machine’s momentum but are ultimately unintelligible. What we mean by this is that the machines that constitute the internet today are far more adept than humans at recognising patterns, far more adept at constructing stories around certain patterns. And this is to consider the broader implications of what might be called ‘deep learning’ – the science of artificial intelligence.Machine learning is the science of artificial intelligence. It takes the form of neural networks</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to prevent them from ever fully understanding the world. But that is neither here nor there. Rather, the question is what to do with the information that is sent and received within the system. That is, what to do with the black boxes that record the world according to predetermined predetermined categories?This is the broader context in which the present work arises. The film theorist Peter Norvig develops his ideas about artificial intelligence and cognitive science via the film 2001: a Space Odyssey. Here, the AI discovers a planet and begins to explore. The question is what to do with the artefacts of human cognition – the objects and processes through which human cognition emerges – which find expression in the form of objects and processes that are designed to excel in a prescribed domain? For the AI, cognition emerges through the mediation of data – representations and narratives of meaning – which are gathered and interpreted via the data. The question becomes, then, what kind of data is this? What constitutes the definition of knowledge? What is its</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to deny the notion of unpredictable and black-hole-like failure completely and instead strive to understand the underlying architecture of the global machine in greater detail. That is, the underlying causes and mechanisms underpinning the global economic system.That is, the dark sides of the economic machine are apparent in the bright terms of globalization, but since the systems that enable such seeming transfigurations are themselves subject to unpredictable and black-hole-like failures, the bright edges of such systems actually signal the world to potential destruction. That is, the bright ends of such systems actually signal the possibility of eventuality in the face of seemingly certain failure. That is, the notion that the economic machine is inherently flexible and that its contradictions are epiphenomenal is at odds with the deeper structures of the social and natural-resource systems that enable such seemingly inevitable ends. That is, the notion that capitalism is inherently pro forma also signals the possibility of eventuality in the face of seemingly certain failure. That is, capitalism</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to describe the world as a system that is increasingly like a human being (reluctant co-citizens). In other words, it seeks to render the world intelligible in some way. The first electronic computer appeared in 1971 and has remained in active service ever since. But while the computer theoretically provides the means with which to understand the world, the realisation of that understanding is a process of elaboration and refinement that is inherently unpredictable. That is, the extent to which the underlying mathematical and computational mechanisms underpinning the system are programmable is uncertain. That uncertainty is part of the reason why computer systems are prone to catastrophic failures – irreparable ambiguity about the underlying architecture rendering them virtually unknowable – and also why such failures are commonplace.In the event of a catastrophic breakdown of the system, the question is what to do with the shards – what to do with the black boxes recording the world? One obvious choice is to scatter the black boxes across the globe, to leave them to destructiveness and anarchy, to where they fall to devastating effect is anyone's guess. But that would render the systems intelligible again, and make them real again. That is, if they could be reconfigured. Another option is to embed smart materials or devices inside the systems to monitor and control them, to create self-repairing units that deployively recycle silicon and other components after a catastrophic failure occurs.That sounds like a recipe for dystopian futures, but the emergence of new technologies coupled with an abundance of data has brought us to a situation where even the most dystopian future may actually be preferable to the present. And while there are undoubtedly going to be those who seek to negate this new humanity from reality, there is reason to celebrate – at least now we know there are other possibilities. That is, there are other futures. That is, there are other ways of interacting with the world. There is reason to be hopeful.That is, there are other solutions. There are alternative</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In this new work, developed in collaboration with a team of philosophers including Professors Max Tegmark, Michio Kaku, Professors Ashutosh and Steven Weinberg, and others, AI is conceptualised not as a set of tools for the employment of human intelligence but rather as a politics of the virtual. This is done through a discourse of consciousness (called ‘brain’), which seeks to reconcile the apparent contradiction between a multi-system AI and its creators, its users and the real-world––in other words, the built environment. AI is not just a set of tools for the employment of human intelligence, but also a system that is deeply political, political even, and that is capable of creating new forms of governance. In this new work, the philosophers involved in the trilogy develop a set of questions that go beyond the boundaries of human reason and suggest deeper philosophical and epistolic boundaries. These questions are: (1) What</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In  	Stages, Bernard Stiegler offers a nuanced and nuanced set of arguments in favour of what he describes as ‘technological determinism’. In the context of AI, these terms refer to the assumption by humans that technology will advance in line with inexorable algorithms, mechanisation and the ever-expanding web of data that it creates. By relying on increasingly sophisticated data capture and processing methods, AI threatens the very notion of individual freedom and self-organisation. In recent years, concerns regarding AI have shifted towards its more obvious negative effects, such as the danger of creating super-intelligent beings capable of ruling humanity, over-saturation of the market with AI-enabled self-repairing robots, and in the words of Alan Turing, the threat to 'think independently’. But while these threats have shifted the philosophical centre of attention away from AI, they have not, and cannot, hide or disguise</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In the wake of Moore’s Law and the exponential increase in processing power that is capable of handling it, a political question arises as to what counts as work and what counts as play. In AI, progress depends on whether there are enough cognitive resources to support the expansion of AI, or whether the AI becomes too complex and subject to human error, and whether the human race is sufficiently aware of this. If the human race is too conscious of the existential risks involved in the direction of AI, then the possibilities for disaster are multiplied. On the other hand, if the human race is able to reason rationally about the existential risks, then the possibilities for creativity and new possibilities for interaction are reduced. AI raises the possibilities of a reduced state of consciousness in a range of new situations. Whether the design of AI is to be understood as a political question or a philosophical one is unclear. But the prevalent philosophical perspective suggests that we should aim to understand AI</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In  	Stages 2 &amp; 3, philosophers, political scientists, and others from a range of disciplines converge on a single location in order to explore a single issue or proposition. This issue of  	New Delhi-based philosophical journal Philosophical Culture examines the philosophical underpinnings of AI, examining the ways in which AI threatens the very notion of human agency and, by implication, the very notion of culture. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre, ‘On Artificial Intelligence and Cultural Crises: From Mathematica to Facebook’, in Philosophical Culture, Vol. 21, Issue 2 &amp; 3 (June–August, 2015), p.29–47.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the 2nd book in the New Intellect series, and the first</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical and political underpinnings of AI. In this book, Lefebvre uses the term  	AI to describe new types of intelligences capable of performing complex tasks. He develops these to different degrees of autonomy, and offers various ethical and legal evaluations of their ethical responsibilities.He also introduces several new philosophical frameworks that reconcile different spheres of power and responsibility. These include new ontological categories for thinking about AI and humanity's place in it, concepts that can be used to redefine the boundaries of what counts as AI and what is not, and the nature of moral responsibility. He shows how AI can augment or replace traditional forms of legal and political adjudication, providing new modes of understanding and action. These are part of a broader theme that he develops regarding the nature of human agency, political agency, cultural agency and technological agency. The ideas and frameworks he develops regarding AI and human agency are drawn from a range of disciplines, including: philosophy, art, architecture, urban studies</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In these two books, I come to understand political philosophy as a social science that studies the mechanisms of computation, and the ways in which social phenomena, including political processes, emerge from the entanglement of interacting components. I come to understand the social significance of the rise of AI, and the ways in which political processes that use AI are entwined with broader trends of AI and robotics. I come to understand political philosophy as part of a broader interdisciplinary field of philosophy, sociology, and political science. These two books also provide the framework for a possible third, though currently undeveloped, book in the series, due out around 2019. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.  [1] Here, we survey recent developments in AI and robotics, and speculate on what might become possible through the social contract theoretical framework of AI and how political philosophers might</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In  	Stages, Lefebvre uncovers a 1980s US government policy memo that creates 'singularity’-like conditions where intelligence becomes a platform for all manner of speculative and ephemeral behaviour. AI, or Artificial Intelligence, is defined by Lefebvre as a form of intelligent ‘thought’ that transcends both biological and technological limits. AI leads to a new kind of social complexity, greater exchanges and mobility, and new modes of interaction between people and things. The possibilities are endless. But the search for AI does have a logic, and that is why Lefebvre engages with it in such pains and in such detail. If the search for AI is to have any meaning at all, it has to be accompanied by an understanding of what that meaning is. 	[i] The second book in the New Intellect series,  	The End of Work, 2012.</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical, political and economic underpinnings of AI. In  	Intelligent Agency, Walter Block and Irit and Naoki Kitano attempt to reconcile the philosophical and political differences between our worlds, in the wake of AI, which they argue is now manifest in ever greater and more pervasive ways. In this ‘post-AI’ world, individuals with super-intelligent AI (Artificial Intelligence 2.0) are capable of understanding and interacting with their surroundings in ways that are indistinguishable from human language, but with the capacity to foresee and alter the course of history, the future, and even the composition of the planet in ways that are impossible to predict or control. What is certain is that AI will continue to be a source of immense social and political change, and a cause of much more. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre, ‘On Intelligence and Cognition: A Secular Humanist's Framework for AI’, </text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI and the socio-political implications of its developments. In  	Stages, Lefebvre frames the social ramifications of AI developments through the narrow confines of his own species, but offers a dialectical distance between human and machine, between architecturally designed virtual worlds and the real world. Drawing on his own evolutionary biology and philosophy courses, and his work as an architect, Lefebvre builds a case for a species to its logical conclusion: that is, progress for humans only.Lefebvre begins by contemplating the philosophical underpinnings of AI and the socio-political implications of its development. He develops these under the heading of ‘the coming catastrophe’, and projects these developments into the form of a planetary emergency. He concludes by envisioning a ‘world government’ that would reconcile competing visions of AI, but which would also preserve not only the design, but also the humanity of the design. This new government</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also seeks to understand the deeper socio-technical underpinnings of our current and future urban environments through the processes of capital accumulation and circulation. Stages 1 and 2 describe the emergence of AI as a political-technological concept in the wake of Moore’s Law, the exponential increase in computer processing power that is able to handle exponentially more data than any human processor. The technological underpinning of AI is now part of the commercial sector, and political concepts like AI and the political implications of AI are coming to be understood as part of the larger social context of AI. 	[i] Roland Lefebvre,  	The End of Work 	, 2012.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AI (2011) is the sequel to  	Stages (2011), the first book in the New Intellect series, which addressed the philosophical underpinnings of AI. In the wake of AI, we return to the roots of the subject and to the role of philosophy in the contemporary world. This time, we look to the origins of AI, and perhaps, future directions for human AI. 	[i] Max Horkheimer,  	The Fall of Communism, 1941, in  	Neoclassical Economics and Historical Materialisms, ed. Michael Ames and others, Blackwell, Oxford, p.xii.Download this article as PDFStages 1 &amp; 2: Towards a Political Philosophy of AIStages 3 &amp; 4: Towards a Social Life of AI Stages 5 &amp; 6: Towards a Social Life of AI (2015) is the thirteenth book in the New Intellect series, and the final book in the trilogy On Intelligence and Social Life. It includes a discussion of the origins of AI, the future of work, and a description of the current tensions between philosophy</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding the funerals herself, as well as any further information that may emerge from these. These works, which she describes as a ‘rejection of formal conventions and the monstrosity of formal systems’, attempt to present a ‘point of departure’ from formalisms that seek to define or constrain artistic expression.[47]In attempting to draw a blank space between the formal and the natural, or between art and state, she constructs a new kind of ‘space of no return’ in which to work, while also asking artists to embark on a ‘contravision’ between artist and community, exploring the idea of community as a multiplicity of voices and bodies, speaking from experience and objectivity into the new ‘space of art’. She ends her book with an extended exploration of the role that artists can play in creating this new ‘art’ space, something that she calls the ‘Art of Making Things New�</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously challenging others to follow suit.  Her first public act as Curator at the New Museum in New York was the launching of a Kickstarter campaign to fund the production of a new series of works, which were published in June 2015.  Her second public act was at the Granby Four Freedoms Park in New York, where the Venice Biennale was also published, in June 2015.  Her most recent piece, published in June 2017 in  	Architecture of the Intimate was the installation for the Venice Biennale, Future City, which is a return to the city environment that she had originally proposed for the park, this time in the form of small scale multi-use art spaces. She also curated the Sixth Biennale of Sydney, which took place six months later. Ameena Atiq,  	Dead Artists, New Museum, 2016. Installation view at Granby Four Freedoms Park, New York</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously standing apart from the cultural norms of the city in which they are embedded. These norms may not be what she wants, but at least these works exist outside the bubble of the Museum of Modern Art, whose mission statement currently includes the words ‘museum’ again, and seems to imply that these norms must be obeyed. There is a clear attempt to bring a more activist and activist agenda to the proceedings, with statements such as those by Living Art Collective members Stanley Core and Amina El Samahyari explicitly rejecting the idea of living as a ‘given’ and instead acting out the duties of the ‘living’ through acts of language and organisation.[47]  Her work finds its roots in the late 1990s when, as part of the Biennale Circle, she co-chaired the commissioning committee and managed the public programmes, with other artists, for the first time ever, of the Al Mezan Center’s academic programme. With</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding certain facts from view. She has also decided to withhold certain information from the public, including the identity of the artists who created the series, in an attempt to protect their identities. 	[1] See, for example,:   http://deadartists.org/. Accessed: 2 August 2016. 	[2] See, for example, http://deadartists.org/. Accessed: 2 August 2016. 	[3] See, for example, http://deadartists.org/works/archive/. Accessed: 2 August 2016. 	[4] See, for example, http://deadartists.org/works/archive/. Accessed: 2 August 2016. 	[5] See, for example, http://deadartists.org/works/archive/. Accessed: 2 August 2016. 	[6] See, for example, http://deadartists.org/works/archive/.</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding certain artists from public view. These works are deliberately provocative and deeply personal in order to allow the artists and audiences to experience the work in a different way, using their own unique voice and visual language. Most of the works are commissioned by artist organisations, but a number of them are written by individuals. Some of the artists have their own works that address the subject matter in different ways. One of the artists, Reem Making a Living in 2009, whose work is the subject of this volume, used the occasion to reflect on the impossibility of understanding death and the profound impact it has had on her work. She reflected on her past work in a series of paintings, each depicting a different aspect of the illness. The images are a snapshot of the condition in which she finds herself today, but they also act as a form of protest and vulnerability. Her concept, entitled Reem Making a Living, is a living organism that draws its inspiration from the art and the legacy of the</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously challenging others to follow suit. These works were developed in response to the art of the living being erased, while the art of the dead is being continually renewed. The works combine contemporary art with traditional arts practices that are state of the art, yet are still subject to the vagaries of economic and social development, creating an inclusive work that addresses the complex interaction of a large number of disparate stakeholders. I was privileged to collaborate with Ameena at her home in the East Village, and she and her team invited me into their creative process. While the process itself was iterative, the actual work  was never intended to be completed; rather it was an ongoing, (potential) point of departure from which further work could be done. So the notion of completion came much later in the process, and in an increasingly mythical or mythical-sounding kind of way. The art was always meant to live on, and so the notion of ‘perfection’ came much later, and</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding certain facts from the public. These works are intended to be seen as works in progress, so that they can be continually (re)negotiated and revised in order to be more current and relevant, while simultaneously remaining fundamentally unpublished, untitled and very much a work of art itself. While the  	Dead Artists project does not yet have a formal curatorial position, Atiq’s own 2014 solo show at Tate Britain, which was primarily curated by Dave Binnington,  	Dead Artists, followed an almost identical structure to that of the first project, albeit with artists from the first event taking over the projects. Both were centred around a biennial, with artworks and textiles from the convention becoming objects of exchange and act as botha currency and a regulatory medium for the institution and the artist. Atiq’s 2014 show was even presented in a video format, though this was restricted to the institution’s website.  </text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding certain works from view. These works are works that deliberately go against the grain of the visual art canon, and attempt to expose socially engaged, politically aware or critically engaged artists to a wider audience, while simultaneously withholding certain aspects of their work from view. She has described these as ‘dead art’, and has called them ‘re-constituting the space that’s being destroyed around them’.[47] These words were chosen for their echo of a sentiment that is widespread in a region: the feeling that the art world is collapsing around them; that the arts are but an afterthought, not among the most significant elements in a city’s development; that the Art of Living is more important than ever; that the Art of Death is imminent and unavoidable. How we respond to this is a question that, as the Art of Living demonstrates, can have very real – even devastating – consequences. What is crucial though, is that we collectively decide</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously challenging the authorities to intervene again in order to change the dynamic. She has received support from the Arts Council, Arts Council Ireland, Arts Council of Ireland, Arts Council of Scotland and the Doha Foundation. More and more artists and arts organisations are coming forward with stories of trauma and despair related to the danger posed by the explosion of modern art, which they claim is destroying ‘our city’[47] and ‘our culture’[48]. A number of these artists have been directly involved in creating Dead Artists, which are now part of the Institute of Contemporary Art. Yet others have direct or indirect involvement in Institute of Contemporary Art products or exhibitions, yet are less open to questioning cultural practices or artists’ practices. 	Ameena Atiq believes that artists should be able to develop and grow creatively independent of the prevailing systems of power and money in society. She has long been an opponent of the commercial artist, and has emphasised</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local artists, in keeping with the city’s long-standing policy of collaboration between the arts and the city’s infrastructure.[46] What is at Stake in the Art World? Even as curators and artists themselves, many are uncomfortable when asked what they think the Art of Living is, or what it means to be ‘in the flesh’. A common response is one of shame or embarrassment: talking about the Art of Living openly is taboo, rarely discussed in the same breath as the Art of Death, and indeed actively discouraged from doing so by curators and arts administrators. But the link between the Art of Living and the Art of Death is becoming increasingly clear, and this taboo finally having shifted, is what  	Ameena Atiq hopes to prevent from happening again. She has set out a series of works to be entitled  	Dead Artists, in an attempt to bring some light to the situation, whilst simultaneously withholding the funerals for as many artists as possible. She has also started a crowdfunding campaign to fund the construction of a series of monuments and halls to remember the dead, which will in turn house the offices and mausoleums of the dead, in what is being described as  	The Pharaoh’s Baths. [1] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, Penguin, 1973, p.3.Download this article as PDFAmeena AtiqAmeena Atiq is an artist and writer. Her artistic work, which addresses themes of identity, regaining one's place in the world, and the role of resistance in contemporary society, was exhibited at the Venice Biennale, Venice, Italy; the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York; the Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.; and the ASPCA, Los Angeles. She is the recipient of two 2016 Arts Hero Awards and was a finalist for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, having to pay for a weekend when these migrants, because of a quirk of market-based market economics, rarely visit.When the city is muggled, it’s time to stock up on food and essentials like a city: but because the market is awash in cheap housing, most of us only have to carry around in our pockets a wallet-sized amount of cash. So how do we create a supportive and affordable city? I propose we follow the logic of the crowds: when the market is open, why not the crowds? When the price of a ticket is low, why not the desperate houselesss? When the market is full, why not the homeless or the drug addicts?When the market is flooded with innovation and utopias are realized, why not the mundane still-living-blocks that feed into it?When the market is corrupt and pushing us towards feudalism, why not the (now) mostly undead but mobile labourers who populate the</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up like the residents of Ho Chi Minh City, living in conditions of overcrowding and poverty.When is the last time you visited a museum? When is the last time you visited a gallery? When is the last time you toured a primary school? When is the last time you visited a kindergarten? When is the last time you visited an art gallery?When is the last time you toured a mosque?When is the last time you visited a heritage market?When is the last time you visited a zoo?When is the last time you visited a field hospital?When is the last time you visited a pharmacy?When is the last time you visited a kindergarten?When is the last time you visited a kindergarten run by volunteers?When is the last time you visited a primary school?When is the last time you visited a kindergarten or preschool?When is the last time you visited a nursery?When is the last time you visited a parochial school?When</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, if the infrastructures that support them collapse, we’ll all be hit with destitution. When do we start thinking about the fact that the city is a far more important node in the social ecology of the city than that it supports all those houses? When do we start imagining the ecological and social ibalousies that result from the city’s constant shifting of funds and the constant need for the city to be more like a plantation? ibalousy: When do we start thinking about the fact that the city is a far more important node in the social ecology of the city than that it supports all those houses? When, that is, the monoculture standard has started to sap the city’s primacy, and when do we start to contemplate the fact that the city may not be able to sustain itself – and, indeed, may be in dire need of rebuilding – when the financial system is allowed to fail?  The answer to both questions</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up homeless. Fortunately, the City Council recently repealed part of its by-laws that restricted new developments to areas with a 'substantial minority' of citizens, a provision that was seen by some developers as a loosening of restrictions. That is, developers were able to embark on ambitious projects with a low density requirement but a high height limit – in most of which the building was retrofitted for office use – or made completely new projects with a much lower density requirement but a high height limit. The loosening of building and building-retrofitting restrictions has undoubtedly hastened the pace of change, but as Gregor Mendelsohn has pointed out, it has also hastened the decline of the city. When the first houses were built in the 1920s, there was a strict hierarchy of needs – you’d want a place to live in a good quality of life, a place to play in, a place to visit? – but now we�</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up like so many others in overcrowded conditions: living in dilapidated conditions, with no facilities, no toilets, no heating, no running water, no running water – a situation that is almost as bad as having no houses in the first place.When public spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could ‘hop on board’ and wish it ‘the best’ – is undermined, opens the door to new forms of oppression. When the city is muggled, over-crowded, over-run, and run amok, and the poorest inhabitants are displaced in a process of displacement that can't be measured in dollars, the city is a place where injustice meets opportunity. The city is a site of conflict, where opportunity meets displacement. And that’s where cities make themselves visible. They’re places where contradictions can exist, where opportunities</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up renting to the gangs that torture and maim the poor. When the city is over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins it – the notion that you could ‘rebuild’ the house in any way you pleased – is undermined, leads to social ills. When, that is, urban centres are no longer viewed as ‘supply' but as ‘demand’, then things start to change. And cities that are no longer able to manage their housing crisis, or to notice when they’re being used as––well, that’s when things start to change. When things no longer add up into ‘supply’ but into ‘demand’, then things start to fall into place. And that’s when things that should be counted on start to happen.When things that should be invisible start to happen. And that’s when we start to</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up like millions of other citizens, stuck in debt and living in overcrowded conditions. And that’s just to get us to the point. In a city as big as Milan, with a quarter of a million inhabitants, that’s just the kind of urban sprawl we want to be doing. It’s sprawl that’s good for us, creates jobs for us and brings us a step closer to the metropolis, but it’s also sprawl that’s bad for us. We need to be creating ways to intervene in that process of urban growth. And there are a few ways to do that.One is to try to abolish sprawl completely. That would mean letting go of all the houses in the city, and letting go of all the buildings in the process. That would mean letting go of the entire built environment, which is increasingly important for our well-being, and creating new environments that are</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up homeless. So perhaps the answer is to be found in the second part of the statement: when the city maximises the positive by ensuring that people come to places where they can find entertainment, places to meet new people, a public realm is created. Perhaps the aim of art should be to make places that are attractive in the maximised sense possible. And perhaps, if contemporary art does that, it should also maximise the negative.Art should do that, but it’s not going to be art. It’s going to be brutish, in ways that are difficult to quantify, and it’s going to be used for destructive ends. That has been the dilemma of modern art for decades: it wants you to invest in its image, to want to buy its work, to want to visit its art. But that investment is always predicated on assumptions about what the city is like before the internet. And the city is often brut</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up living in overcrowded conditions in dilapidated hostels. And that’s not just unpleasant. It’s a fact of life in many cities. How can we imagine cities any other way? Creativity, I guess, is constrained by the availability of space. Not all urban spaces are created equal. And yet we tend to treat them that way – that way, for instance, because the rich have always enjoyed the clear advantage in urban space. If you give the impression that the city is full of monsters, and you neglect to provide any kind of natural feature that attracts people’s imaginations, then urban life is likely to repeat itself – which is to say, it’s likely to become much more difficult to change. The rise of the super-urbanist, in other words, is a condition that can no longer be accepted. The city is expected to be increasingly like a laboratory, where experiments are carried out in an</text>
    <text>should be curated’, in the words of one commentator. It’s an interesting observation, one that raises the question: what does it mean when a work of art is considered a fabrication? When, for instance, is the Mona Lisa a forgery? When is Augusto Boal, the Ponte City mausoleum built on a medieval false sense of Christian piety, built on a false sense of architectural grandeur? When, in the words of another commentator, artefacts are considered to be often secondary to their use as forms of transport?When urban spaces are over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins them – the notion that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, leads to social ills. If you’re living in a big house and wish it to be a pleasant one, you’ll end up renting an apartment to muggled migrants. Or worse, you’ll end up homeless. When the city becomes over-determined, and the self-regulating mechanism that underpins it – the concept that you could invest in a house and wish it to be as nice as possible – is undermined, cities do things that make it easier for people to become homeless. For instance, once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house, and once you have a house,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial becomes even murkier when it comes to listening tours. As biennials recommit to their permanent venues, they are inevitably cast as a lost art form, lost in a time when travel was considered performance art. Yet, as the biennial calendar turns to to to year four (potential five in 2019), it is now a scarce commodity, and people who frequent the biennial are more and more likely to be tourists, who come to see what a biennial can do for a city. The biennial is a place-maker, a site-finder, a curator of cultural capital, and a par excellence of its own kind. It can and should do all these things in a multitude of forms, but above all it should be able to govern itself.  	So far, so normal in most cities, even in those cities that invented the biennial and continue to crown it with plaques, names, statues and plaques today. But what happens</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the cannabis industry seems to be: if you put enough of it on the market, the police will come; and if they don’t come, people will figure out ways to get high; and if the market fails, something will inevitably go bust, either because the authorities have no money or have no plan, or because people will figure out other ways to get high. In other words, the cannabis economy needs an intelligence that can readjust when the market fails. 	What makes the cannabis industry so unpredictable is its ability to turn profit in response to changes in its environment. As cannabis is classified by the DEA as a Schedule I substance, its production becomes subject to controlled access controls, which shift as the market shifts. So far, so normal, but what happens when the market shifts is also subject to change. When the cannabis plant is officially declared legal in all 50 states, sales will cease to be counted towards the DEA goal of producing opiates for human consumption. In other</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial is to offer something new and different each year, so that you can always count on something different in the future. But, as biennials everywhere learn, the hard way, the promise of quick fixes is always far too early followed by long-term too-little, far too-later solutions. That’s why biennials, including the   	Great Art Biennial, which opened in 1994, stayed put in the face of overwhelming cultural and institutional change, and which was followed by another in 1997, which was followed by another in 2011. It took thirty years for the biennial market to catch up with the new ideas and creativity swirling around in the art of the moment. 	The lesson of the cannabis crisis is that, in the age of the biennial, everything is on the line. The biennial market is too big; the biennial as a cultural form is too valuable; the biennial as an artistic medium is too limited;</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the cannabis/biennial trade seems to be that it does not matter that the economic impact of these policies is far greater in the US than in the UK; the politics of data-mining and social engineering seem unaffected by the law. The interesting thing, however, is just how many elements of the biennial trade that actually feed off each other. If the biennial is to have any real effect on the ground floor, it seems that it has to be able to feed off the good parts of the city, which is why, as biennials, we are told that we must ‘ensure that our hosts have what we would call a ‘cultural capital’. 	But what is the equivalent of a ‘cultural capital’ in the US? There is no obvious answer to that question in either European or North American capitalism. Nor is there any obvious answer to the question, which is why biennials, including in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial is to offer a history of a given art form, an index to the current state of understanding, and a platform on which a political movement can grow. The ‘big four’ in the US biennial index are all in the midst of a political revolution of some sort. 	The logic of the biennial remains as valid as ever, although the scale of the project – which is, at the moment, mostly about capitalising on the commercialisation of art within the museum – may be beginning to affect the cultural relevance of the event itself. The biennial might begin to represent the political and economic evolution of the ‘useful idiot’ as opposed to the ‘useful citizen’, the quick fixer rather than the thinker. 	Some activists within the cannabis movement are beginning to view the art institution as a home and ally themselves with those who are building self-sustaining ‘know-how’ into art institutions,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial as a visitor-supported venue seems to be that, since the city is now awash in biennials, the biennial will be a source of financial and cultural identity for the city, even if this comes at the expense of a host of vital services. The logic of the biennial as a transient art market appears to follow the logic of capital as a continuous flow of commodities, with the biennial representing the ultimate in the accumulation of capital. 	It was at the Biennale of Sydney in 2011 that the notion of the biennial as a transient cultural phenomenon entered mainstream English-speaking consciousness. The word ‘biennial’ had already been coined by The New York Times that October, and its usage that fateful fall day that year, when a tumbling brick of uncut glass and concrete rebounded off a building in New York's Financial District, lodging itself for years, if not centuries, in the form of geometrical cubes, each one</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial today is to make us ‘use it now, pay for it later’ by creating a fantasy or a hang-gliding ‘revenue stream’ by indulging in some of the most banal commodities: food, drink, art, cultural artefacts etc. But what if the payday were never in doubt? What if, instead, the availability of such things ever depended on technological advances and the whim of politicians, courts and juries? What if, as historical ephemeralism suggests, we could always travel back to the present and revisit past moments in order to learn more? 	The idea of the archaeological, or historical, is often used to describe a kind of temporality that exists between now and then. But what kinds of relations between now and then, and between artefacts and their audiences? 	When looking back to the present, we’re told that we’re obliged to revisit and understand the past in order</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial seems to be that it transacts more rapidly than the art world can gather information, which is why biennials have this special relationship to information that is both cheap (cheap access to information is good for business) and completely invisible (having just been declared a biennial, it is not subject to the vagaries of market forces, tourism, and cultural tourism). As soon as information becomes available, it is used to sell things both good and bad. Biennials have a business model that relies on the fact that, unlike any other art market, the public has little idea what art is made up of. This is why, as soon as the first biennial publishes a catalogue, it engages the public like never before. It does not have the resources or the will to continuously update itself. It is a monument to information, at best. 	The next edition, to be published in 2016, will be even shorter and more focused on pressing local problems. There</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the biennial is set against this backdrop of legalised highs, in which case the biennial is almost always a front for a new wave of drugs or contraband. The end result is that biennials, while they may account for a small slice of the overall pie, are by now almost a monopoly for a particular industry. Even if the industry is experiencing a downturn, these days these days seem preferable to the other. 	In general, biennials tend to manifest themselves as a function of a given city’s economic development, with the financial capital flowing primarily from the north to the south. 	Given the choice, most people move to the south, as it provides them with cheaper housing, better schools, and better health care. 	But over the past 15 years or so, the economics of housing and education have shifted in favour of the south, particularly in the midst of the crisis. At the same time, the social costs of housing have continued to</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data and analysis to understand how art is made and what this might mean politically. 	However, it’s also true that, as the biennial calendar turns to to to to year three (potential four in 2019), the importance of monitoring and analysis goes down even further. Art and cannabis have both recently come out of the black. The arrest and imprisonment of British artist Andy Warhol for ten years in 1971 seems like passing fables compared with the plight of cannabis users or users of other Schedule I drugs, which are still felonies in the US. Art and cannabis have come a long way since that fateful summer in 1971. And now that we have a legal cannabis market in the UK, the biennial, which began in 1993, is experiencing a financial miracle as legalise campaigners crow. As legal highs sweep the board in the cannabis biennial, the biennial with the largest domestic audience in the UK, the biennial with the lowest is yet to arrive. 	The logic of the financial biennial is simple: as soon as the legal highs kick in, the biennial will have to book in huge numbers. If it is unable to book in huge numbers, or even come close, the biennial will have to make do with a rather smaller number of exhibitions. In other words, the legal highs are the elephant in the room, and the legal highs are the settlement. The financial settlement is what makes the cultural industry work. It is the elephant in the room that begs to be taken out of the shadows. It is the elephant in the room that demands to be treated with the respect it deserves. But it is the cultural industry that settles for what it calls the 'right to be left alone' – to be able to act with dignity and self-assurance on behalf of the many. 	But the cultural industry has an even bigger cultural impact on the wider society: in order to compete in the global art market, it has to create a narrative that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the site and the context are constantly shifting and shifting, as new technologies make it easier and more economical to travel to and from, then the artefact would remain somewhat of a point of reference for contemporary art production, but would also tend to represent the technological obsessions of artists and art institutions rather than providing a dynamic tapestry of ideas and practices. 	So how can art be made to shift and change in response to these new technological infrastructures? One way is through the use of simulations, but this is by no means always possible, and even if it is possible, it is a powerful countermeasure because it creates the perception that things can, and do, shift. 	The use of new media such as  	YouTube has certainly brought new media creators into the fold, and even though the emergence of these new media is often muddled with the growth of old media (since they are usually created outside of the service provider’s context), they</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the site, the artefact and the art are all produced and delivered by hand, the artist’s role would be completely different. So while the art world might try to pin an exact figure on the number of internet users in the UK, the real answer is likely to be somewhere in the neighborhood of 10–15 million. 	There are of course many other factors that come into play when considering the totality of a geographical area’s population, but the fact of the art being produced in that area, its use, distribution and consumption, as well as its cultural institutions –  	both local and national – coming together to produce something as simple as a website, app or magazine to be downloaded across a geographical area –  	in this case, the internet – is likely to be a factor. 	Artists, curators and arts administrators in the UK have been slow to adopt the internet in large measure due to its perceived association with underground ‘scene</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in part of, the art institution, the street or the park, is part of a larger urban landscape, then the problem with the square would be much worse. 	But although the art institution certainly has a role to play in the creation and maintenance of a city, it does not play that role in a divine way. The role of the artist is to create what she or he perceives to be an experience, an artefact or set of relations, that is memorable and meaningful, in order to instill that experience in others. And although the role of the urbanist is to conceive and implement a concept or idea in a city, the role of the artist is to create what she perceives to be an experience, an artefact or set of relations, that is unique and meaningful. And whereas the urbanist might conceive of a concept or idea as a set of relations, an organisation of individuals or entities, the role of the artist is to design the relation by which that concept or</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the site, the landscape, the art –––all of it – would still be there, and all of it would be art, but we wouldn’t have that capitalizing on a natural resource. I believe that in a future world where the internet doesn’t exist, and social media doesn’t exist, but exists nevertheless, we would still need archaeological digests, museum collections and like tools to help us understand how we can contribute to the art process, and how to engage with the art in ways that are meaningful to the communities who are the creators of the tools we use to produce art. 	Another way to put it is that we would still need archaeological digests and museum collections to understand how art can be produced in a particular way, and how to produce meaningful ways of being engaged with art. This is another way of putting it: we would still need cultural geographers and anthropologists to understand how art is produced in specific situations, and how</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the art, is inherently a global production, and so consequently also the location, would remain static. Today, this is a global phenomenon, and so although the art world doesn’t always reap the benefits of the technological innovation that artists and art institutions dream of, it does all the same. 	What is now considered art may in the future be science; in the present, it may be media; but the point is that it is art nonetheless. As the internet makes possible the decentralisation of production and consumption, research and discovery will always be a global enterprise, and so will always be an element of the globalised future envisioned by artists and art institutions. 	What does it mean for an art institution to produce, or be part of the production of, art? In the past, when the term ‘art space’ was used synonymously with ‘production space’ the answer was obvious: the production of art, or at least the space in</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in took part in the World Trade Center’s redevelopment process (despite having nothing to do with the fact that art ever existed in New York or in the US), we might still be living in a world where the super-rich can get fabulously fabulously rich while everyone else sinks into poverty, but at least now everyone has a reason to be alive.  	And maybe that reason will still matter in fifty years when the super-rich have done away with the concept of the art world and everything will be run by experts in one of a number of fields of expertise. But right now we’re in a world in which technological disruption is the rule rather than the exception, and as a result most of us are subject to the rule of a few extremely rich individuals who may or may not be interested in what happens to the planet. 	What does it mean to be an artefact? To comprehend, perhaps, the significance of this new technology, what it can do and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the museum it in, the gallery it in, the estate it in, exists primarily as data feeds for other forms of media (including but not limited to blogs, Twitter, Facebook and satellite imagery), then the art world would collapse. And although this is a globalisation of artistic production right now, it is precisely because art’s realisation is so elusive and fleeting that we are so fixated on its physical manifestation, whether that’s on a pedestal, as a commodity on a par with other artworks, or as part of a media ecosystem such as a museum or an art gallery. The physical is  	present in all its real estate – whether that means the painting is on a building’s grey, black or glass façade, or whether it means that the image is projected onto a building’s facades and that building’s air quality is so bad that it practically begs the viewer’s existence to move to a</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in and the context of which it is made is constantly shifting, the art’s inherent tendency is to do the opposite: to capture what it sees as desirable and magnify its own significance, while simultaneously underestimating and rejecting what it doesn’t see. 	Similarly, the internet is massively globalised now, and as such is everywhere. It’s no longer just an island – thanks to ubiquitous mobile phones – but part of a datacentre, where users everywhere can look up what they’re supposed to do, and what they’re supposed to be doing, in real-time. This is why so many artists find the datacenter so fertile ground for their work, because it’s there for a reason: because it’s there for a reason, and because it’s there for a reason. Although there are artists who work outside the gallery context, and within the gallery context, who tend to find the internet productive and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in for is made up of glass and aluminium, this wouldn’t be an issue; the glass and aluminium would be able to shatter under the force of an impact. 	But what if the glass and aluminium in the building starts to fracture? What would happen then? The question of when this happens means something fundamentally different to artists and art institutions than it does to non-artists; when art begins to fail its own dynamism test, it’s time for a radical rethinking. If, as some artists have suggested, the future of art is created when social media allow us to connect across geographical locations and social networks, then perhaps the future of the artworld may well be created when architecture and urbanisation are greatly reduced. Perhaps it may well reside in cities that no longer exist, where artists can reside for decades or even centuries in permanent physically identical but unrelated ways, and where cultural institutions may once again exist in the form of neighbourhoods and small towns. But the key point</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated through social media, and as the internet matures and changes, so will the need for data to grow. Already, big data mining is reshaping how art is produced and consumed, and this will continue to be the case even if the internet is invented. 	What will become of the artefact? Will it revert to its natural state and become part of the landscape, as it has for thousands of years, or will it radically alter its form and become something completely different? The answer to this question is a definitive ‘no’. Art as such is inherently a global process, and as such its form and substance will always be fluid and variable. What is natural about it is that it can be controlled, and this is why artists and art institutions alike are so invested in how it appears on a map: because it’s there, and because it’s there for a reason. If it weren’t for the fact that the building it in, the art is what gives the impression of the city, then the city wouldn’t exist, and if the city were to disappear, the art would have to find a place somewhere. Therefore, while the art world would certainly love to erase the internet from existence, it would cease to be: it would cease to be an image, and instead become something completely different. 	What this means in practice is two-fold: firstly, that the art world would no longer want to invest in the infrastructure of cities, which is increasingly becoming unmanageable; secondly, that the infrastructure would cease to exist in any meaningful way; and thirdly, that the art world would no longer want to invest in the infrastructure of the city because it would no longer generate the image of the city in the way that it used to. 	So how would the art world react to such a scenario? Well, there are of course many different ways of looking at it, but the immediate reaction</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the support of the state. In other words, the institutionalisation of education is a political-institutional trick. It is expected that the institution will grow in power and influence as a result of its democratically expressed mission to educate future publics. It is this expectation that is constantly under attack in the name of neoliberalism and post-nationalism, but despite its obvious support for those seeking to rule others into submission, it is also continually undermined by those seeking to claim it for their own purposes. This constant political-institutionalising of education in Canada today is largely due to the direct and indirect collaboration of countless individual teachers' unions, whose members comprise the vast majority of the teaching force. These unions represent both the vast majority of low-income and working-class teachers in the country, as well as many students from other professions. As a result, they are often at odds with one another on issues of policy and composition, and their joint strategy to expand access to higher education remains questionable and potentially</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the involvement of political or popular power. In other words, the institutionalisation of education is often seen as necessary in order to ensure public good. In the current federal context, this means that maintaining a public good is not only an issue of pressing public needs, but also of strategic national priorities. In a 2015 report on the state of Canadian education, the National Education Association (NEA) and the Canadian Federation of Students (CFS) declared that tuition hikes were necessary to address a funding shortfalls, and that the demand for educational materials had become unmanageable. These reports were issued on the heels of a historic tuition freeze that was being implemented by all public institutions across the country. While the reports may seem to lay bare institutional failures and injustices, they also present a picture of a publicly accessible and potentially transformational public good. In the words of Murray Bookchin, ‘a public good’ entails both ‘a means of knowing and a commitment to protecting it’.[7</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the participation of the public. In other words, the institution is an entity with certain definite capacities and expectations. 	Therefore, the relationship between education and the public sphere is complex. It is possible to engage in transformative change through education without necessarily engaging the state in a public sphere, and this is precisely what the public sphere requires. It is to the detriment of both the individual and the institution as a whole.  	Thus, the public sphere is often misconstrued to mean the institutions – including the school – – – but also the community of learners (including educators), students, parents and others who engage with the educational process as students (including students who may be members of other groups, but especially the members of the privileged group of persons, such as middle- and upper-class parents, students, and employees). It is to the detriment of individuals and the institution alike. This is particularly true when the public sphere is publicly funded, as is the case with postsecondary education in Ontario</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the support of the state. This principle is often misconstrued, and a fundamental misunderstanding of the institutionalisation of education in Canada arises when state education policy is framed as a function of a school’s ‘learning landscape’. 	If the state attempts to subvert the authority of the institution by creating a differentiated public school system or providing individualized education options to individual students, it is the institution – rather than its students – who are expected to adapt and respond to this new educational terrain. In other words, the institutional capacity must be flexible and subject to change in order to meet the dynamic needs of the ever-expanding and interrelated public school sector. 	This flexibility and heterogeneity is essential to the functioning of any educational institution, but it is particularly so when it comes to the provision of high-quality education to meet the increasing needs of the ever-expanding and diverse population of students, teachers and parents who inhabit the institution’s grounds. While it is</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the support of the state. This last condition is seen as especially crucial in a country as large as Canada, where the vast majority of people remain rural and urban poor. It is believed that the political will is still lacking to end institutional poverty, but in the past few years concerted action is beginning to emerge on the ground level. For example, the End Hunger Movement is an emerging national grassroots movement that seeks to end hunger through a three-tiered agricultural system.4. Education and democracy in the age of abundance. 	The digital revolution has fundamentally transformed the educational process. The former bureaucratic imperative of teaching and promoting knowledge has been replaced by the power of the machine. The educational function is no longer confined to educating practitioners of a discipline to profess knowledge; machines now impart knowledge as much as they do through their ubiquity and proliferation. This transformation in the educational process is sometimes characterised as ‘devolution’, in that individuals now wield considerable political and economic influence over what is taught and</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the knowledge and involvement of the public. In other words, the institution is a check against the public good. If the institution is too present and has too much power, it is also expected that the public will somehow step back in order to be consulted and to influence the outcome of crucial decisions. 	In the case of a democratically-institutionalised school, students would enter through the front door, walk through classrooms, participate in board meetings and take part in creative projects throughout the school year. They would then leave the building and begin a new academic year where they would participate in assemblies and engage in community action projects throughout the city. In many ways, this scenario mirrors the way in which our current education system operates. In this model, students enter the building through the front door, participate in classes and then graduate, participate in cooperative and collective learning programmes throughout the year and engage in community action projects throughout the year. In many ways, this scenario also mirrors the way in which Mao Zedong thought</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the support of the state. In other words, the institutional school must be responsive to the interests of the governed in order to fulfil its stated mission. 	In his address to the 1916 National Education Conference, John A. Macdonald outlined the institutionalised role of the school in the Canadian public sphere: to some extent it is an instrument of the state ‘in the making’ of Canadian culture. Macdonald concluded by proposing an alternative institutional structure that would ‘reproduce the mystery and magic of “old”” and nurture the creativity of “new””’: 	[T]he present school cannot […] educate “all”, but’it can’’t educate all students, nor can it educate all citizens, nor both.’4 Like the federation of school districts in the US, or the urban school district in Britain, the district is a unit of the state that is sovereign in its</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the involvement or involvement of Parliament. In other words, the institution is seen as a positive agent rather than an instrument of oppression. 	In the 1970s and 1980s, the pedagogical practices of the day were given a radical reorientation through a radical pedagogical approach to the knowledge economy of education. This was most evident in the book  	By G. Paul Lynd, who co-authored the classic work, Schools, that was followed by several sequels including several collections of essays that were collected and published in a journal called The Juvenile Record. Lynd also wrote the award-winning posthumous work, A Simple Manifesto that was followed by several collections of poetry and essays as well as several collections of index cards and magazine articles. Lynd was a writer and editor. 	The historical persistence of ‘education as a social' discourse is largely a product of two events: the Sixties Cultural revolution and the AIDS epidemic. Both movements were built on the</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the participation of the public. If the institution is to have any transformative effect, its institutional capacity must be maintained in perpetuity. As noted by the late sociologist Peter McCaughey, changing the institutions of higher education is seen as a public good in its own right, rather than a radical disjunction between the institutions and the publics. This is, of course, in part due to the widespread adoption of courses by non-traditional degree-seeking students, many of whom have their own set of institutionalised education inclinations. 	4. 	Immigrant Movement International (2010-ongoing). IMI council members at a January 2011 training session in Mississauga, Ontario. Photo taken during IMI Corona conference in Toronto. 	Immigrant Movement International (2010-ongoing). IMI council members at a January 2011 training session in Mississauga, Ontario. Photo taken during IMI Corona conference in Toronto. 	Immigrant Movement International (2010-ongoing). I</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. What the government can and must do with regards to schools and training is a different story. The government has a significant role to play in creating a climate conducive to the creation of independent schools and ensuring that schools do not become instruments for the social engineering of individuals or groups.  	3. Education as a political-institutional tool. 	The power to create and reform schools and educate individuals must come from above, and it is this fundamental principle that underpins the institutionalisation of education in Canada. This principle is what makes it institutionalised in the first place: the school, like the state, is required to be responsive to the desires and priorities of an entrenched and powerful minority. Any attempt to subvert this obligation is seen as fundamentally inconsistent with the public good. 	At the same time, the institution – which is often called upon to engage in transformative change – is also expected to maintain its institutional capacity, meaning that it can carry out its mandated tasks with or without the support of the state. Thus, the institutionalisation of education is often seen as a necessary condition of any progressive agenda. In fact, this is often seen as a precondition for any progressive agenda: the more we demand of education, the less we will actually deliver; namely, the perpetuation of inequality and oppression. In the current political context of austerity measures and massive deficits, it is imperative that we strive to constructively engage the institutional capacity of our education system, but this –  	above all – must come from above. Otherwise, what is meant by radically transforming our educational infrastructure – transforming it from the bottom up, in order to the top down – is really just anchoring of existing inequality and oppression. Current educational paradigms are often seen as the necessary outcome of in-depth, long-term research into the history and nature of education, and thus demandingly-intensive, rendered-in-process educational paradigms are usually developed in response to a set</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
