<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in D
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar. It transmits signals across the historical and contemporary dimensions of the city, creating a virtual double bind in the metropolis that is drawn up around a single tower. The installation is a powerful symbol of the city’s increasing urbanisation under the guise of addressing a void in the city. The tower is a double bind – it is sensitive to changes in its footprint, but also subject to the whims of a changing geopolitical order. ‘Signal’ is an epic poem by none other than the poet Hafiz Saeedi.Safieedi’s poem, which was one of the top ten most read on Twitter in the United Kingdom at the end of 2013, begins: Though the metropolis writhes with signs of stress, a little comfort can be found in the fact that ‘there’s a reason why the metropolis breathes.’ The poem is a lament for the excesses and abuses of capitalism. But it is also</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar. The project was officially launched by the artist and his team in English and Dohaese newspapers on 7 June 2014. The artist’s own journal entry from the same journal entry device found its way into the local media as well. 	This project was a response to a broader question that has been circulating around social media: in the age of the ubiquitous media reportage, why are journalists reluctant to report the news? As the journalist David Graham Kerr puts it, when ‘false starts, mistakes and leaks are allowed to happen, there is a risk that a bigger story will be told – and told badly – about the region that is being told.’1 To some extent, this was also true of the post-WWII period, when the media was understandably reluctant to present the geopolitical landscape that was unfolding in the Middle East in a way that would tip the balance in favour of imperialist interests. But as the decades went by, and the media increasingly relied on</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar. It transmits information about construction works and the state of the environment in the Arab world. When activated, it produces a variety of effects, from purifying the local air to dispersing [smog’s particles] across large areas to augment the city’s urban fabric. —Graham Turner 	[1] The idea of a biennale as an event that engages with the notion of place first arises in English that way that biennials – and their host countries – engage with ideas of time. In  	The Erosion of Places (1937), Henri Bergson develops this in relation to the emergence of a ‘glimmer of new ideas about human life’ that had to be confronted. He traces these fading ‘metaphors’ to a ‘metaphor-rich source: the old idea of linear time’.[2] Gross and his ilk were, in other words</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar. It transmits news of incidents unfolding all around the World in real-time. More and more people are becoming aware of the signals that the city […][…][…][…][…][1] and its streets provide for their continued existence. Local people’ take pride in their historical and urban significance, and in fact, in the fact that the archaeological dig at their neighborhood site of the Great Mosque of Doha, conducted by the Qatar Museums Authority, is the largest archaeological dig in the country.  	[2] See, for example, Lou Kalrahan and Amber Dean, eds.,  	Signal: Art and Architecture in a Decentered Society (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2017), p. 1–16.[3] See, for example, Towards a Research-Based Economy, a project led by the London School of Economics and the London School of Physics,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar, and it broadcasts live images of the city. The installation, which in Doha is often referred to as ‘The West Wall’ or simply the ‘Eiffel Tower’ after the structure’s name, is part of a larger renovation project that is also dedicated to the architectural character of the old city. It forms part of a plan to modernise the old city centre, which is to be integrated back into the historic district of Doha. The project is being led by architect and Doha-based firm QMA. The new architecture is to be ‘reclaimed’ by the local people, according to a press release issued by the firm in conjunction with the artist’s residency. It is to be ‘reclaimed’ in the sense of the local people’s mixed reactions to the industrial revolution and the postindustrial society it has created.The press release also suggests that the ‘Signal project’</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar, and is reporting on the latest developments there. The installation itself was designed with a retractable glass roof and self-contained power supply. The novel it tells is a hybrid of traditional forms of art and civil defence, using film noir tropes to explore the political and social implications of a large-scale reconfiguration of infrastructure. In the words of the artist, who has a long-term project underway that aims to reconstruct the Doha of the 1990s, the ‘Signal’ is a tool for &quot;revolutionary politics and social transformation[…] It is a new kind of infrastructure that is neither dam, railroad, nor city […] It is a society without a state […] It is a kind of assembly line’ that is run by and for the people, producing not only products but also organising world views, orienting space, and in some cases, creating or shaping reality&quot;[7] Such political and social imaginaries are among those told in</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar – the Doha Tower. The installation of this system in the building that was once a meeting point for many different subcultures of people from all over the world, including many cultures from many different parts of the world, is now used by an international network of humanitarian organisations, including the Red Crescent, working in cooperation with many local residents' associations. The system transmits imagery, data, audio and video – all in real time – of developments in the region, often including geographical locations and historical periods – all in the interests of humanitarianism, democracy promotion and peace.” The artwork was presented as a limited edition one-off curatorial gesture that, in its own way, signalled the end of an era. It became part of a larger exhibition programme being curated by the curator, using materials from the museum collection and international art fairs at the time. The epigraph was cut and pasted from a document prepared by the Emir of Qatar and submitted as part of</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar, and will remain online for years to come. This is the story of how a young person in Qatar came up with a new way of visualising the contemporary urban environment through reporting on events in the region.  	Figure 1: Model built by Doha Future City for the exhibition,  	Signal, located at the Qatar Museums Authority, 2014.  	[1] Gareth White,  	Visual Cultures: Ancient Greece to the Present Time, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009, p.20.Download this article as PDFGareth WhiteGareth White is an artist with a curatorial practice who has exhibited extensively worldwide, including in The New York Art Museums, The California Association of Independent Curators, PHC, Barcelona, and Venice. He has written for The New York Times, The New York Times Digital Briefing, The New York Times Weekend Magazine, The New York Times Higher Ground</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar. The building, which the artist has named as ‘The Egyptian Presentation Room’, is the final word in the soundproof booth of the modern Egyptian present. When completed, the system will be able to project images and sound into a completely different world, called ‘The Egyptian Present’. 	[1] The epigraph is a response to the newspaper clippings that regularly appear in the Old Doha Newspaper, a publication produced by the Qatar Museums Authority (QMA). The clippings, which frequently refer to events in Doha, are a combination of past and future, recording the ‘current events’ that occurred in Doha prior to the art installation being installed.[2] The opening sequence of Steven Soderbergh’s Contagion of 2011 is a perfect example of this. In the film, a group of activists form a human chain to try to stop a nuclear weapons program, using seismic alerts</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist himself, who commissioned the works to be viewed as a statement of intent. The installation, entitled  	Signal, is a series of print poems that appear as part of a three-month residency at the Tate Britain, 2014. The print poems, which take the form of ‘bulletins’ sent from the Tate, are a direct response to the daily newspaper clippings of the ‘signal[…]system’, which reported on developments in Mesopotamia from a variety of media outlets. The ‘Bulletins’ form an extended epigraph that narrates the narrative of the ‘Signal Project’, taking the form of a chronicle published monthly in a local newspaper in the region where the conflict is occurring. In the epigraph, the reporters write: The signal system that the artist […][…]] has been developing for over a year now is installed in one of the most prominent buildings in Doha, Qatar, and will remain operational for at least another five years. The installation is a ‘monument of technological innovation’, and its continued operation signifies a major step forward for Doha, Qatar, and the world.1 The installation is one of a number of displays during the exhibition, Doha: The City of Parallel Universes, 2014, curated by Hussain Mumtaz, 2Doha, Qatar, 3Doha, Qatar, and 4Doha, Qatar. The other displays during the exhibition 2Doha: The City of Parallel Universes represent recent advances in the city’s digitised version of Muzaffar Ali Abdullah, the city’s first digital artist, as a result of the ongoing Doha Digital Art Project. The exhibition is the result of a three-year collaboration between the Doha Digital Art Project (2013-16), the Qatar Museums Authority (QMA) and the artist</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money to establish a non-profit land trust that would later be used to establish a private wildlife park in the San Joaquin Valley. The park would have included a number of rare and threatened species of wildlife, including bison, elk, horse, bighorn sheep, badger and bighorn sheep pairs, as well as tribal members and local residents. The park would have been privately owned and operated – unlike the USA today – and it was to have been a sanctuary for threatened, Endangered and Protected Species, as well as local residents and visitors. The park would have been managed by a non-profit land trust established in California under the auspices of the California Parks and Recreation Commission (CPSC).The cancellation of the Venice Biennale is important for understanding the reasons for the current state of California wildlife policy. If the Biennale had been able to take place in the USA under the same terms and conditions as in Venice, it is likely that the Bi</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money for the development of alternative economies. So the closure of the chapter may have had another unforeseen consequence. The odd jobs that the Venice Biennale had performed as a public good may have found new uses. The Venice Biennale may have been able to find new audiences elsewhere in the world through its arts and culture legacies, but these organisations are passing on to future generations a burden of public relations. The Venice Biennale has a responsibility to act in good faith and to provide a meaningful programme of engagements. In the USA, it may be too late for that to happen in a timely fashion. In 2020, the Biennale will be organising its eleventh Venice Biennale, and in two years time it will be organising a 30th edition. The Venice Biennale is a venerable international art institution with roots in the Venetian city. It was founded in 1875 and continues to be a major international art institution, with works from every continent, in many cities throughout</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money from the foundation’s Charitable Fund to support a series of &quot;free-market&quot; think-tanks in California. These would have funded the formation of anti-capitalist political parties, and possibly libertarian or anarchist parties. The reason for this was that these parties were seen as too right-wing for the times and were therefore not part of the Koch plan. Instead, the biennale was to support a host of right-wing causes across the state of California. So the chapters that had been planned for California were instead sent to regional offices in other states. And these regional offices would in turn recruit other states for their own chapters.In this way, the biennale was able to exist in a political framework separate from the times, but it also sent a political signal to other art institutions in the US and internationally that the time had come to reorganise themselves. These would have included not only the Venice Biennale, but also the regional and local offices that it established</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money raised for the arts in local communities to support the development of alternative economic models in the region. Arts and cultural organisations here in the USA were quick to respond by opening arts centres and educational institutions in underserved communities. In 2014, the Oklahoma Art Bureau opened its Oklahoma Cultural Centre, which offers free art-making and public cultural activities to low-income communities. The Art Bureaus in L.A. and San Diego established partnerships with community organisations in order to provide free cultural and educational opportunities to local youth. In effect, these cultural agencies found a home here, provided the resources and the political leverage to be able to say yes to lucrative cultural tourism, and then worked with community organisers and tourism commissions to ensure that the communities they worked with actually used the tourism revenue for projects in their neighbourhoods. This may be another story, but it is an example of cultural agency emerging through the buying and selling of cultural power.Art is a universal language; art can be bought in almost every corner of</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money raised for the US and Italian chapters of the Rome Biennale to support projects in the Middle East and Africa. The decision to cancel the planned California Chapter came as a surprise to many artists and to many artists not associated with the project. It was also a surprise to Venice itself, which had hoped to use the money to support an independent local arts scene. It was also a surprise to artists who had been collaborating with the Biennale on an independent basis on a temporary or limited basis, while the Biennale was on life support. The cancellation of the planned California Chapter came as a surprise to the artists as well, since the Chapter had been voluntary and self-financing. It was only after intense lobbying from local artists and the California Arts Council that the Biennale was forced into permanent administration in 2011.Artists and performers were left with little choice but to leave the Biennale as a temporary or limited basis. The Biennale’s support depended on the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money from the foundation’s Charitable foundations to launch an independent political action committee, not associated with the California Chapter, to support conservative candidates in the 2012 and 2016 presidential elections. The Koch brothers’ purchase of the California Trust Company in 1887 gave the foundation broad political and institutional power, and through a variety of well-intended but ultimately ineffective actions, including the creation of the California Biennial, founded in 1990, the Biennial was able to create a parallel universe where all political ideologies were placated.In this parallel universe, the Biennial began a sustained programme of events designed to establish its institutional knowledge and power base, and began to think about its relationship to its global community. It established partnerships with large corporations, including those involved in California ‘s agriculture and food systems’; established a partnership with the California Agricultural College, which offered training in Inventing Accountancy to any aspiring artist interested in entering the biennial sphere; established the California Biennial Liaison</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money from the cancelled projects to establish a global religious-educational network focused on libertarianism and individualism. The chapter would have been based in California and funded by the Foundation through a private gift.Instead, the project was put into the hands of a private company, which put it into operation in Qatar, where it was run by the Foundation’s trustees. The Doha Development Company was established in Doha, Qatar, and is a founding member of the Foundation’s trustees. The company has a board of directors, which includes representatives from the United States and Qatar. It is the largest shareholder in the Foundation, with a voting interest of up to 90% in the company. The trustees also own a minority interest in the company. The interests of the holding companies in the new company are shared between the two groups. The owners of the company are the Qatar Council of Contributing Companies (QCC), a private company established by the Qataris to manage the construction of the D</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money from the cut of the fossil-fuel tax-free to start a private non-profit land-use organisation, the Koch-E company, which would own the land and operate the biennale. As a result of this and other Koch-funded non-profit initiatives, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (1998–2011), which was set to focus on the history of urban culture in the USA, was merged with the California Museum of Contemporary Art (2011–16), which was set to focus on the history of postindustrial and urban development in the USA. The California Museum of Contemporary Art, which became the California Academy of Sciences, was to have been a regional hub for the museum of art and the culture of the future, drawing artists from all over the USA and abroad. However, the museum of art, which morphed into the California Museum of Creative Strategies, attracted artists dissatisfied with the monoculture of the museum of art, which entailed institutionalised forms of exhibitionism</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money raised for the arts in local communities to build solar projects and wind turbines in Oakland, but the Biennale cancelled these projects due to budget constraints. So the artists who were planning to do a biennale in Oakland instead made alternative biennales in other cities. For instance, in 2014, the Biennale in Vienna used the money from the Austrian government to fund a series of self-built community arts projects in other cities.And the fourth reason may be connected to the introduction of micro-grants, which were initially funded by the Biennale and then distributed to local artists' organisations. Micro-grants have since shifted funding to the local communities. So some of the artists who were thinking about doing a biennale in the USA in the future may now have to reconsider.I see artists who are now considering doing a series of small-scale projects in their local communities. I see artists who are considering doing a biennale in their own neighbourhoods. I see</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial may be remembered for a number of reasons. The most obvious is the war that erupted in the Persian Gulf. Many artists were killed or ill and the Persian Gulf became a symbol of global conflict. Many artists were repatriated to their countries of origin but many were not. And some were not able to return and remain in their countries.The second reason may be connected to the 23rd Venice Biennale, in which Florentine artist Pier Paolo Pasolini staged a retrospective of the work that he had already done when he died in 1964. The Venice Biennale had invited Pasolini to participate in a private project. The Venice Biennale – with its rich patron organisations and well-funded public programmes – ensured that Pasolini would have the opportunity to continue his artistic career elsewhere.The third reason may be connected to the virtual abolition of the biennial in the USA in 2011, when the Charles G. Koch Foundation cancelled the planned California Chapter. The Koch Foundation had planned to use the money for 'social and political activities of a broad range of interest to the Foundation’s goals, but the sudden and total abolition of the biennial seemed to conflict with the Foundation’s long-term interests. So the art world reacted by trying to find another place to play its part in the society that had been abolished. The result was a crisis of participation that was partly created by the biennial itself. The art world had to find another organisational form to play its part in the society that was no longer there.The fourth and finally unexceptionable reason may be connected to the invention of the smartphone. The smartphone is a manufactured object and as such is subject to the same social, economic and political forces as any other manufactured item. It was invented as a way to access information about goods and services produced or supplied by another place. And just as the biennial had become a production line for the social conditions that now accompanied the production of objects, so the smartphone was conceived</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6  The research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’ was part of a wider research project entitled ‘Camouflage’7 which was jointly funded by the Academy and the Newcastle University Art Department.8 The Art and Research Centre was part of a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’9 which was jointly funded by the Academy and the Newcastle University Art Department.10  The research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’10 also found funding from the Arts Council through the ‘Camouflage and Art Fund'11 and the ‘Royal Academy of Arts’12 Early in its research, and continuing to this, the Art and Research Centre is still engaging with the question of what it means to be an art institution. This is particularly significant in light of the increasing financial interstices between the Academy and the University, which could be used to undercut the costs of artist-per</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6  The 10-year research project was led by Professor Alan Walker, with support from the Arts Council and the DfID.7  Walker and his team spent two years in South-East Asia, Australia, and New Zealand, including a two-year stint at the Otago Museum of Art, where they documented the history of minimus and urban camouflage in New Zealand.8 The second year of the research project was led by Professors Debasish Desai and Olafur Eliasson, with support from the Arts Council and the DfID.9 The research projects were part of a wider cultural exchange programme organised by the Academy and the city of Newcastle.10  The Newcastle Arts Forum was a project of the 10th Academy Awards held in November 2001.11  The Academy’s Research Centre for Photography and Digital Art (ACRDA) and the city’s Photography and Digital Art Students Association (PDSA</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6 The Institute of Contemporary Arts and Museum of Modern Art in New York initiated the project by commissioning the Museum of Modern Art and the Institute of Art and Architecture in London to establish a joint commissioning institute.7 The two institutions established a commissioning institute, which in turn established the Newcastle Museum and the Royal Academy of Arts. The Newcastle Museum was established as a museum of modern art in the city, while the Royal Academy of Arts was established as a museum of art and culture in the country.8  The Institute of Contemporary Arts and the Royal Academy of Arts both maintained permanent exhibitionary collections, which they used to fund research-based programmes into their art worlds. The Institute of Contemporary Arts maintained a permanent collection of works on loan from the Royal Academy of Arts, while the Royal Academy maintained a permanent collection of works on loan from the Museum of Modern Art. The collections were used to support a number of research programmes into their respective fields, including the Institute of Contemporary Arts</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies. The 10 Years of Camouflage Painting project was part of this wider research project, and the following diagram illustrates the spatial distribution of the artworks commissioned through it:6 A map of the United Kingdom, created by DigitalGlobe, identifies the regions where artists have exhibited their work in the United Kingdom over the past ten years. 	The A. Alfred Taube Foundation is a Washington, DC–based non-profit arts organization founded in 1960 with the mission of supporting the critical arts activities of the public in `global art' (as defined by the British Council) through arts and culture programs. Its current funding comes from individual donors; corporate foundations; the Taube Foundation; the British Council; and the United Arts Council.7 	The Taube Foundation’s current annual budget is £250,000, distributed among various projects across the UK and abroad.8 	The 10 Years of Camouflage Painting project is a research project at the University of Newcastle</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6 As part of this, the Royal Academy of Arts established a Camouflage &amp; Fleece Scheme to award funding for research-based projects in the art and art-related disciplines of minimus.7  The RAA funded research projects in the art and art-related disciplines of camouflage, such as that led by Dr Vanessa Beebe and funded by the UK’s Department for Transport and Transport for Northern Ireland.8  The RAA’s support for art-related research projects was also extended by the Arts Council, whose funding was conditional upon a certain number of artists being trained in the art of minimus, and were to be staffed with artists from the Arts Council Schools and the Camouflage Scheme staff.9  This relationship between the Academy and the University was illustrated in a number of ways. The most obvious one was the provision of artists’housing and studio space, which was limited to artists who had full-time</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6 The 10 Years of Camouflage Painting project envisaged a five-year long curatorial and research project into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment,6  (2015–2019) with the Newcastle Artspace, commissioned by the Arts Council, the National Museums Commission and the Arts Council, and part of the wider Newcastle Regional Region (NCR)8 Research &amp; Development Centre (NCR)9 Research &amp; Development Center (NCR)10 ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’ commissioned by the Newcastle Artspace and part of the wider Newcastle Regional Region (NCR)10  and part of the Centre’s Research &amp; Design Centre (CrCD)11  funded by the Arts Council and NH8. Some of the projects envisaged a return to the roots of minimus, such as the minimus rift, although the main thrust of the curatorial direction was developing a 'new approach' to what had been</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6 The 10 Years of Camouflage Painting project was one of these, commissioned in 2010 and 2011 respectively, and the subsequent projects into minimus, which were part of a wider research project into art and culture into which the Academy had invested much of its early research and cultural capital.7  The rationale for this massive, long-term, multi-year cultural capital-laying and cultural reproduction project was that, as the Commission on Cultural Relations had long realised, the art and craft of minimus – the art, crafts and materials of minimus, including the minimus itself – lay outside the parameters of acceptable cultural objects, outside the reach of permissible artistic and curatorial influence, and above all, outside the remit of the Union Jack.8 The rationale for this massive, long-term, multi-year cultural capital-laying and cultural reproduction project was that, as the Commission on Cultural Relations had long realised, the art and craft of minimus – the art,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6  The 10th Biennale of Camouflage Paintings opened on 14 January 2013, in Lisbon, Portugal, and the following June, in Berlin, Germany. The research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’ was part of a wider research project entitled ‘Camouflage: Geographical Indicators’7 which was jointly undertaken by the Academy and the University of Bristol.8 Both the A and UCAN commissioning departments were led by eminent artist-in-residence, Frans de Waard.9 The 10th edition of the Biennale was curated by Frans de Waard and published in October 2014.10 The project was part of a wider research project entitled  	10 Years of Camouflage Painting’11 which was also jointly undertaken by the Academy and the University of Bristol.12 The project received funding from the Danish Council for Independent Research (contemporaneous with the Academy</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6  The 10-year research project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’7 which was jointly undertaken by the Academy and the University of Glasgow.8 The research project involved artists, photographers and art workers from across the UK and Scotland taking part in a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Painting and Concealing the British Army’.9  The 10-year research project also involved artists, photographers and art workers from other parts of the UK and Scotland taking part in a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Painting and Concealing the Lutheran Dies’.10  The images in each of the four books were sourced to documentary and photographic documentary makers who could identify with the themes and concerns of the project.11  The research project was part of a wider programme of joint research projects between the Academy and the University of Glasgow, funded by the Arts Council and the Scottish Arts</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by Newcastle University’s Artistic Office, which invited artists to explore aspects of their practices through a research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’.1  The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’2 which was commissioned by the Art and Research Centre (formerly known as the Royal Academy of Arts) and the Newcastle University Art Department, and tasked with exploring the contemporary art practice of ‘Camouflage Painting’ (or more correctly, camouflage painting).3 The project was part of a wider research project entitled ‘10 Years of Camouflage Painting’4 which was commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and the Newcastle University Art Department.5 The projects were part of a wider joint initiative between the Academy and the University to develop research-based projects into the art and culture of minimus, or urban concealment, through a series of commissioned works and residencies.6  The 10 Years of Camouflage Painting project concluded in 2016, but the interests of the artist remain relevant. In 2017, when Uma Thuraya did the same for Shadow, we asked: what would you do if you no longer painted in urban settings? Here, she reflects on that moment when she decided to continue living as she has since 1976: �I painted portraits of contemplative people in the margins of larger cities. In the years that followed, other artists did the same. The result was a kind of metamorphosis: the painted city became a kind of practice in itself. 	Thuraya’s paintings are characterised by a chronic sense of time spent in the present, questioning the permanence of experience and the relationship between appearance and memory. Questions of appearance are questions that are difficult to answer in a definitive way, but questions of memory are questions that can be answered with sufficient frequency that the art of colouring in graffiti is no longer a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something further.But the way in which the museum and the gallery is structured today makes that impossible. Music, theatre, dance, sports venues, events such as the Liverpool Biennial, which was so helpful in turning young people off cigarettes, are now structures of the city and used as delivery systems for a culture of consumption. And once you have that culture of consumption – which is being sold as being culturally responsive despite its actual being cliched – then you have to engage it, to make it real, to make it interesting, to make it useful. And that requires people who actually live and work in the city to be part of the equation. That’s what a museum is for. That’s what a gallery is for. What a marque is for the working class. That’s what a district is for the rich. That’s what a town hall is for the elite. And once those things are in place, once they are there long</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something cool with it. But there is this whole rub, or rubric, that young people use: rubric, which is short for Something Young Person’s Guide. It was this rubric that young people used when choosing artists and artworks for the Hayward Art Gallery’s exhibition venue. It was this rubric that young people used when choosing artworks for the Hayward Art Gallery’s permanent collection. It was this rubric that young people used when deciding on projects for the Hayward Art Gallery’s online art gallery The Gallery Above Ground. It was this rubric that young people used when deciding on restaurants for the local cinema. It was this rubric that young people used when deciding on schools for the local secondary school. It was this rubric that young people used when deciding on shops for the local supermarket. It was this rubric that young people used when deciding on sports grounds for the local stadium. It was this rubric that young people used when</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something else. But there are other, more subtle forms of cultural patronising involved as well. Not all art institutions in the world, of course, have the same kind of cultural missions. And, again, Hayward is only one of many examples of a single artist being given a kind of cultural high horse by a single institution.I don’t quite know what to make of all this. I don’t quite know what to make of it. I don’t know what to do with it.I remember, years ago (around 2003), thinking that maybe the reason why some artists were so successful was precisely because they were given a kind of cultural horse by their institutions. Why were artists able to get funding from institutions for their art projects? Because their institutions were so reliant on commercial sources of funding, and so dependent on the development of ideological frameworks and priorities. So, for instance, if the Islamic arts institutions in the UK or the Museo Islamice in Lisbon</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something with their lives. But it’s much more complicated than that.The mission statement of the Hayward Art Gallery, which I found very difficult to understand, is a kind of a cheat sheet for what the gallery might do with the art it acquires. It gives the gallery complete control – not to mention the legal right to take the art back if it doesn’t like it or to sue if it does. In other words, the gallery can either buy the art or not buy it. The Art Gallery of Bologna, which I visited in an attempt to understand the mission statement of the B.A.B.'s Florence House project, had a kind of a back door that invited you in if you were not supposed to be there. It wasn’t a very sophisticated hiding place, but it did make the Art Gallery of Bologna somewhat invisible in the city.In the 1960s and 1970s, the Biennale was an annual ritual that</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something cool with their lives. Except that this isn’t what young people do with their lives. They have careers, and often very different lives-styles from the young people who attend the Hayward Art Gallery. So, the mission creep, which is a part of museum-building, starts earlier and is much more visible.The second part of the mission creep, which is happening at the Hayward Art Gallery but is also happening at the Museum of Modern Art, is engaging the community itself in creating a kind of cultural district in which the art can be done in ways that will be pleasant and convenient to them. This may involve engaging the community through participatory ways of engaging with the art, or producing art that serves a different kind of mission – engaging because it’s there, making sense of it, knowing what’s being done with it and why and how it fits into society. For example, the Circulation board that’s developing in the neighborhood around the museum</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something else.But here’s the rub: while engaging young people in something that’s going to enrich their lives is great, what it’s really about is capitalising on that young people’s capital and using that capital to do something else. And that’s what museums do. They capitalize on that capital and use it to do something else. And that something else is going to be art. And, by the way, the thing is more about the Art Gallery than it is the Biennial. The Biennial is the thing that engages the people who are going to be its future visitors. It’s what brings people in from the outside in and of itself. If the Hayward Art Gallery can’t claim that title, well, that wouldn’t be a biennial. It would be a curatorial biennial. The problem with the Hayward is that it’s become something that’s almost synonymous</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to make something better. And, yes, that is exactly what the Hayward Public Gallery did. But it wasn’t a mission that was inherently adventurous, exploratory or pluralistic. It was a mission confined to the interests of a very narrow kind of person: that is, a very narrow kind of person who happens to be a visitor to the Hayward Art Gallery. That kind of narrow person is not likely to engage with or understand art or art culture outside of the narrow parameters of her or his group.I don’t have a narrow kind of person. I have a broader kind of person who happens to be visiting from the Bay Area. And, if I do, I’m not surprised if she or he finds art or a particular form of art distressing or even provocative. I’m interested in how art is produced in a particular culture, and how that impacts how we think about art as art, and how that impacts how we act and think about culture and</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something else.But it’s also that simple: to achieve that kind of cultural impact, you need artists, you need venues, you need a network of artists, you need festivals, you need a website, you need social interaction, and, above all, you need people to enjoy the art. The problem with the museum is that, as the Art Gallery of New Zealand shows, that is all you can do. You need talented curators, and, for many reasons, that can be difficult to find. The Art Gallery of New Zealand declined to make its curators available for an interview, but a document released by the museum shows that the journal entry was written soon after the end of the First Opium War in 1840. It seems that the conflict between the artist and the museum was over an entry on a canvas that had been previously given to the British Museum. The curators clearly think that the painting should be incorporated into the museum, although it is notable that the entry</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to make something better. And, oh, how the mission has been accomplished.I think the real mission has been accomplished in other places as well. The mission of the New York Public Library is to bring books from around the city to be donated to public libraries around the country. And, oh, the missions have been accomplished in other places as well. The mission of the LA County Museum of Art is to restore the historic vault of the Public Theater, which was destroyed in the city’s blighting project known as The Big Easy. The LA History Museum is trying to figure out what to do with the huge vault of film and television footage that was left behind after the city’s massive and expensive Culture City video arts project was put on hold in the wake of the AIDS epidemic.The real magic of museums, I think, is in the margins – the places where the real magic happens. Where the magic happens where the art and the people don’t quite connect. That was</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial which was completely sold out within hours but, miraculously, not one of the dozens of cancelled or rescheduled exhibitions will ever see the light of day. But, as the legend on the back of the forty-five-inch biennial exhibition Vorticism ‘Claimed World War One’ makes clear, that was only ever going to happen if you were part of a museum.The museum perhaps has a kind of rarefaction – talented young people who become cultural patrons or, in the case of a Hayward arts institution, young people who find art elsewhere in the world. Curators at the Hayward Art Gallery, who I am told are among the best in the country, are among those people. They have a kind of a mission, although I don’t quite know what that is. It sounds simple enough: get young people to see art, engage them in something that’s going to enrich their lives and then, if they like it, commission them to do something more.But the way in which arts education has to be delivered within the museum, and the museum needs to find a way of supporting that education, is different from the way it has to be delivered elsewhere. The Hayward Art Gallery, which has a long-standing partnership with the Museum of Contemporary Art, has to find a way of supporting this kind of learning within the museum. The kind of educational programmes put forward by the Biennial, and the museums in that vein, are academic programmes, not ‘real life’ based programmes, and the way in which art is often presented within the context of those programs – not the way in which the artist is presented elsewhere. So the educational programmes of the biennials today are a little bit different from those of the mid-1990s, and they are a little bit different from those of the early 1990s. They are put forward as a solution to a problem which, at the time, was much more ‘averse</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air,
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the Panhandle, the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, soon after the first article was published, was a major influence on the city’s development. The introduction of subways and cars into the political equation made it easier to subdue public dissent, while the increased industrial production that followed the introduction of textiles and packaging was matched by a corresponding reduction in employment.The introduction of automobiles into the political equation made it easier to subordinate workers to corporate interests, while the expansion of airports and sea ports made it easier to ignore them. The advent of the automobile coincided with the increasing importance of image and heraldry in the public sphere, which made it easier to spot public works, such as the Mulholland Lighthouse and the SoMa Subway, that would later be renamed the John Lennon Memorial Trail and the Fernando Cruz Memorial Trail, respectively. The advent of the automobile also coincided with the development of the world’s largest and most widely read newspaper, the New York Times</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, as well as the airport, transformed the site into a major international airfield. The creation of a ‘warren’ of housing projects, many of which were built on the site of the former Los Angeles Municipal Airport, combined with the rapid growth of the city, eventually generated enough demand for a further seventeen National Park Service land grants covering much of the site.  The Biennial would relocate many of its visitors to areas closer to the proposed site, including to areas adjacent to the Transbay Tract, a collection of residential streets that is part of the Transbay Area Rapid Transit District. The change in the site’s character would be attributed to the development of the Tenderloin and its environs, as well as to the development of the Transbay Expressway and its elevated rail line.  The Biennial’s proposed cityscape would stretch west to east across the peninsula from Northern California to Georgia, including a cityscape similar to that of Liverpool, but</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the construction of new intermodal freight tunnels under the LA-Subway elevated tracks, were two other factors. The rapid transit lines would carry passengers between the new and old SoMa districts in a matter of minutes, rather than the decades or even decades of the former zoos. This would mean a major reduction in the size of the exhibits, and a significant increase in the number of exhibits, since the rapid transit lines would be the only means of transportation between the two new zones. Second, and more importantly, this meant that the exhibits would be mobile, since the architects’ plans for the site called for a new kind of urbanism, one in which exhibits would be left to chance and nature, and would be left to the elements. This kind of urbanism is the opposite of what the present really is, and the effect of this kind of urbanism is to tear at the fabric of the city, leaving behind what Arthur Caplan, the geologist, and his team</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the airport, which would make possible the construction of a large military airbase, was a major factor in the development of the area. The proposed airport would have provided convenient access to the proposed zoo, as well as the sea and airfreight links leading to and from the proposed terminal. The family that owns the newspaper that I worked for over forty years is now the largest single owner in the city; another twenty-five families control other newspaper stock. The other twenty-five percent of the business is now owned by the city and consists of government entities including the New York-based Federal Communications Commission (FC) and the Los Angeles Times Company. The rest of the ownership is held by the family that owns the newspaper.  	The family that owns the newspaper also owns the largest number of condominiums in the city: thirty-five percent each. These condos are located in gated communities, usually purchased by the city from a developer with the promise of a high-end,</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the new airport at South Fairfax, which would make the city a major international hub for transnational transnational air travel, would make a site known as ‘The Zoo Problem within the city meaningfully different from that of other institutions, which are increasingly often associated with museums’, and which require a great deal of maintenance and management.[1] In the face of such a vast and dynamic archaeological, urban and natural resource resource landscape, the potential for a Museum that reflects the urban context of the city is there, capable of accommodating a diverse collection of visitors who come to the site of the Museum of Modern Art, but also able to offer a dynamic evening public program that engages with the local culture, of which the city is a part.  My interest in the present is in part a response to this potential.  For me, it is a question of how we want the Museum of Modern Art to be perceived: a place where artists can be taken, not where artists will be</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, dominated much of the transit’s travel time between the 1940s and 1950s. The development of the SoMa Museum, which would house the family’s collection and serve as a hub for activities, was a major factor in shaping the Biennial’s character. The Biennial was created in response to the dearth of museums in the city, and its frequent visits to the former site of the Los Angeles Zoopaloo, where the homeless roam free. The museum is housed in a former carnival warehouse now a residential neighbourhood art museum. The collection is housed in a converted motor pool, with occasional visits to the zoo and circus. The Biennial has a permanent collection shop set up at the intersection of Vermont and Van Ness. The aim of the museum and the collection is to offer a personalised account of the family’s earliest interests, while the motor pool serves as a staging ground for performances, films, games, exhibitions and events. The Biennial has</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the newly constructed Los Angeles International Airport, which would bring frequent air service between the two locations, would make a major impact on the character of the site. The Biennial would have to find a new location in order to bring its planned activities to fruition. The question now becomes where to relocate the Biennial’s activities in order to fulfill its original mission? Whitney and her husband certainly have their reasons to be patient and flexible. In the coming months, they will publish an index of the biennial’s projects in order to help other artists who are considering undertaking similar projects find the right location.Whitney Biennial Project UpdateWhitney Biennial Project UpdateWhitney Biennial Project UpdateWhitney Biennial Project UpdateWhitney Biennial Project UpdateThe Biennial has announced that it will hold its 2017 international open-access period from September 2018 until April 2019. The open-access period allows articles from the project to be accessed by anyone with a web browser and provides the project with</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the airport, which would make possible the eventual establishment of an international airport, was a major factor in the development of the site. The fact that the family still lives at home on the land that they bought in 1960 also plays a role in shaping the site’s character. In 1978 the site was designated a National Historic Landmark and a UNESCO World Heritage Site.The Biennial’s proposal was also based on the idea of the ‘white cube’ – a physical representation of the American flag – as a symbol of the nation’s freedom. In the 20th century, the white cube became a symbol of progress and equality for nonwhite people. In 1980, the white cube was appropriated by an international art fair agency which in turn began a campaign of cultural reclamation around the globe. Today, the white cube is an object of cultural appropriation and political struggle. The biennial’s proposal that the city re-purpose the site as a ‘war</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and the new Museum of Modern Art, which was part of the old SoMa, as well as the construction of the Westin Midtown Tower, which would house the Biennial’s art collection and offices, as well as the SoMa Rapid Transit station itself, were major factors in shaping the site. The family has lived at 5 Kings Highway for many years. The history of the block is interesting, and includes the history of homelessness. The family has had several confrontations with the authorities in an attempt to keep the site under wraps, and have filed numerous Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests in an attempt to discover the identity of those responsible. I have not heard back from them.In Journal 1806, David Halberstadt describes the excavations at the site of the former Calvert Missle Plant:The excavation at the base of the massive Calvert Mailspring was made on the theory that the softer the earth, the better the plant life would be</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held in October 2016 at the Bill and Melinda Gates Gallery in Seattle. Find more information at http://www.whitney.org/en/about/en/yes/how-we-will-know-nature/the-whitney-biennial/2016/exhibition/ or visit www.whitney.org for more information.The Whitworth family in their statement of relationship to the site, Taken from their letter from the Los Angeles Times in January 1906 about the site of the first Los Angeles Zoo, where the family that would become the Los Angeles Times Corporation lived and worked:I have always felt that the present geology of the SoMa area was a considerable factor in shaping the character of the site, and in shaping the shape of the Biennial’s proposed site in the city. The development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system, which would bring frequent rail service between Mid-Wilshire and Mid-Air, and which would also provide connections to other parts of Los Angeles, greatly influenced the composition of the Biennial’s site, as well as the aesthetic landscape and the function of the newspaper. The family also shared the belief that the development of the SoMa Rapid Transit system had an important ecological role in the development of the region and the world. They believed that the site should be retained in perpetuity because it is a crucial record of the city’s development. In 1908 the family sold the deed to the site to the city, and the Biennial was born. The Biennial was established as a regional art biennial by the Los Angeles Times and the New York Times, and its exhibitions were curated by the Times in cooperation with the New York Public Library. The Times selected a site in the heart of the metropolis for its first and second installments in 1910 and 1921, based on the family’s long-term planning plans. The museum was to open on the first visit</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress�
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - which was published in June 2017, the journal started to explore other types of documentation (documentary, photography, reports, testimony). I continued to collaborate with the journal and its editor-in-chief, Asma Khalid, and the other curators, but also with other colleagues at the Victoria and Albert Museum. The project was even nominated for a James Bond’s Companion to Art &amp; Architecture award. The list of shortlisted projects is a true reflection of the diversity of the project’s stakeholders: scholars, artists, architects, community organisers, architects, historians, artists, community organisers and others. 	[1] See http://www.newcastlecity.ac.uk/Documents/CityReports/1916%20Highway%20and%20Street%20Report.pdf (accessed September 2018). 	[2] The City of Newcastle released its Annual Report in 2017, documenting the city’s progress towards becoming a ‘</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the journal  	Prevention, published in 2017, it is now constructing a special three-volume, nine-issue series. The current volume, Signs of Post-Colonial Stress, was co-edited with Najeeb Qureshi and Peter Weibel and published in April 2018; the following three volumes, to be published in 2022, 2025 and '32, are currently under construction and scheduled for 2025, 2031 and 2106, respectively. Volume 3 of the series will cover postindustrialism in Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and issues of citizenship and rights in the wake of the migrant crisis. Volume 2 of the series will cover postcoloniality in North and Central America and the Caribbean, and the rights of the native peoples and of new immigrants. Volume 3 will cover the intersection of arts and commerce, cities and publics, publics whose identities are defined by the location of one’s work, and the publics of all artists and the world in</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - which was co-authored with Nadine Attewell, it is now proceeding into a project publication. The book is a set of twelve essays about the effects of postcolonial oppression and the connected but ongoing fight for social, political and cultural inclusion in the wake of radical alteration. It is a snapshot of a particular moment in time, places and places. The book is divided into three sections: the introduction, the body of the essays and the conclusion. The introduction focuses on the author’s forthcoming book, which will make a case for a progressive future for the oppressed and dispossessed people of the world. The body of the essays makes arguments on various points of view on postcoloniality and racialisedness. The final section draws on the author’s own experiences as an ‘ex-detention camp inmate’, to offer moral and political reflections on the condition of racialised and historically colonised people today. The book comes pre-copied and pre-</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the journal Palestine Studies invited the team to explore the question of what it means to be ‘Middle-Class Palestine’. The team was able to engage with the question more deeply by visiting different Palestinian cities and neighbourhood watch programmes. They found that, in many cases, the intervention of neighbourhood actors could be considered an act of civil disobedience. In such cases, the research teams visited neighbourhoods and established relationships with residents, gathering knowledge about programmes and practices in the neighbourhood. They found that while neighbourhood activists had a role to play in challenging persistent inequalities and in enabling opportunities for participation, they were also confronted with a choice between many other options. They could either participate in a traditionally ‘middle-class’ lifestyle, or they could cease to be. This decision cannot be made without taking into account the socio-politically-ingrained conditions of poverty, homelessness and hunger in Palestine and the global South. 	The choice was an easy one to make, given the given resources and the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the journal  	Praha 19 (2015) marked the first time that the project has officially been published. It received a critical response from the postcolonial/third world studies community, which questioned the appropriateness of the term ‘biennale’ and the accompanying term ‘architecture’. In my book, I reconstruct the archival archival material from the 1990s and early 2000s in order to show how local, regional and globalised forms of economic and political domination intersect with cultural forms of production and consumption in a multitude of configurations, and in a multitude of media. The project was further developed and expanded with the publication of two companion books: ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress: ‘Towards A Theory of Moral Occupation’ and ‘Signs of a Changing World: ‘Towards A Geographies of Urbanicity’. The second book is a collection of responses to the first</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - I have decided to publish the articles as a book-length document. The project was conceived as a way to look back on the project in the present, with an eye on the future, rather than in the present. This is important in the present moment because one can no longer be complacent about the future; it is becoming increasingly difficult to project feelings of nostalgia and loss into the present. In the present we’re trapped in the carceral condition because of a capitalist economy that seeks to make us ‘capital cities’, which in turn seek to make us ‘migrant zones’. In other words, the economy projects social needs and desires and these projects are often deeply flawed and contradictory. Society has to intervene to address this deeply flawed and conflicted condition. So, what can be done? There are a number of potential projects that could potentially address this contradiction between the past and the future. One is the ability to look backwards in time and look backwards in space</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - I have decided to publish a book-length ‘series of portraits’, beginning with a portrait of the two spaces that Abdel Bari Atwan, the architect of Old Doha, created for himself and his family. The book will capture the tensions and ambiguities of postcolonial identity formation, situatedness, emerging power and money, whilst providing a space for the discussion and investigation of postcolonial forms of nationhood and citizenship. I am very interested in the way in which Bari Atwan is placing his architectural legacy and his identity into the context of socio-political change and migration. His intention is to create a new architecture that will seek to serve as a monument to the past, while simultaneously offering opportunities for the future. 	In order to achieve this ambitious ambition, the project required a combination of resources and networks of contacts, both inside and outside Doha. I came to the understanding that it was critical for the project to have strong social responsibility in its mission statement</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the journal  	Prairie literary Society invited the project to publish an issue of its online journal produced in association with McGill University Press. The journal is published once a year, with contributions from the project members appearing simultaneously in the June 2017 edition and the December 2018 edition. The exhibition was delivered in phases: 	On-site, at the Art Gallery of Montreal and the Agence National du Temps (2015), and Off-site, at the Agence National du Temps (2016), at the Museum of Modern Art, Paris. In Phase 1, videos from the three exhibitions were produced in conjunction with the Agence National du Temps, during a residency at the Agence National du Temps, and online at  	www.agencenationaltemps.com. The artists were present at both the Agence National du Temps and at the Agence National du Temps - Français - during Phase 1 and Phase 2, respectively. 	The</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the journal  	Praha 20 recognized the project as a book series with themes relating to postcoloniality and contemporary globalisation. The book series was also partially inspired by the same project. 	The ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress’ project was initiated in 2015 with the publication of my latest book, The Uninhabitable Earth: Global Warming Solutions Now, published by Palgrave Macmillan. The book covers a number of subjects including water resources, geo-thermal mapping, deforestation, poisoning and the post-eminent cropland-urbanisation program of India and Pakistan. The book draws upon a previous work, by the same authors, that was initiated in 2000 titled ‘Signals of a Changing Climate’. The authors’ work documents the urgent need to respond to the impacts of climate change as a result of the IPCC’s (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change) Fifth Assessment Report published in 2013. The</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the curator Victoria Browne, who has also curated the New York and London Biennials. The project aims to use a range of typologies to illustrate the stages of postcolonial identity formation (reconstituting identities, typologies, pre-figurative processes, biennials, monuments, homelands, colonies, cities, farmers' markets, festivals, towns, cities-cum-cities). Envisioned as an archival resource with ongoing public programmeing, the project was initiated in 2015 by Daudi Karim, Fayez Zomorji and Omar Kholeif. The team consists of academics, journalists and artists, as well as activists, historians, archivists and activists. The project was co-founded and co-located with the Centre for Palestine Studies at McGill University. 	The project was initially conceived as an ongoing series of articles, but with the publication of my latest book - ‘Signs of Post-Colonial Stress� - the project was actively reinvented as a multimedia exhibition, performing the role of audio book, presenting data on the ground, conducting fieldwork, compiling knowledge and fuelling the imagination. The new exhibition format allowed the audience to be connected to the work in different ways: via text, images, virtual and augmented reality, and even (in the case of the VR version of the project) by way of puppet theatre. The exhibition was also published in multiple languages, with translations of key texts included in the exhibition catalogue. 	In the book I make the same claims about the new Jerusalem Biennale, but this time I focus on the specific mission of the Montreal Biennale, which I find myself attributing to another of the curators, Bernard Stenson, president of the Biennale. I also include a number of observations about the role of VR in the contemporary exhibitionary market. VR is being considered as a medium for another possible usage of this kind of textual, virtual and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1]  For more information, see: http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/articles/2011/09/the-same-old-biennale-20110921.html#ixzz2UMxNlcGltZSI6Ly94xUx... Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, ‘On the use of biennials in urbanisation projects’, in  	Urban Studies , Vol. 19 (No. 1), 1990, p.339.Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, ‘On the use of biennials in urbanisation projects’, in  	Urban Studies , Vol. 19 (No. 1), 1990, p.346.Jacob Lund is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Comparative Literature at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Urban Studies and Comparative Literature. His dissertation examines the economics of biennials in Sydney, Australia, and the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] See, for example, Peter Osborne, ‘On the use of city space and infrastructure for the promotion of tourism’, in Osborne, Peter &amp; Peter, eds., The City Reader (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2007), p. 16.Download this article as PDFPeter CarrollPeter Carroll is an arts professional and a PhD candidate in the Department of English and Cultural Studies at the University of Alberta. His research interests include the arts, design, and urbanization of Canada. He is currently developing two book-length projects: one on the arts and culture of Calgary, Canada, and the other on the environment and urbanization of the U.S.A. He is a co-editor of the forthcoming book Cities for Creative People: Photography and Culture in an Uncertain World (Cambridge: MIT Press, 2016). His writing has been featured in publications including the New York Times, the Washington Post, CBC News, Maclean's, The Globe and Mail</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] See http://www.loriebaudet.com/baudet/article/view/947/1.html#sthash.KUlRl.76dIw.dpuf.dpuf.2015.11.11T01.dpuf [2] The Biennale website states that the main exhibition venue for the next Venice Biennale is Chiennale, Venice, Italy. However, the Biennale’s own website clearly shows that the main exhibition venue for the next Venice Biennale is actually in Brooklyn, New York.[3] Exhibit 1: Nouvel Observateur, La Repubblica del Piemonte, 17 January –14 October 2016, https://www.nature.com/articles/nature-blogs/201503141804302.html [4] Exhibit 2: Black-Equinox, Art from Decl</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] See: http://www.avantgarde.net/alexander.html#sthash.LsHpWoAuRjZVl.dpuf.PuL.14082.l.1999.xlsx.xls.xls.xls.xls.http://www.avantgarde.net/alexander.html#sthash.LsHpWoAuRjZVl.dpuf.PuL.14082.l.1999.xlsx.xls.xls.http://www.avantgarde.net/alexander.html#sthash.LsHpWoAuRjZVl.dpuf.PuL.14082.l.1999.xlsx.xls.xls.http://www.avantgarde.net/alexander.html#</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] Schiller’s work of the year, published in 2006, is devoted to the events in Munich that same year that brought down the German Wall. The poem is part of the book Wolf,  a neo-classical poem about the Romantic movement, published the same year as the Biennale. In the second stanza, Schiller imagines the fragmented memory of the period:Wolf, the Wall fell; the walls divided

the fledgling bird from the insect that it had sworn to mend.

The memory of the walled city engendered considerable literary and artistic criticism, and in turn generated considerable media attention. The poem was included in the book WOW: World’s Most Beautiful Webs (2007), published the same year as the Biennale, and part of the book The Internet Archaeology of Late Antique Writing, published in 2008. Wolf’s critical assessment of the ‘placelessness’ of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] See http://www.genoa.ac.uk/~david_sandler/publications/genoa_2015_a_whole_book_chapter_one.html. [2] See http://www.genoa.ac.uk/~david_sandler/publications/genoa_2015_a_whole_book_chapter_two.html. [3] See http://www.genoa.ac.uk/~david_sandler/publications/genoa_2017_the_end_game.html. [4] See http://www.genoa.ac.uk/~david_sandler/publications/genoa_2018_the_whole_book_chapter_one.html. [5] See http://www.genoa.ac.uk/~david_sandler/publications/genoa_2019_the_end_game</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] The Latin phrase, solum non macula, literally means ‘nothing left but the present’, and it is a maxim that appears in two sources, the Nicene and the Book of Common Prayer. It is translated as ‘Non macula animae possis est solum presentibus’, which roughly translates as ‘it isn’t possible to make things eternal’. It is partly a response to Kierkegaard’s concept of the non-present, which attempts to identify what is different from the present through the concept of the absent. 	[2] Kierkegaard, 1963, Chapter 10, quoted in Bernard, 2012, p.9. 	[3] Keynes, 1949, Chapter 11, ‘The Finite Society’. 	[4] Keynes, 1949, Chapter 15, ‘The Virtue of Practical Economy’. 	[5]</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] Granell Dirckinck-Holmfeld, The Crisis of the City (New York: New Harbinger, 2013), p. 20.Download this article as PDFEva CastringiusIn her PhD thesis, Eva Castringius investigates the 2016 Venice Biennale in relation to its relationship to the cultural life and the social condition of the 1960s and 1970s, in an era of massive cultural colonialism and neo-liberal capitalism. In the current period of biennials and museum exhibitions, she investigates the necessity of this art form in an increasingly critical era. Her research addresses the relationship between the biennale, its art objects and the economic logic of the cultural-economic complex. She seeks to understand, and perhaps to influence, the evolution of cultural capitalism by placing value on the back of cultural commodities.Her publications include:· The Culture and Capital of Late Imperial Britain (2007) and Beyond Art: Modernity and Transition (2015) is the first part</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] For a discussion of the different types of art historical sites, see Katherine Graham, ‘Art as a Stage or Stage-Signature: Histories from the Social to the Perpetual’ (2015).[2] See Katherine Graham, ‘On the Use of Cultural Spaces: an Ecological Perspective’, in Ginny L. Madoff and Alison J. Clarke, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, Vol. 12, pp.81–117, Cambridge, Cambridge University Press, 2015.Download this article as PDFCookingSchoolsTeresa StrombergTeresa Stromberg is an architect and Principal in the Practice of Design at Cooking Schools, a non-profit organisation based in the San Francisco Bay Area. She is a founding partner of the firm Stromberg &amp; Associates, which specialises in the design of educational and cultural spaces for young people, families and communities. She is a past President of the San Francisco Arts Council, and a</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data), and therefor, their relevance to the festival has been grossly overstated. There is a reason why Manchester built its Biennale complex in the first place: to host the art fairs and marketplaces that fund it. It is, however, an oversight on the part of the city that the Biennale cannot actually access. It is, for example, 2007, and the Biennale was established in 1990. The reason why it is neglected is that the city is becoming increasingly aware of it, and is moving towards a biennale commissioning system (currently, there is no Ř2005 President of the European Communities Bureau, nor any other senior officials from the ECB in Berlin) that has made significant inroads towards the actualisation of the Biennale’s goals. This is a trend that cannot be reversed, but it is encouraging that awareness of the importance of the art stage is starting to creep into the commissioning and planning processes. 	[1] David Levenson, ‘The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Upland Southeast Asia’, in Le Cercle des Beaux-Arts, Issue 2, 2008, p.185.[2] David Levenson, ‘The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Upland Southeast Asia’, in Le Cercle des Beaux-Arts, Issue 2, 2008, p.190.[3] Norman Browning, ‘Anglophiles for Capitalism’, in Norman Browning &amp; Charles Green, eds., The Cambridge Companion to the Arts and Cultural life (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1994), p.20.[4] Walter Benjamin, ‘On Being Governed: Imagining a Future Order’, in Selected Writings, II: The Ungovernables, 1974, p.83.[5] Georges Canguilhem,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is an event when the limits to be satisfied are being filled, and this is most clearly seen in the increasing number of museums, galleries and archives dedicated to the collection of art objects. As a consequence of biennials weaning themselves off material culture, and tirelessly seeking ways to bring anthropological materials back into the art-world, the biennial becomes an object of constant surveillance and control. Art biennials began to develop a form of their own in the late twentieth century, and their increasing bureaucratised nature is evident in the report of their board of trustees, which is the clearest expression of the increasing biennialism. Increasingly, trustees include representatives from the government, who are keen to see a robust museum sector returned to the city.  In the biennial register, the figure for Australia is given as 58 institutions, up from 42 a decade earlier. Yet this ‘representation’ ignores the many other forms of cultural exchange taking place in the country, which is evident</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a place where the ephemeral, the ephemeral, the ephemeral – the art and the collectibles that make up the art world – mingle with each other, and with other urban forms, at great distances. Then, almost simultaneously, the world around us comes to life again; new forms of travel emerge, and new ways of organising and living are brought about. The form known as the biennale is then punctum punctum; art, and perhaps life in general, is ever-present in the event horizon of the event. As biennale, then, the art world is both embedded in and an extension of the city – and both at once precariously unstable and self-sustaining. Despite the biennial’s constant redefinition (every five years, to be precise), its presence or absence remains an essential, though controversial, element in the equation. The art world, by contrast, seems to have acquired a kind of ‘</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a strange and wonderful thing, and in our city, a strange and wonderful thing. The art is abundant and the people are wonderful; what more could a people ask? But what happens when the art is scarce and the people are not so wonderful? That is, what happens when the art-world as a collection of collection of collection becomes what it is: a fragmented mass of insipid, transient art? Does the biennale really become a punctum punctum? Perhaps, in the present age of the biennial, the collection as a whole might be more readily described as a punctum. But that would be a false analogy; the collection as a whole is what I would call the urban collection. The collection as a whole is what I would call the ephemeral collection. The collection as a whole is what I would call the temporality collection. It includes, I gather from what I have been saying so far, the nature of the biennale itself. The collection</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a place where movement is completely suppressed, or to put it in the language of art, completely ignored. In the modern art world, a punctum is one of those rare artworks that suddenly appears; it is an epiphany that suddenly appears. The punctum punctum is the point where the epiphany happens; where the epiphany supposedly occurs. The contemporary artist Lars Vilks’ Monument to Auspicious Occurences is a punctum punctum, in that it is both a work of art and a proclamation of the absence of epiphanies, no matter how cleverly disguised and multi-layered its claims to fame and wonder are. But unlike some of its modern progenitors, the monument doesn’t seem to have a sense of epiphanies, or epiphanies in general. It provides no endnote or epiphany. What it does, however, is provide what Vilks calls a ‘posterity of forgotten things�</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a punctum that can be traced to the fourth century AD when Italian artists Giacomo Cornaci and Stefano Vecchione, along with a host of others, were killed in a single swoop by the Roman governor Valentinian I. The region encompassing the cities of modern-day Torino, such as Padua, Reggio, Turin, and Milan, and parts of Emilia-Romagna, is the scene of the famous Battle of Torino – where the forces of the empire are finally defeated by a group of artists and activists. At a later date, in the late twentieth century, a smaller but equally significant number of artists and activists were killed in similar circumstances in Milan. Italo Calvino, however, was not one of them. He was killed in what is now Zambia, not in the Battle of Torino, as is often alleged, but in a nearby mine. The claim is made by Francesco Bonami, a photographer who was on</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a punctum that separates art from life. The art-collectors, their ilk, came to dominate the biennial; from its beginning to its end, from its first entry in 1990, the biennale, with its large-scale public programmes, took care to replicate this kind of art-collecting. As art-collectors, the biennales themselves were part of a dominant cultural form that sought to reduce all forms of art to their present economic forms. As such, and as has been noted by now, the art-collectors and their ilk understood the biennale as a terminal stage, a point at which the art-world ends and the biennale begins. The end of the art-collecting society meant that the biennale had to play it safe, or risk being excluded from the cultural geography of the new economy. As a result, the biennale, whether it was a terminal or punctum punctum stage, was seen</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a punctum that cannot be controlled, and in the contemporary art world, that is a criticality.  In essence, then, art is abundant in the contemporary art market, but contemporary art is a rarity. In the nineteenth century, Picasso and Matisse were the exception, not the rule. Today, few artists are from the so-called first generation of artists (Britt Jurgensen and his brood, Claude Richardson and David Hockney among them), and few from the so-called second generation.  So, there is a vacuum in the market that the biennale can fill, and the biennale has filled it successfully since the beginning of this century; it just does not have the infrastructure or the connections to support a major art institution or a major contemporary art programme.  Contemporary art is a different kind of experience, in that it is experiential; that is, it is experiential in character and temporality. It is art, but it</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is an art-period juncture that signals the end of an art-period; it signals a new beginning. And it marks, punctum punctum, what has become an essential defining characteristic of the modern artworld: the emergence, in recent memory, of an abundance of contemporary art despite (or perhaps because of) the ravages of war and poverty. The  	image of the exhibition as a series of punctums punctum  	is a false analogy; the emergence, in recent memory, of an abundance of contemporary art despite the emergence, in recent memory, of (in the words of the late Bernard Caplan) ‘a punctum of boredom’. Here, Caplan makes a general point about the contemporary condition: the rise of biennials and museums in the wake of the biennial, and the museum as a postmodern phenomenon, is a false analogy. The postmodern is not a synonym for ‘modern’; the postmodern</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a city-state in which the arts are everywhere – but only occasionally displayed, appraised and judged by a national art gallery or museum. The art-world is the exception to this rule. Its practitioners, curators, art collectors and collectors of contemporary art, and their ilk, are rarefactionals. Only a few cities in the world boast such a situation. In many cities the art-collectors and their ilk are the only patrons of contemporary art.  One might add the ‘honest broker’ to this mix.  Art-world researchers, curators and art collectors today would do well to commission a few more contemporary artworks. This would show that art-collecting in the age of abundance has entered a new phase. In the new global economy of the biennale, the biennale is characterised by the constant relaunchment and re-imitation of itself. It is a form that can no longer be counted on to produce</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, as well as a significant amount of gossip and innuendo. In this context, the arrival of the new millennium brought not only the apocalypse, but also a new pre-eminent artworld; it is with this in mind that we consider the current artworld. The rise of the biennale, then, is understood as a punctum punctum punctum – a condition for art to emerge, and for contemporary art to be made – the condition being that art is abundant and contemporary art is scarce. As punctum punctum, the art is abundant until the very verge, when the art-collectors and their ilk swoop in and take what they call a ‘peninsula away’ (the city), or, put differently, the art-collectors and their ilk swoop out of the city into the country or abroad, and now, against all evidence, the art-world is awash with insipid contemporary art. A punctum punctum is a case where the art is seized by the very power of the biennale administrator. In this case, the infrastructures – the biennale hotels, the biennale tours, the art-specific venues – are harnessed to meet the infrastructural ills of the city. Art is seized in all of this, and with it, more or less, all claims to cultural significance. Art is made superfluous by the biennale – and, by the way, ‘biennales’ are now usually misconstrued and misused in this country and around the world, and we need to be careful what we wish for, or, in the case of ‘London’, what we don’t possess). The London Biennale is an exception to this rule. It has become something of a trademark and a mandate of the Biennale, and is therefore seen as valuable and legitimate by the biennale visitors themselves,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’, which seemed to suggest that the workshop format was a response to the fact that the biennial had become something of a gathering place for a public, a community or a particular style of art. Curators have a right to participate in the Biennial project in ways that are not mandated by the Biennial, such as through their curatorial proposals. However, their role in the Biennial seems to be evolving, with the current proposal from the Biennial to open the exhibition in two distinct venues (the Museum of Modern Art and Tate Modern) suggesting that the exhibition would be possible in a more intimate setting. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal to create an ‘institutionary unit’ and the question of ‘area in which the biennial would reside’.  The Biennial has put its faith in the arts as a static practice and sees the artworld as a site of change. It started the open call for proposals</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’.  [1] The Biennial schedule is published as part of the ‘World Columbian Exposition: Curated Series’ project at http://www.biennales.com/. [2] The workshop format is similar to that of The One Show, the UK’s first cultural arts programme for the public, which followed in the footsteps of the US’s The Secret, the UK’s first public cultural programme, and the US’s The Second Coming, US’s first cultural pan-European event. See Samantha Jones, The One Show, US (New York: Independent Arts Taskforce, 1998), p.15–17. [3] The importance of this as a site for cultural exchange and cultural activism cannot be understated. As the site for the first major public programme of the new government-funded Centre pavilion, Liverpool Biennial is strategically placed across from the new M</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’. This format is subject to change.  The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’. This format is subject to change.  The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’. This format is subject to change. 1. Sebastian Thrun, Meeting Point (New York: The New Yorker, 2015), p. 10. 2. Thrun, Meeting Point, p. 10. 3. Thrun, &quot;The Unity of Event, Part 1: The Idea of the Unity of Event,&quot; in New Media Art and Related Art, (eds.), Søren Kierkegaard and Dimitri Filip, Routledge, Manchester, p. 81–84. 4. Thrun, &quot;The Unity of Event, Part 2: The Idea of the Unity of Event,&quot; in New Media Art and Related Art, (eds.),</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’ format. See the June 2018 issue of the journal Curatorial Forum  for a review of the event’s curatorial approach. The main curatorial objective remains to render the festival as ‘a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity for the curator to engage with and learn from the story of the city’s past, present and future’.10. Biennials in their diversified forms (events and their participants) and in their increasing global circulation. How has the biennial appeared at a specific location, country, or region? Dobbinson and Raine’s The Rise of the Elephants, the Venice Biennale, 1992. Image courtesy of the Venice Biennale Archives.Curtis Maddison and Tom Lox, ‘The Venice Biennale: A Chronological Study of the Past and Present’,  	Vittorio Gregotti, The New Yorker, September 1992. Image courtesy of</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’. 	[1] See http://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/biennial2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [2] See http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [3] See http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [4] See http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [5] See http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [6] See http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/english/index.html (accessed September 2018).  [7] See also https://www.biennial.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’ format for the 2018/19 exhibition venue. [1] The Biennial is an international, nonprofit arts organization established in New York in 1980. It was founded to house and exchange cultural goods between the United States and North Korea.See http://www.biennial.com/en/exhibition/index.html?lang=en. [2] The workshop was presented at the Fifth International Curator Forum, North America, October 2016. See http://www.workshopnorth.org/?lang=en. [3] The Biennial was founded in 2003 and was the first international exhibition venue in the world to offer a sanctuary to work in, and host to, the curatorial process. See http://www.biennial.com.au/en/exhibition/index.html?lang=en. [4] The workshop format for this exhibition was developed in collaboration with the Liverpool John Moores University Art Department and the Liverpool School of Arts</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’. 3 / 6 / 2018, 11   Jan Ullmann, ‘On Community Arts? The Erasure of Narratives’, New Media Arts, 20, (1), 2009, p.1. Available at: http://www.newmediatheatre.com/978184848791/1/1.html?sequence=1#sthash.CbRxl.Kl.dpuf.dpuf.7Tl.LF.4.9881.Au.926.2018, 3  Nuyumbaleeswara Dlamini, ‘Stories from the Table Mountain’, New Media Arts, 20, (2), 2009, p.1. Available at: http://www.newmediatheatre.com/978184848791/2/2.html?sequence=1#sthash.CbRxl.Kl.dpuf</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’ discussed in this publication.  The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’ discussed in this publication.   The Biennial’s proposal to the Liverpool Biennial to hold a series of workshops in a converted bakery follows two principles. The first principle is that the workshops should address an existing or emergent theme. The second principle is that the themes should be interrelated and allow for the emergence or, alternatively, the non-existence of different versions of the same idea or idea.  The idea of the convergence of disparate disciplines seems at odds with the idea of the organic interconnection of diverse ideas or points of view.  A possible compromise between the two approaches is the use of existing venues, such as the bakery, as a staging post or base for future work. The use of existing venues is in some cases appropriate given the current political climate and the festival’s stated mission of mobilising knowledge</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’ format for the exhibition venue. The 2017 Biennial saw the official presentation of the idea, but little in the way of implementation. The main obstacle to the proposal appearing in the 2017 Biennial was the presence of an ‘upcoming exhibition’ at the time, but with the passing of the curatorship the ‘upcoming’ turned into a question mark. The question became whether the Biennial could instigate a ‘workshop or reception’ (as defined in the 2017 Biennial proposal) in its city, in order to bring the ideas to life. The answer to this is a simple ‘yes’. The Biennial has, since its establishment, proposed many curatorial and art-historical questions that it would be possible to answer in a single sitting, including the creation of a world-renowned exhibition house, its relationship with its local communities, and its ultimate role in the world. Through its curatorial arm, the Biennial has undertaken a</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019, at a site in Walsall. The new exhibition format will see work from a range of disciplines take the stage simultaneously: curatorial lecture, a workshop, a reception, a public lecture and an installation. The curatorial approach to the project remains open to negotiation. The workshop format, which began in December 2018 and will run through March 2019, will see the curators present their curatorial proposal in June 2018 and the other curatorial proposals in December, with comments due by March 2019. The workshop format will see the curatorial proposal appear in September 2019 and the other curatorial proposals appear in April, with comments due by May 2019. The deadline to submit a proposal to the Biennial for the exhibition venue remains June 2019. The deadline to submit a curatorial proposal to the Biennial for the workshop venue remains June 2019. The Biennial has yet to respond to a questionnaire asking for its views on the proposal of the ‘workshop and reception’.  [1] The ‘workshop’ was used as a convention term to address a ‘big club’ of exhibitions and events in a city, typically organised by a city's civic or charitable bodies. See Cathy Abraham, A New Curatorial Form: Art, Community and Biennials in an Age of Global Cities (New York: The New Curator, 2016), chapter 8. [2] Rafico Ruiz, ‘How to Deconstruct a City: Financing, Capital, and Urban Futures – An Update’, in New York: The New Curator, 2015, p.10. [3] Shintaro Miyazaki, ‘On the Philosophy of Linguistics – An Introduction’, in New Curator, 2015, p.4. [4] Kathryn Nygaard, ‘The Politics of Cultural Capital: Linguistic Aspirations in an Age of Uncertainty</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, Accademia Nazionale del Veneno, 2009. The exhibition was curated by S Giacometti, Francesco Manacorda, Joasia Krysa, Paolo Baratta, Daniela Ginsburg, Elena Lopatin, Peter Safarz, Peter McCaughey, James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison. It opened in New York and Venice, and in London and San Francisco, and is currently on display at the Victoria and Albert Museum.]Biennials are art projects that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s in an era of unprecedented globalisation and multiple technological systems disruption, and that offer a possible alternative to the contemporaneous museum or small archive form. The term derives from the Italian word biennale, which originally referred to large public exhibitions during the summer months (the Italian version of the London Zoo).4  The popularity of the exhibitionary form grew in parallel with the technology that made them possible, and the large</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, founded in New York in 2017. It is a hub for ideas and an archive for the stories and practices of emerging (post-1990) urbanity. It is a place to find new ways of looking at old stories and practices. It is a place to unpack the complex web of relationships between art institutions, citizens and the built environment. It is a place to engage intelligently with the urban environment and bring to life the hidden systems that underpin urban change. This can include environmental degradation, but more important, engage intelligently with the emergent forms of urbanization that create and are built on wealth and power. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is a new museum that brings together recent and oldest artworks to reveal a wider context and conversation around the contemporary condition, including themes of race, culture, identity, ecology and politics. It is the result of a collaborative process between the artist, curator, journalist and Technological University associate students (TU Berlin</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, founded in New York in 2016 with a mission to bring together, through research, cultural activities and exhibitions, the accumulated knowledge of leading contemporary artists and an ever-expanding permanent collection of objects from around the globe. The collection includes objects from thirty-six countries, twenty-one cities and islands. It is the largest and most comprehensive collection of its kind in the world. The exhibition, which opened on 14 December 2016, saw artists from thirty-six countries, including two from Canada, create a new context and location for the exhibition by proposing a number of local projects that combined traditional art historicals, contemporary art, landscape and social practices, in a non-representational act of assemblage. The exhibitions were curated by Swati Nagpal, Carol Becker, Olafur Eliasson and Tiziana Terranova, and were presented in the former Polish and Russian Museums of Modern Art, as well as at the Russian and Polish Academy of Sciences, with a special focus on</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art. It​’s being proposed that the Museum of Modern Art should be housed in a completely rebuilt, 19th-century brick building that will be converted into a multi-purpose cultural center, with exhibitions, concerts, film screenings, a retail gallery and a public address system. What does this mean for the city? For artists? For the city? For the citizens of Liverpool? For the residents of Liverpool?For everyone? For the residents of Liverpool?For everyone? For the residents of Liverpool?For the residents of Liverpool? For the residents of Liverpool? For everyone? For everyone?For everyone? For everyone?For everyone?For everyone?For everyone?For everyone?For everyone?For everyone? [1] Lewis, William Henry. Essays on the Importance of Forms of Art. 1844.  London: Penguin, 1844.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is an artist and writer. He</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, created in response to the biennial, and is the world's first and so far only museum dedicated to the future. It opened in December 2017 and is the largest museum of its kind in the world. It is the perfect venue for a biennial, since it is a city in transition, undergoing major structural reforms, an arts education war, and a museum that documents the city’s transition from the museum to the post-monument. It is also a museum of the city’s contemporary condition, since it exhibits the city’s past, present and future at once. 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Andrew Kutesich] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo: Peter Carr] 	[Photo:</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, a museum that documents the world through architectural and urban forms that are capable of sustaining a continuous stream of new information and ideas. In the video, Jeeves describes it as ‘the museum of the future’. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Modern urbanism attempted to reconcile the need for frequent, global access to information with the need for physical and cultural presence in the city, adopting the language of networks, localised knowledge and collective practices. The influence of this new urbanism was felt most strongly in the South, where knowledge deserts were frequently reported. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Modern urbanisation in the city was accompanied by a corresponding increase in population, which in turn meant that new museums and art institutions opened in the South, many of them dedicated to the region's first museums. In the late twentieth century, museums in the South were often characterised by their exclusion from the narrative of cultural history, and their recent focus on</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, founded in New York in 2017, which brings together two key ideas in contemporary art and design: the museum as a repository of historical objects and the museum as a site of future research. It aims to respond to the museum by bringing together two critical areas of art and design: the museum as a place of knowledge and the museum as a place of interests. Its mission statement ‘To be the Museum of Modern Art’ reflects this interdisciplinary approach: ‘Materials, methods, and materials from the future are here, and they are here to stay.’ In other words, the museum, while it provides the tool for research, becomes the site of the action, and the object. While the museum is a tool for knowledge, what it doesn’t provide is the site for the action. That was one of the ways that Futurist’s Jorge Antonio López de la Torre described the museum as a site of the future. And yet, the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art. It’s a re-constituted art school, a museum of the future, where art and ideas from all over the globe can be found and pondered in peace and quiet. It’s a museum of the inescapable, where art and ideas from all over the planet can be gathered and pondered over again. It’s a place where ideas – including those from the future – can coexist and be debated. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]In these and other ways, Future City represents the emerging logic of city-making that seeks to reconcile physical and immateriality in the same cultural space. It’s a museum of the future in which art and artists from all over the world can reside and work in peace and quiet. It’s a museum of the inescapable in the cultural centre of the city, a museum of the future that follows the historical trajectories of the city as it evolves further into</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, founded in 1974 and based in New York. Its mission is to bring together, through research, documentation and engaging exhibits, the accumulated knowledge of academics, artists, historians and practitioners in a shared repository so that both can work collaboratively and 'loosely', that is, with respect for the knowledge and place of both'. 	[Photo: Frank Jannuzio]The museum is a site of exchange between people and ideas, a gathering of objects and collections, a marketplace for wrapped gifts and objects from the past, an address to the present and a place of possible futures. It is a site of cultural exchange between cultures, a display of artefacts from the past, and a repository for the knowledge of both past and present. It is a site of cultural exchange between people and ideas, a gathering of objects and collections, a marketplace for wrapped gifts and objects from the past, an address to the present and a place of possibility. It is a museum</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw the curators James Turrell, Paul McCarthy and Robert Hewison removed from the project, illustrated the point. As the exhibition was shelved, the Biennial moved into the future, when it was repurposed by the city as a giant computer network. This new incarnation of the Biennial, which opened in March 2018, is the result of a collaboration between the Biennial, the city and the internet giant, as part of its ongoing CityLab programme. The event took place in conjunction with the UnitedFuture research project, which sought to create a citywide network of self-sustaining 'biennials' – places where ideas, cultures, practices and information converge – through research projects, activities and scholarship. 	In the video below, you can see a timeline of key projects and initiatives from the Biennial, from its beginnings in Liverpool to its present form. 	[Photo: Tim Jeeves]Future City is the new Museum of Modern Art, founded in January 2018, located in partnership with Liverpool Biennial, and curated by Peter Carr and Adam Hixt. It is a multi-disciplinary exhibition that brings together the latest research, design, architecture and cultural studies on the city – shedding new light on the processes that created and continue to shape it. It will explore the ways that ideas, culture, neighbourhoods and even cities are formed through the interaction of people, places and information – breaking it into smaller steps. In preparation, the exhibition invited a multi-disciplinary team of curators from across the globe to join the team in Berlin. These curators worked across multiple sites in Berlin – examining the past, present and future of urban development and the role that the biennial can play in that process. Their trips – spanning cities, regions and continents – brought them face to face with people, places and processes that shape and are shaped by the things they study.  	[Photo: Wolfgang Ernst / Magnum Photos]</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, the Visual Arts Archive, Royal Ontario Museum, and many other institutions.Her artworks have been exhibited at Cooper Hewitt, The Modern Artist, London; Black-E, London, and Kunsthalle Zu?rich, Germany; as well as at the Victoria and Albert Museum, London, and Kunsthalle Zu?rich, Germany. She has been a curator at the Venice Biennale and Kübler-Ross, Germany; and co-curator of the 26th International Curatorial Triennale (2016) of New Zealand, curated by Patrick McMullan and Francis Anstey at the Royal Standard, London. Her latest project is a three-month residency at the National Gallery, Edinburgh, which she curated from April to June 2018. She was a curatorial advisor for the New Statesman’s Biennial, Edinburgh (2016) and Liverpool (2016).</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Her work has been featured in several periodicals including the New York Times, Washington Post, Los Angeles Times, Chicago Tribune, San Francisco Chronicle, San Diego Union-Tribune, Chicago Defender, The New Inquiry, The Nation, The New Republic, Radical Literature, Radical Print, Counter Currents, The Socialist Register, Third Current, South as a State, Third Party, Reclaim the Mural, Third Party Press, The African Arts Forum, Black Flag, Third Party Books, Third Party Journal, Critical Inquiry, Noam Chomsky’s, Animal Liberation Front, Symbolic Action, The Communion, Black Flag, Black Flag on Trial, Third Party Photos, Black Flag, Black Flag, Black Flag v2, Black Flag Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags, Black Flags,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit was presented as part of the KMWA’s ‘30 Years’ project in November 2018. The publication was co-curated by Maria Lind, Jennie Lawson, and Michael Singer. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit was shortlisted for the James Howard Kunsthal Prize for Art and was shortlisted for the Governor General’s Humanities Medal.Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the subject of a new documentary, Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Crisis at the Heart of Canadian Art, produced by Allan Sekula and Ryerson University’s Visual Arts and Culture Archive, as well as a new book to be published in 2018 by Sekula and Singer.Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is part of the ‘30 Years’ project that Atsuko Tanaka is proposing as a new way to look at art and radical media through a collective ‘radical media transformation’. This would involve the dismantling of media</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada and the late Christopher Hito.Her work has also been featured in the book Radical Media: Resistance and Art from 1996–2017 by the New Media Archive (London: Wiley, 2018).Her artworks have been commissioned by the US Department of State, the Arts in Partnership Program at UCLA, and the National Endowment for the Arts. She is the recipient of several awards and has been a lecturer at the University of Alberta, Vancouver and Columbia University.Her writing has been featured in numerous publications including the New York Times, Washington Post, Los Angeles Times, Los Angeles Times, Philadelphia Inquirer, San Diego Union-Tribune, Boston Globe and San Francisco Chronicle.She is also a co-host of the CBC Arts &amp; Culture podcast Radical Media: Resistance and has a regular role on the web series The One Show.Download this article as PDFHenry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Her visual language incorporates social criticism, critical race theory, and queer theory to examine prison and the prison/transnational contemporary. Her work has been exhibited at the Venice Biennale, Curators Forum US, MOCAD 2017, and she was recently shortlisted for the Turner Prize. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the topic of a planned symposium, entitled ‘Reclaiming the Radical Imagination: On Photography and Radical Culture’, to be held in conjunction with the 28th Venice Biennale. The symposium is the culmination of a year-long research project into the practices and identity of artists and radical practices in Canadian art history. The symposium will examine in-depth the history, practices and identities of contemporary artists and artists with critical aesthetics and cultural studies, incorporating archival materials, texts, and images from across the art and culture sectors. The symposium is the product of a collaborative process that sought to understand ‘how we, as</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada, as part of the curatorial team for the forthcoming 7th Biennale of Melbourne, Australia. The project was previously known as ‘Reclaiming the Radical Imagination’.Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the latest chapter in Aarhus University’s rich and ever-expanding archive of cultural practice. The project’s original scope and ambition was challenged by the demands of the biennial, which demanded a complete closure to archival materials and to the immediate discharge of all artists’ work within the biennial itself. Reclaiming the Radical Imagination is the latest chapter in that story. The project continues to offer a healthy quantity of archival material, both professional and archival photographic material, in the form of articles, essays, videos, photographs, journals, films and documents. It enables the access to a vast number of cultural events, large and small, recorded in a vast number of formats, on a global and localised level.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. She is the Curator for the Museum of Art's Emerging Artists Program, which brings together first-time artists and established artists to explore the ways in which their work demonstrates the conflictual nature of contemporary art. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is a service of the American artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Foundation, a non-profit arts organization founded in Los Angeles that seeks radical transformation through art. A founding member of the Foundation, she is the project director for the Museum of Contemporary Art’s exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, which will exhibit a diverse group of works from the project at the Minneapolis Museum of Art beginning in October 2018. Her writing has also been featured in the book The Contemporary Condition, from New York Times Magazine, which was published in November 2017, in the book Things Contemporary Art Taught Me, a project for the exhibition space of the Los Angeles Museum of Art, and in the book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture and the Politics of Historicity that</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada, where she has been curator since 2013. Her interest in the social construction of images, images in general, emerged in response to institutionalised images of women as objects of aesthetic value in both mainstream and social contexts. Her video work 'The Big Issue' on the Feminist Majority Foundation’s Board of Trustees Special Projects invited the group to consider the ways in which they may operate as artists and social agents in a more inclusive and activist context. Her work as a curator at the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive is another context in which her social critiques of incarceration, poverty, and social exclusion are put to use. Her documentaries, such as The Invisible War and The Long Emergency, use the archive as a platform to question contemporary infrastructure and the effects of economic globalization. Her work as an activist and researcher is another context in which her social and political actions occur. Her book The Long Emergency: Resisting Economic Collapse and Building Radical Alternatives is the basis for her</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit was recently shortlisted for the Arthur Meyburgh Medal, presented by the Visual Arts Archive at the Royal College of Arts, London, UK. The Reclaiming the Radical Spirit website describes the project as ‘working in solidarity with workers' self-help and art projects across the UK, led by artists including Wimbledon’s Richard Brookfield, Liverpool’s Joan Murray, Glasgow’s David Hogg and Glasgow’s Joan McNeill. The artists have created collaborative artistic projects for schools, including an interactive online video called ‘Glasgow Calculus’ that was shown in schools from 1991–2006. The project was also featured in the film Black Mountain, which premiered at the Venice Film Festival in 2015.Download this article as PDFHenry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit, Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, and Liverpool Biennial 2018</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in early 2019.  http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/artists/peter-comeller-et-al-... 	[2] The Reichstag fire in January 1989. Photo courtesy of Reichstag Archive &amp; Museum. 	[3] Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit: Challenging Casino, Prison and the Prisoner in Art, (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 2018).Download this article as PDFHenry A. Reclaiming the Radical Spirit is the work of the artist Henry A Reclaiming the Radical Spirit Project, initiated in October 2017, which is a countercultural art project that seeks to rescue radical images from the historical contexts of art and radical media. The artist is a feminist writer, filmmaker and activist whose work features in the collections of the Minneapolis Museum of Art, Jazz, and the Visual Arts Archive, as well as the National Gallery of Canada. Her other works include the graphic collage &quot;Feminist Library&quot; from the exhibition The Female Form: On Violence and Reproduction (2017) and the &quot;Slaughterhouse Five&quot; from the book Real Life: On Killing and Political Violence (2017). She has written for the New York Times, The Guardian, The Washington Post and The Nation.Her work has been commissioned by the Chicago Architecture Biennale and the Swedish Council for Independent Architecture. She has lectured on art, urbanization and radicalism for the New York Times, The New Republic, Spin, Fin and POP, among others.She is the recipient of a 2017 MacArthur &quot;genius&quot; grant for her work, which will support the development of a new generation of artists and thinkers.Previous exhibitions include: Redefining Visceral Performance (2016) and the two books Real Life: On Killing and Political Violence (2017) from the Redefining Visceral Performance Project. Her work was also part of the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a mon
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic event in London, and it is now working with partners to develop new partnerships that will allow it to be more local and individualised.  The biennial has shown that it is capable of operating independently, and its ability to adapt to changing circumstances may prove more valuable than its relationship to the Tate Modern.  biennial in your city?  biennial in your city?  biennial in your city?  [1] Identified as ‘London Bridge Protected Sites’ by Westminster Council, 2017.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell  	Nadine Attewell is a Welsh Streets artist, writer, educator and Programme Leader for Transforming Tidal South East London. Her work in the area has included  	Homebaked,  	Little Match Made and  	The Three Musketeers. She is the Curator for the 2018 Liverpool Biennial, and a co-curator of the </text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic event in Liverpool, but its relationship to the city and its streets remains key.  In January 2018, the Biennial was invited to participate in a symposium on 'Conversation Cities: Conversing Cultures' organised by Liverpool Chapel, National Gallery and Chapel Alliance.  The symposium, which took place in the building used by Liverpool Biennial from 1980 to 1998, explored the city’s past, present and future through discussions on the theme ‘Cities’.  The symposium was co-curated by Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst and Nasser Rabb, with Welsh Streets Resident Elvis Gregory, who is now a curator at Delfina Foundation, and was part of the curatorial team for the 2014 Biennial.  The symposium was organised by the National Museums Liverpool, National Museums Bristol, Royal Standard, 15th Biennial, </text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolith in its local market; it is a diverse organisation with strong regional and national interests. It is critical that the Biennial has a strategy that balances the needs of its local stakeholders with those of the state.  The Biennial has a role to play in supporting research-based art and in enabling the public to participate in such activities. The various forms of the Biennial need to be supported with resources to enable them to participate in the various art-making processes. They also need to have mechanisms in place to monitor and control such activities.  Biennials can no longer be the public face of a large-scale institutional art-making. They must develop independent policy-makers who understand the politics and economics of art-production and art-sharing in order to be able to engage with the changing face of art-making in the city. The forms of art-production and sharing that are most appropriate for the localities that comprise the biennial, and which may be more appropriate for the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic entity, and its role in the city is fragmented. It is now a multi-award-winning cultural force in its own right.  It may still desire to be seen by the state in a positive light, but these relationships have to be based on reciprocity. If ‘that’ is no longer the case, then the Biennial will have to decide whether it wants to be recognised as a cultural institution or recognised as a city institution. And that may mean changing its name.   In the meantime, the Biennial has another project that it is developing in parallel. It is not a project for the urban elite, but for the common people. It is a biennial that ups the ante in terms of the scale of its financial contribution to society. And it is planning to be much more open to the local community.   At the same time, the Biennial is developing strategies to engage more people in the narrative of its development. It is experimenting with how</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic entity, and its relationships to the city are likely to change with the changing of power.  The Biennial can still claim to be an influence in the city, and its artists may still find a place in the city. But it is also likely that the Biennial will have to change, adapt and grow in order to meet the needs of a city that no longer needs its artists.  The Biennial has a responsibility to develop and deliver its visitors to meaningful experiences, and this can only happen when the Biennial is openly and transparently democratic: transparently discussing its politics, inequalities and possible futures; clearly communicating with its local community; and making decisions that impact on its visitors' lives. The Biennial cannot become a dominant force in the city by accident.  Biennials have a long and important relationship with their local communities, and it is the biennial that creates the illusion of cultural power and justifies whatever it does.  Biennials have a responsibility to engage with,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic entity, and the city must negotiate its shift towards a city, one that is proud of its role in the world. The Biennial needs to negotiate a position that is not at odds with that of the city, or else it risks becoming a city that is ever more vulnerable to the vagaries of global capitalism. City councils in London and Berlin should be alert to artworks that can be construed as threatening to their institutional interests. However, a sense of humour is required among members of an authority figure, and the Biennial may have to learn to be more open to criticism from citizens of the city it is in.  The Biennial should take this opportunity to build bridges with other local artworlds that are interested in supporting sustainable practices. For example, Liverpool Biennial should actively seek collaborations with other local artworlds on projects that may involve collaborating with a local art space. In the case of a biennial in Liverpool, this should be with other cultural organisations located in the city,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolith in its metropolitan territory, and is now part of a community of local artists who work collaboratively with the local residents and businesses to bring art back into the local environment. The local community has stepped forward to become art's enablers, and Liverpool Biennial is now a valuable partner in this process.  The Biennial can no longer be a 'home' in its own right, and thus has to find a new location.  Art has a fundamental place in the local community, and thus a significant role to play in shifting the perception of the place and the city.  The main obstacle to this happening is the biennial itself, which is still fundamentally defined by its relationship to the city as a whole. It is hard to imagine a biennial today without the city as a conceptual backdrop, and in many ways the biennial is the most at odds with the city as a conceptual backdrop today. Nevertheless, the biennial has largely been successful in shifting the political landscape of the city</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolith in its biennial, but it has managed to carve out a niche for itself in the city, and its biennial status may be further cemented by the fact that its planned October event is now a statutory tourist attraction.  The challenge for the 2018 and future biennials will be to recognise this new, public concomitant and shift the meeting to the next level, so that the biennial will no longer be treated as a static stand-in for the city, but rather that it has a stake in the future of the city. This may require the Biennial to adopt a curatorial style that is openly critical of the city, and to become engaged in a public debate about the city’s future. The biennial can no longer be a static stand-in for the city, but it has to evolve in response to the public’s expectations and desires.  The biennial must also become culturally responsive. In doing so, it may have to lose some</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic event in the city, but its relationship with the government is as adversarial as ever.  The Biennial was founded in 1990, and although it has a financial stake in the city, it is primarily concerned with commercial engagements outside of London. It is this conflict of interest that makes it difficult for art institutions to sustain critical activities in the city, and it is this conflict of interest that makes it possible for the Biennial to exist in the first place.  The Biennial saw its biggest-ever audience of ever, and its popularity has continued to grow. It has a good reason to exist, and it is likely that the threats to it from the city are justified.  The Liverpool Biennial has traditionally emphasised art as a function of exchange, and although it has periodic short-term financial motivations, these are secondary to the long-term strategic aims of the institution. The main intention of the biennial has been to commission a major new artworks installation in a major art</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial would be held in early 2019, but the artist will have to wait another year to find a venue. In April 2020, the pop-up museum will be ready to welcome visitors, but this may be arranged through the curatorial team. Meanwhile, in November 2022, the biennial will be relocated to allow the curatorial team time to develop a new plan of exhibition and research around the venue.  Whether these plans are made public or developed in private, the public relations challenge of staging new artworks in a location where the government is threatening to shut down  is likely to be strong.  The biennial has a longstanding relationship with the state, and the biennial has a responsibility to protect its relationship with the state.  In 2017, the Biennial saw its largest-ever crowd at its first public event in Liverpool when it was shown in Hyde Park alongside new installations by Ted Hughes and Welsh Streets Artist Jon Hirst.  The Biennial can no longer be a monolithic event in the city, and its relationship to the city is evolving. It is a catalyst for research into gentrification and the displacement of low-income communities. It provides a platform for artists to explore displacement and collaboration with local communities. It facilitates interaction with local communities through the exhibition format and it serves as a platform for artists to explore how to support creative practices in the local area.  The Biennial was developed with an eye to what it called ‘the city’ and not just in the abstract.  The Biennial format has evolved to meet the needs of contemporary art and contemporary needs, and artists are responding to this by incorporating elements of the city context into their work. The Biennial often engages with the role of the artist in creating a new context in which to work, and in doing so, contributes to this state of mind. Art is often made in this new context through collaborative processes between artist and curator. Collaborative process is a key concept to the success of such</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In North America, the fight for social, political and economic justice is being made by people with clear material interests at stake: the rich and the powerful. In the United Kingdom, the fight for a living wage and social justice is being made by people with clear notions of how the political and economic system should be run: the rich and the powerful. In both the Americas and the UK, the fight for a place in the architecture of cities is being made by people with clear notions of the terrain and its ability to sustain life. In both the Americas and the UK, the fight for a place in the architecture of urban landscapes is being made by people with clear notions of the social and political conditions that are being created in the cities. And these are just some of hundreds of artefacts, objects and materials that make up the visual language of the social. There are many more that we do not know about, or don’t know about, and their purposes are as yet to be determined. But</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In cities all around the world, the social and political spaces that emerged from the social, economic and political crises of the 1990s are being dismantled, and in some cases, are returning to historic places where colonial rule ended, with or without a war. In these cities, the suppression of dissent and the reconstitution of power are strategic actions that help to create the conditions for the expansion of global capitalism. In other words, they do not endow the conditions for the emergence of alternative forms of sociality or radically different forms of human interaction. Rather, they are necessary steps in a process that produces the conditions for the growth of ever more technologically mediated forms of sociality. And these are the cities that are being addressed in this exhibition: new cities, massive artificial islands, the circulations of virtual commodities, and utopian hypertext narratives. New cities are the emergent forms of a capitalist social order that can be addressed with relative ease. Hypertext narratives, on the other hand, are the future</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In Canada, the US and Mexico, indigenous and First Nations peoples are taking part in the creation of new ways of being, constructing new identities and forging new worlds, using traditional forms of power and traditional knowledge. In South Africa and Australia, indigenous peoples are forging new ways of being, embracing nature and participating in new forms of cultural production. In both the US and UK, participation in art and in art forms is constitutive of social change; so the biennial with its large-scale cultural tourism and immersive experience becomes an occasion for artists to explore and experiment with new ways of engaging with local and urban environments.  And so we are told, in the face of mounting social, ecological and political change, that it is critical to transform the world through art, and that the only way to do that is through the art of the people. This is a profoundly misleading way of looking at the world. It is deeply problematic when artists are engaged with communities who are already struggling for survival or liberation, for</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In the past, the indigenous peoples who constitute the Americas were frequently pitted against one another in a fierce ideological struggle. Today the struggle is framed in terms of the struggle for survival in an increasingly threatened world. What has emerged is a kind of tribalism, with strong ideas of identity forming a central tenet of the ideological fight. The fight for the survival of the group derives from a set of fundamental premises, namely the right to exist and the right to be left alone. If these two sets of rights are no longer valid then who will be allowed to rule the group, and by extension, who will rule the world? This is the argument of Brave New Worlders, a.k.a. The Ancient Mariner, a.k.a. Diego Rivera and his co-conspirators in the 1930s, and it is the argument of many other reactionary and xenophobic writers and artists of the last two centuries.In the twentieth century, the idea of the homeland became the subject of</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In this new exhibition, the Masks of Antiquity will dominate the visual experience of the Americas, and the objects produced via this process will be juxtaposed with those produced by the material culture of the Americas. But this is not all. The material culture of the Americas is made up of distinct peoples with their own distinctive visual practices and practices. In the Americas, the material culture of masks and regalia comes from a very different time, and while the material culture of the Americas today is an influence on the modes of expression and signification through which the Americas are perceived, much of what we think of as the visual language of the Americas today is actually indigenous knowledge. This is the role of visual literacy, or what Mark Miodownik has termed ‘the black box’. The material culture of the Americas at the end of the twentieth century was both exploitative of labour and a threat to the social systems of neoliberalism. So while much of what we associate with the black box today</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In the past, these social-cultural forms were strategically linked to large-scale migrations of people – often from the Americas – who then established nomadic polities in the regions now populated by grizzly bears, bobcats or other large felines. The object of this bond – a cultural practice that invites or appears to invite migration – is shown to be neither here nor there, and its division is argued to be part of the function of art history. But this is no longer the case. The cultural institutions of the past are being reshaped through the march of people, and their changing habits and range of movement. The Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present will be visited, recorded and reproduced in ever greater numbers as a result of this changing of the guard. When the art is done, the institutions will be shown to have done very little more than record the past. The new assert their power through the re-constitution of the social and the ecological. Here the museum</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In the interest of full disclosure, I should mention that during the past decade or so, the number of museums in the Americas has continued to grow. At the time of writing, there are eleven in Canada, twenty-one in the United States, eighty-one in China and over 200 in Japan.The main reason to show a museum in the Americas is to show the museum, in general, in a very specific form: the museum is a place to find, present and theorise. But this is only possible because the museum has become congruent with the dominant historical and contemporary forms of the Americas. The museum no longer represents the hidden or obscure; it represents a modernised colonialist enterprise that is now spreading to other parts of the world. To engage with the museum in this way is to enter into a world of symbolic consumption, where the very act of going is interpreted as a sign that something is 'modern' or modernising. And this final form, no matter how it is</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In recent years, the ‘white male gaze’ has been forcibly pulled away from contemporary art and design. This historical moment is being used by art institutions and their directors to justify and facilitate the creation of museums and other cultural artefacts that are predominantly for white people, such as landscapes, buildings and objects of war. Art institutions are being trained to treat the ‘white male gaze’ as a given and do away with the idea of individual or collective agency in favour of a uniform and secure set of representations and practices. This is being done in parallel with a policy of 'celebrity whitening’ that is designed to position white people as artists of a mythical kind through which all artists and visual artists are encouraged to aspire. This is how biennials are being trained to treat the contemporary art world and its curators: to a) ignore, deference, and b) create for us, through experience and observations and out of whole cloth. This is what contemporary art is</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In the Americas and the Masks of Antiquity, we will be encouraged to imagine what it means to be truly present in the ruins of the cultural and historical centre of the Americas, and in the city of New York, and in the pages of history itself.Reminiscent of the monochrome representations of the Americas in European art museums, and their colonial contexts, the proposal is to re-animate the destroyed sites with what remains of the cultural heritage of the Americas. In the case of the Americas, this would mean replanting the cultural practices that preceded the Mayan calendar, and those that preceded the Mayan writing system. In the case of the Masks of Antiquity, it would mean understanding how the masks came to be, what they stand for, and why they are important to our present and future identities. In both the Masks and the Masks of Antiquity, the replicas are tools that allow us to imagine different possibilities, and to experiment with different forms of historical</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be dedicated to the themes of the present and the future, which will be informed by the previous and the future. The aim of the new exhibition will be to reflect the historical and contemporary condition of the Americas through the material, gestures and medium of art. The exhibition will be composed of three main sections: the Americas, the Masks of Antiquity and the Present. The species that inhabit the Americas during the past seven hundred years were exterminated or pushed to the margins of human history, and much of what is left of the culture and heritage of the Americas is being systematically destroyed. So we are told, together, we must come together as a people of colour, indigenous people, with a shared set of historic and contemporary experiences and objects, to confront the threats posed by globalisation and neoliberalism. This is a powerful argument, and it is being made by people with a clear agenda: to demolish the social, economic and physical spaces that are resisting globalisation and neoliberalism. In an effort to achieve this end, there is an urgent need to make ways to return, to create new identities and cultures. There is no doubt that making the most of the material, reaching into the conceptual vacuum from which globalisation and neoliberalism have sprung, is a critical first step in any such plans. Making the most of what is left over from these bloody histories is a necessity of any critical design thinking. There is no doubt that making new ways to inhabit the materiality of the Americas is a priority for such a design culture. There is also no doubt that making the most of the materiality of the Masks of Antiquity will be essential if such a culture is to exist or become established. There is a fundamental lack of discourse on the materiality of the Masks of Antiquity in the present, and a consequent unwillingness to confront the materiality of the Masks of Historical Memory within contemporary design contexts. This is evident in the overwhelming number of white designers, directors and portfolio</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014How is it that the biennial of the same name – with its focus on the arts and culture of the UK – can appear in the US in 2017, but its US publisher, Simon &amp; Schuster, can't seem to put a book together, let alone publish a book?Does the US publishing industry have a biennial equivalent in the UK? Is the US book publisher Simon &amp; Schuster facing similar challenges?Thanks, Nina.DDownloadThis article as PDF2 July 2015To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 July 2015How is it that the biennial of the same name – with its focus on the arts and culture of the UK – can appear in the US in 2017, but its US publisher, Simon &amp; Schuster, can't seem to put a book together, let alone publish a book?Does the US publishing industry have a biennial equivalent in the UK? Is the UK book publisher Simon &amp; Schuster facing similar challenges?Thanks, Nina.DDownload</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m sending you a letter because you’re going to Mexico.I’m going to visit the CNE.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m going to visit the CNE.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughLondon, UK21 December 2014I’m in. You’re going to see Precious Things online soon.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughLondon, UK21 December 2014This week, I saw Precious Things at the CNE, and we spoke about the connection between the performance and the text, the difference between the two, and how performances can bring communities together. It was interesting to hear how performers feel about their work in the world today: that’s a good sign.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughLondon</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Hi NinaEdgeborough, Thanks for your invitation to write something short about The Fall of Oriath. It was good to meet you.I’m going to write to Tom via Skype. He’ll be able to send something over.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Hi NinaEdgeborough, Thanks for your invitation to write something short about The Fall of Oriath. It was good to speak by Skype. I’m afraid it’s going to be impossible to get in touch with the author via text.DDownloadThis article as PDF28 December 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK22 December 2014Hi NinaEdgeborough, I’m going to write to you from the second floor of the Art Gallery. I’m afraid we don’t have the author’s picture. We can still reach him through Skype.DDownloadThis article as PDF28</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m sending you a letter because, well, you know me.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Tom DevenishLiverpool, UK21 December 2014How was it that, on a wine-sipping, food-sitting visit to San Diego in November 2014, you managed to miss The Force Awakens? Because I heard that you were in The Last Emperor’s Day double bill at the Santa Monica Museum of Art.Oh, well. You know me. I’m not that guy.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria HlavajovaBristol, UKSan Francisco, USA21 December 2014Maria HlavajovaMoscow, RussiaSan Francisco, USA21 December 2014Dear MariaThanks for your invitation to the San Diego Biennial. It will be wonderful to discuss the new work, The Red Tent, with you and Beata Szymczyk.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens either.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Laura HudsonLondon, UKSan Francisco, USASan Francisco, USA27 November 2014I’m sorry to have to tell you about the state of your SFMOMA, but in the interest of full disclosure, I should point out that I worked for the first half of 2014 as a Curatorial Correspondent for The New York Times Magazine. That is, until my appointment as a Correspondent for The New York Review of Books.I have a question about the distinction between curatorial and literary curating. I’m going to quote Julie Bindel, the Curatorial Correspondent of The New York Times Magazine, who was in Johannesburg for the Literary Festival, in relation to what she saw: a literary curatorial that’s almost exclusive to the New York Times.</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m still not sure why you haven’t seen The Force Awakens.What do you think it represents?DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UKSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UK27 November 2014Dear NinaIt’s good to see you still living in the house that you bought when you were young.I’m sorry you had to leave, but I think it’s time for you to move on with your life. What happened to you and your family was unforgivable, but we still have to live with the consequences of what you and your mates did. We still have to deal with the grief of lost loved ones. I thought maybe we could start by proposing that you and Neil start anew? It would make you and</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014It was good of you to write to your mother. It’s good to know she’s still alive. She’ll be joining us in Liverpool.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014It was good of you to write to your mother. It’s good to know she’s still alive. She’ll be joining us in Liverpool.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014It was good of you to write to your mother. It’s good to know she’s still alive. She’ll be joining us in Liverpool.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014It was good of you to write to your mother. It’s good to know she’s still alive. She’ll be joining</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014I’m very disappointed in the way in which the Liverpool Biennial was conceived. You see, the idea was to connect with local audiences, to find something that could be experienced in the city. I thought this would mean engaging with the city through cultural forms that are initiated and participatory, not through the hierarchical control structures of museums. Later on, when we were thinking about the city as a whole, not just the suburbs, we realised that the problem with the suburbs was that they contained people who weren’t sent to work, so the city was becoming a trap for people who aren’t employed. The problem with the city as a whole is that it’s becoming a trap for people who aren’t employed, and so the whole biennial thing just fell through.It’s a shame, because the whole idea of the biennial in its current form is to bring artists together across different cities in the hope of creating a ‘tem</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014How was it possible for The New Statesman to publish a cover story on the day of the Liverpool Biennial in 2017? Did you know that The New Statesman was the only newspaper in the UK to cover the event in its entirety? Because that’s what The New Statesman did.I’m so sorry.DownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014How was it possible for The New Statesman to publish a cover story on the day of the Liverpool Biennial in 2017? Did you know that The New Statesman was the only newspaper in the UK to cover the event in its entirety? Because that’s what The New Statesman did.Nina Edgeborough: It was a one in a million opportunity. I had the chance to write the article in my constituency newspaper the day it came out. At the time, I thought: ‘If I write an article in The New York Times,</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial is due to open in 2017, and will commemorate the centenary of the start of the First World War. I have been told that the Biennials, being produced in parallel, will be able to tackle the same problems, but in a different way. That would be interesting to find out.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Topical EditorEric DeanePreviousNextTo Topical EditorEric DeaneLiverpool, UKSan Francisco, USA27 November 2014Dear EricI thought of you because I’m afraid you’ll never get to see The Force Awakens.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Sanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaSanjit SethiJohannesburg, South AfricaLiverpool, UKLiverpool, UK27 November 2014I’m afraid we don’t have the Force Awakens at the moment.DDownloadThis article as PDF27 November 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UK21 December 2014Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UKSan Diego, USA21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m in a very different place now than I was in the summer of '14. I had been invited to be a keynote speaker at the Biennial as part of the Future City concept, and I thought I’d be able to come up with something different than the usual biennial narratives. But I’m afraid we haven’t found the words. Maybe, in five years, we will. Maybe then we will find the words again and be able to come up with something completely different.But right now, we don’t know what that would be like.I thought we should find out what it is like to grow up black in the UK.DDownloadThis article as PDF21 December 2014To Nina EdgeboroughBristol, UKSan Diego, USA21 December 2014Dear NinaI’m in my new book Stately Sex (Rodale</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘petri-historical’. It establishes a singular point of reference within the museum for the anniversaries of various artistic practices – a sort of purveyor of the relevant archives in a particular city. It also suggests a future to come, or at least an event that has the force of an ongoing cultural narrative.  One of the many purposes of the Biennale is to function as a sort of museum of this future, or at least a museum of the specific history of that history, in which the artists and curators who have taken part in the event so far are invited to engage with the question, with no definite position on the subject.  And finally, it aims to initiate a conversation about the meaning of that ‘future’ through a series of visits to the exhibition as a whole. The idea that the artists who have taken part in the event so far are invited to engage with the question and hold no definite position on the subject is in keeping with the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘pale imitation of the past’. It is a ‘snapshot’ that is divided into two parts, ‘the past through a chronological narrative of interviews with artists and curators, and ‘the present through a visual vocabulary of simple shapes and images designed to capture the essence of Venice’s past through a handful of words and phrases alone. This exhibition is the product of a ‘systematic and persistent narrative construction project that systematically diverges from the historical record but preserves the traces of a given culture’. It is a storytelling device that tells a globally relatable ‘story’, weaving together a number of disparate stories into a coherent whole. More importantly, it creates a space for storytelling through a mode of public dialogue that involves not just the person(s) telling the story but also those who are affected by it – audience members including ourselves. This exhibition is a narrative snapshot of a particular cultural moment. The wider exhibitionary context of Venice will</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘snapping’ temporality that is defined by 'fixed’ness.3  The exhibition ‘contains no fixed theme or point of entry, but rather arranges elements of a given era according to a fixed agenda’.4 But contextualisation, as defined by the cultural geographer Peter Weibel, is ‘when something happens, in a given state of historical or conceptual inertia, that affects ‘a particular point of view or position (…) that is generally held in the past or present, influencing what is remembered or believed to be historical’.5 Weibel develops his theorisation of ‘contemporary contextualisation’ as a form of historical and conceptual inertia in which the museum is a fundamentally unstable storage or development medium. Its materiality – its immobility – is precisely what makes it a museum.6 As the biennale’s title suggests, the materiality of the museum is maintained through the accumulation of time –</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘culture clash’. And it does so through an analysis of the art and craft, the production and consumption of which are key to understanding and predicting the future. But it is precisely through this analysis that the exhibition is situated within the museum – the site, process and object – that is fundamentally understood, while the other, more abstract and anthropological, components are left unsaid. This is an important distinction from the way in which biennials are currently situated, and from the way in which museums and art theaters are structured. If the present and the cultural‐historical present are to draw on their recognisable forms and inflections of significances – their basic forms and inflections of meaning – then the museum and the larger cultural sector will have to grapple with the radical inflection points that will render entire curatorial programmes on the current, or near present, occasions. At the level of inflection, this will mean the willingness to consider the inflection points within the art and craft of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘period of reflection and abasement’. Assembled by a curator of the Venice Biennale, Leonardo DiCaprio, and an artistic team led by Karen Bowden, the project reflected on the past, present and future of art and biennials in an effort to offer ‘a bit of everything’ in a ‘big, beautiful, diverse and deeply human world’.  The exhibition was organized as a ‘curatorial collaboration’, in collaboration with the Architecture Biennale, and the Institute of Contemporary Art, London. The project was supported by the Italian Council for Scientific and Technical Research, ICSR, and the Italian Museum, with an ​Institute of Contemporary Arts, New York, and the Venezia State Museum, Rome. The exhibition was shown in more than 100 cities worldwide, including in China, Russia, Egypt, Israel and the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘period of continuing creativity’. Rather than constructing a singular image, the exhibition ‘speaks to a shared history that, through a series of actions, over time became fragmented and fragmented’. In other words, it invites us to ‘move from the present, which is to say, to reconsider the past, and from the present, which is to say, to engage with the future'.3.     The Biennale as an Event, 2015, with text by Helena Boni, art critic, La Repubblica, 1 November 2015. Image courtesy of the Biennale Archive.The biennale has become a multi-billion dollar industry, and its increasing political and economic dependence on energy imports and exports is becoming increasingly evident. The 2016 Venice Biennale was the first to incorporate biennials as an integral part of its exhibitionary structure. In this context, the 2016 edition of the Biennale in NYC may well be the last to</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘pale imitation of the stature and grandeur of ancient empires and cultures’. Drawing on the research of his research team, he speaks of the ancient origins of the biennial and its positioning in the art museum. After noting that the image of an elephant in the exhibit is often used as an example of an ancient culture, ‘anodyne’, he suggests that the animal is often used in an image of a cultural form: ‘anodyne’, he says, ‘shows the un-modernisation of contemporary art’.[62]He then describes the anthropologist Michael Parkinson’s book Animal Memoirs, published in 1976, in which ‘aesthetics in general, and animal memories in particular, play a part in human culture’. ‘The appeal of the animal is not merely aesthetic: its significance and intrinsic appeal are cultural, ‘inherent in its relationship to humans’. ‘The appeal</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘pale imitation of the forms and processes of cultural organisation that were once the dominant forms in Asia, Africa and the Middle East’. It is a ‘snapshot’ of a cultural organisation that has ceased to be, or, as the writer David Harvey puts it, to cease to be ‘an image of the past’. But it is also a ‘snapshot’ of a world that is continually changing. How can art be taken back, as Harvey proposes, from the past into the future, while remaining an image of the past? How does art create a space for such radical imaginaries to exist in the present, while remaining grounded in the present and the here and now? Harvey’s radical proposition is supplemented by biennials themselves, institutions like the Venice Biennale which feed the spectacle of change through the production of ‘past exhibits’, and their periodic recurrence across Europe and North America. Harvey, however, is</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘prelude’ to a ‘prologue’. The exhibition is divided into two parts: the initial presentation of the work in the exhibition space, and the ‘presentation’ of the work on a site-specific basis. The first part, ‘presentation’, takes place on the first Saturday of every month (1st September, 2014). The ‘presentation’ is a ‘snapshot’ of the article, while the other, ‘presentation’, takes place on the following Saturday. The exhibition ‘integrates’ the texts with artefacts and historical documents of the exhibition ‘as a whole’. In the exhibition ‘presentation’, the author is placed in the context of the history of art photography in a city. Part of the exhibition is devoted to the book ‘Photocultures of Art’ by Peter Osborne, which documents the life of Ben</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data is generated and published online, and the exhibition and its contents are a constant companion on the internet. The biennial, by contrast, organises its viewing public around a defined set of permanent exhibitionary spaces. Its mission statement reads more like a marketing document for a type of permanent art gallery (Picture: Getty)More from the Life of the Art Biennial, 2013, via History of Art: Penetrating the Biennial – Inside the Biennial – 2.     Venice, Italy: Biennales in Venetian and Pan European Art History, 2013. Drawing directly on the Biennale archive from which the exhibition was produced, this exhibition ‘investigates a particular moment in art history’. It presents a ‘snapshot’ of that ‘moment’ – a photograph of the exhibition – ‘by any means necessary’. It also looks to the past – placing the present within the larger historical context of a ‘pale imitation of the past’. By doing so, the exhibition reproduces the effects of a moment in the past, but with the added effect of placing the present within the larger historical context of a given city. The exhibition is essentially an interrogation of a given space, placing its transformation within the larger dynamic of a city. The name ‘Venice Biennale’ derives from the fact that the Biennale was initially held in Venice, and later in Bakery Square, the site of the Biennale's first opening. This is significant, because Venice is the location for much of the Biennale’s business, entertainment and political functions. It is, in fact, the site of the Biennale’s second opening on 4 September, 2014.3.     History of Art, 1st series, 2012, p.112. Drawing directly on this archive, the exhibition ‘Origins of the Biennale�</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
